<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy: Unification of German
                    States</title>
                <title type="short">Unification of German States</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison and Linsday Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States announced its independence from Great Britain in
                        1776, Central Europe was a fragmented area of roughly 300 sovereign,
                        independent states (kingdoms, duchies, principalities, free cities, etc.).
                        The German states were bound together in a loose political entity known as
                        the Holy Roman Empire, which dated to the era of <persName>Charlemagne</persName> in the 800s. By
                        the late eighteenth century, the Holy Roman Empire was, as Voltaire
                        remarked, <quote>“Neither holy, nor Roman, nor an Empire.”</quote>
                </p>
                <p>During the mid-eighteenth century, a rivalry developed between the Holy
                        Roman Empire’s two largest (and strongest) states: the Kingdom of Austria,
                        ruled by the Habsburgs, and the Kingdom of Prussia, ruled by the
                        Hohenzollerns. Traditionally Austria was the dominant German state, and as
                        such the Habsburg king was elected as the Holy Roman Emperor. This influence
                        started to change in the 1740s when Prussia, strengthened by newly acquired
                        lands and an enlarged military, began to challenge Austria’s hegemony. The
                        Kingdom of Prussia was the first German state to officially recognize the
                        United States in 1785 when it signed a Treaty of Amity and Commerce; Austria
                        did not recognize the United States until 1797, when it accepted <persName>Conrad
                            Frederick Wagner</persName> as U.S. Consul at <placeName key="trieste">Trieste</placeName>, a city then under the
                        jurisdiction of the Habsburg Empire.</p>
                <p>During the early nineteenth century, <persName>Napoleon</persName>’s armies occupied, moved
                        through, or were allied with the German states. In 1806 the Holy Roman
                        Empire was dissolved, and when the Congress of Vienna met in 1814-15, a
                        major question was what to do with Central Europe. The solution was to
                        consolidate the German states and to create the German Confederation, a
                        conglomeration of 39 states, including Austria and Prussia. The members of
                        the German Confederation pledged to come to the aid of any member who was
                        attacked by a foreign power; however, the confederation fell short of any
                        economic or national unity. The first effort at striking some form of
                        economic unification between the members of the German Confederation came
                        with the 1834 establishment of the Zollverein customs union. </p>
                <p>In the meantime, the effects of the First Industrial Revolution (1750-1850)
                        began to take hold in Central Europe and North America. During this time
                        there was increased emigration by Germans to the United States in search of
                        greater economic opportunities as well as political, religious, and personal
                        freedom. The combination of these two events propelled the first official
                        acts of recognition between the United States and various smaller German
                        states as they negotiated and signed treaties, conventions, and agreements
                        to regulate trade, commerce, navigation, naturalization, and inheritance
                        rights. In a few cases, the United States established diplomatic relations,
                        such as with the Hanseatic League (the Free Cities of Lübeck, Bremen, and
                        Hamburg) and the Kingdom of Baden. </p>
                <p>The main issue that confronted the idea of German unification by the
                        mid-nineteenth century was the idea of a “greater” Germany versus a “smaller”
                        Germany. The concept of a “smaller” Germany was that a unified German entity
                        should exclude Austria, while the idea of “greater" Germany was that Germany
                        should include the Kingdom of Austria. Proponents of “smaller” Germany argued
                        that Austria’s inclusion would only cause difficulties for German policy, as the
                        Kingdom of Austria was part of the greater Austrian Empire, which included large
                        swaths of land in Central and Southeastern Europe that was composed of nearly 15
                        different minorities. Those who favored “greater” Germany pointed to the
                        traditional role played by Austria, which was mostly composed of Germans, and
                        the Habsburg rulers in German affairs.</p>
                <p>The first effort at unifying the German states came in the revolutionary
                        year 1848. Once news of the February 1848 revolution in Paris spread, many
                        felt that the time was finally at hand for German unification. Rural riots
                        broke out in the weeks after February 1848 and spread to the urban areas.
                        Throughout the German states revolutionaries advocated for freedom of the
                        press, a national militia, a national German parliament, and trial by jury.
                        Other ideas that were championed during the heady days of 1848 were the
                        abolition of privilege of the aristocracy, the creation of constitutions in
                        several of the German states, a more fair system of taxation, and freedom of
                        religion. </p>
                <p>On May 18, 1848, the German National Assembly met at <placeName key="frankfurt">Frankfurt</placeName> am Main,
                        representing the first assembly to be freely elected by the German people.
                        Yet, despite the election of an imperial vice regent (<hi rend="italic">Reichsverweser</hi>), the
                        government was flawed from the beginning by its lack of a strong executive
                        power. By the autumn of 1849 the revolution disintegrated and hope of fully
                        unifying the German states was extinguished for the time being. </p>
                <p>The next attempt at German unification, a successful one, was undertaken by
                        <persName>Otto von Bismarc</persName>k, the Prime Minister of Prussia. Bismarck was a proponent
                    of “smaller” Germany, not to mention a master at the game of real-politik.
                        German unification was achieved by the force of Prussia, and enforced from
                        the top-down, meaning that it was not an organic movement that was fully
                        supported and spread by the popular classes but instead was a product of
                        Prussian royal policies. </p>
                <p>The first war of German unification was the 1862 Danish War, begun over the
                        duchies of Schleswig and Holstein. Bismarck allied with Austria to fight the
                        Danes in a war to protect the interests of Holstein, a member of the German
                        Confederation. </p>
                <p>The second war of German unification was the 1866 Austro-Prussian War, which
                    settled the question of “smaller” versus “greater” Germany. This brief war
                    (fought over the course of mere weeks) pitted Prussia and her allies against
                    Austria and other German states. Prussia won and directly annexed some of the
                    German states that had sided with Austria (such as Hanover and Nassau). In an
                    act of leniency, Prussia allowed some of the larger Austrian allies to maintain
                    their independence, such as Baden and Bavaria. In 1867 Bismarck created the
                    North German Confederation, a union of the northern German states under the
                    hegemony of Prussia. Several other German states joined, and the North German
                    Confederation served as a model for the future German Empire.</p>
                <p>The third and final act of German unification was the Franco-Prussian War of
                        1870-71, orchestrated by Bismarck to draw the western German states into
                        alliance with the North German Confederation. With the French defeat, the
                        German Empire was proclaimed in January 1871 in the Palace at Versailles,
                        France. From this point forward, foreign policy of the German Empire was
                        made in Berlin, with the German Kaiser (who was also the King of Prussia)
                        accrediting ambassadors of foreign nations. Relations were severed when the
                        U.S. declared war upon Imperial Germany in 1917.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="major-events">
                <head>Major Events </head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States’ Recognition of the Federal German Republic, <date when="1848">1848</date>.</head>
                    <p>On July 8, 1848, Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/clayton-john-middleton">John M. Middleto</ref>n informed U.S.
                            Minister to Prussia <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/donelson-andrew-jackson">Andrew J. Donelson</ref>, that the United States was
                            prepared to recognize any unified, de facto German Government that
                            <quote>“appeared capable of maintaining its power.”</quote> On August 9, 1848, Donelson
                            was appointed as U.S. Minister to the German Federal Parliament at
                            Frankfurt, and presented his credentials on September 13, 1848. However,
                            the failure of this first experiment of German unification led to the
                            U.S. recalling Donelson from service to the Federal German Republic on
                            November 2, 1849. Donelson resumed his previous appointment as U.S.
                            Minister to Prussia.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States’ Recognition of the North German Union, <date when="1867">1867</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following the establishment of the North German Confederation on July 1,
                            1867, on November 20, 1867, the U.S. Minister to Prussia, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/bancroft-george">George
                                Bancroft</ref>, informed Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William H. Seward</ref> that he had
                            attended the opening of the North German Parliament. He requested,
                            however, that the Secretary formally notify him of the intentions of the
                            U.S. Government concerning the question of the recognition of the North
                            German Confederation. On December 9, 1867, Secretary Seward approved of
                            Bancroft’s decision to attend the opening of the North German Parliament
                            since he was the officially-accredited U.S. Minister to the Prussian
                            <persName>King Wilhelm I</persName>, who was also the hereditary President of the North
                            German Confederation. Furthermore, Seward informed Bancroft that he
                            would disseminate a description of the Confederation’s flag so that its
                            ships would be welcomed in American waters. This exchange between Seward
                            and Bancroft implicitly signified a formal recognition of the North
                            German Confederation by the United States. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States’ Recognition of the German Empire and Establishment of
                            Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1871">1871</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following the establishment of the German Empire on January 18, 1871,
                            the United States recognized the new German Empire by changing the
                            accreditation of its Minister to Prussia to become Minister to the
                            German Empire. On April 8, 1871, U.S. Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                            Plenipotentiary to Prussia George Bancroft presented the new German
                            Emperor Wilhelm I (who was concurrently King of Prussia) with a letter
                            from U.S. President <persName>Ulysses S. Grant</persName> dated March 16, 1871. The letter
                            from the President congratulated the Emperor on his assumption of the
                            German throne and recognized him as the head-of-state of a federal
                            Germany.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Termination of Relations During the First World War, <date when="1917">1917</date>.</head>
                    <p>Germany’s resumption of unrestricted submarine warfare in early 1917 led
                            to the termination of diplomatic relations between Imperial Germany and
                            the United States. On February 3, 1917, U.S. Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Robert
                            Lansing</ref> informed the German Ambassador in Washington, D.C., <persName>Count Johann
                            von Bernstorf</persName>f, that U.S. President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> had severed
                            diplomatic relations with Germany, that the U.S. Ambassador in Berlin
                            (<persName>James W. Gerrard</persName>) had been withdrawn, and that the U.S. Government
                            would be returning von Bernstorff’s passports.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Declaration of War Against Imperial Germany, <date when="1917">1917</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following a series of attacks against American merchant ships on the
                            high seas by German U-boats, on February, 24, 1917, the U.S. Ambassador
                            in London, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/page-walter-hines">Walter Hines Pages</ref>, received the infamous <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/WWI">“Zimmerman
                            telegram”</ref> from British Foreign
                            Secretary <persName>Arthur Balfour</persName>. This led to the decision to abandon the plan
                            to adopt “armed neutrality” by placing U.S. naval personnel on civilian
                            ships to guard them against German attacks. On April 2, U.S. President
                            Wilson went before Congress to ask for a declaration of war against
                            Germany in order to make the world “safe for democracy.” Following the
                            passage of a Joint Resolution by Congress on April 6, President Wilson
                            issued on the same day a proclamation to the effect that a state of war
                            existed between Germany and the United States.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="impact">
                <head>Overall Impact upon U.S. Foreign Policy </head>
                <p>The history of the establishment of recognitions (and relations, where
                        applicable) between the United States and the German states impacted several
                        different areas of policy, including:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Trade and Commerce.</hi> Although the Napoleonic period stunted the growth of
                        industrialization in the German states during the early nineteenth century,
                        by the 1820s and 1830s the industrialization process was underway,
                        especially in areas such as Westphalia, the Rhineland, and Upper Silesia. It
                        was also during this time that the first railways were built in the German
                        lands, thus facilitating the transportation of goods to and from the main
                        ports of Hamburg and Bremen. As a result, the German states (and after 1871,
                        the German Empire) and the United States both sought to cultivate trade and
                        commercial ties for mutual benefit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Emigration, Citizenship, and Naturalization.</hi> In the nineteenth century, most
                        German states (and later, the German Empire) had mandatory military service
                        for all male subjects/citizens, whereas the United States did not have any
                        such policy. One point of contention between the U.S. and some of the German
                        states was whether German citizens were emigrating to the U.S. to obtain
                        citizenship and then return to Central Europe and thus eschew military
                        service. In 1868 U.S. Minister to Prussia and the North German Union George
                        Bancroft negotiated a series of naturalization treaties that sought to close
                        this loophole. See Bancroft Treaties for further information. </p>
                <p>After the creation of the Second Reich in 1871 there were questions as to
                        whether U.S. officials should abide by treaties concluded with individual
                        states or with Prussia (the German Empire was considered the successor state
                        to Prussia) in dealing with issues of trade, citizenship, or extradition.
                        Two major principles guided U.S. foreign policy towards the German states.
                        First, <quote>“where a State has lost its separate existence, as in the case of
                        Hanover and Nassau, no questions can arise.”</quote> Second, <quote>“where no treaty has
                        been negotiated with the Empire, the treaties with the various States which
                        have preserved a separate existence have been resorted to.”</quote>
                </p>
                <p>Although the Constitution of the German Empire of 1871 stipulated that the
                        Empire was responsible for treaties, alliances, and representing the Empire,
                        the smaller states still retained the right of legation. This included the
                        right to legislate, to grant exequators to foreign consuls in their
                        territories (though not to send German consuls abroad), and to enter into
                        conventions with foreign nations as long as they did not concern matters
                        already within the jurisdiction of the Empire or the Emperor. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>