<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy: Unification of
                    Italian States</title>
                <title type="short">Unification of Italian States</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison and Linsday Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>For many centuries, the Italian peninsula was a politically fragmented
                    conglomeration of states. This was the case when the United States announced its
                    independence from Great Britain in 1776. When war broke out between Austria and
                    the Revolutionary French Government in 1792, the French invaded the Italian
                    peninsula, consolidated many of the Italian states, and established them as
                    republics. In 1799 the Austrian and Russian armies pushed the French out of the
                    Italian peninsula, which led to the demise of the fledgling republics. </p>
                <p> After Napoleon’s rise to power, the Italian peninsula was once again conquered
                    by the French. Under Napoleon, the peninsula was divided into three entities:
                    the northern parts which were annexed to the French Empire (Piedmont, Liguria,
                    Parma, Piacenza, Tuscany, and Rome), the newly created Kingdom of Italy
                    (Lombardy, Venice, Reggio, Modena, Romagna, and the Marshes) ruled by Napoleon
                    himself, and the Kingdom of Naples, which was first ruled by Napoleon’s brother
                    Joseph Bonaparte, but then passed to Napoleon’s brother-in-law Joachim Murat. </p>
                <p> The period of French invasion and occupation was important in many ways. It
                    introduced revolutionary ideas about government and society, resulting in an
                    overthrow of the old established ruling orders and the destruction of the last
                    vestiges of feudalism. The ideals of freedom and equality were very influential.
                    Also of consequence, the concept of nationalism was introduced, thus sowing the
                    seeds of Italian nationalism throughout most parts of the northern and central
                    Italian peninsula. </p>
                <p> With the downfall of Napoleon in 1814 and the redistribution of territory by the
                    Congress of Vienna (1814-15), most of the Italian states were reconstituted: the
                    Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia (often referred to as Sardinia), the Grand Duchy of
                    Tuscany, the Duchy of Parma, the Papal States, and the Kingdom of the Two
                    Sicilies (fused together from the old Kingdom of Naples and Kingdom of Sicily).
                    These were largely conservative regimes, presided over by the old social orders. </p>
                <p> Although the Italian peninsula remained fragmented through the mid-1800s, the
                    concept of a united Italy began to take root. Secret societies formed to oppose
                    the conservative regimes. Several of these societies also promoted Italian
                    nationalism and the idea of a unified Italian political state. One such society
                    was the group Young Italy, founded in 1831 by Guiseppe Mazzini. Mazzini was an
                    ardent advocate of the necessity for Italian unification through the desires and
                    actions of the Italian people. Thus, the movement of Italian unification, a
                    process referred to as the Risorgimento (resurgence) proliferated by
                    mid-century. </p>
                <p> The revolutions of 1848 ignited nationalist sentiment throughout the Italian
                    peninsula. There were widespread uprisings in several Italian cities that year,
                    mostly by the professional classes (such as doctors, lawyers, shopkeepers) as
                    well as students. Lombardy-Venetia and Milan tried to rise up against Austrian
                    rule. Although the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia sent troops to aid the revolt,
                    it was crushed by the Austrians at Custoza in July 1848. The Italian uprisings
                    were unsuccessful and by 1849 the old regimes were once again in place. </p>
                <p> Yet, the idea of the Risorgimento continued to gain adherents after 1848. The
                    final push for Italian unification came in 1859, led by the Kingdom of
                    Piedmont-Sardinia (then the wealthiest and most liberal of the Italian states),
                    and orchestrated by Piedmont-Sardinia’s Prime Minister, Count Camillo di Cavour.
                    A skilled diplomat, Cavour secured an alliance with France. The Franco-Austrian
                    War of 1859 was the agent that began the physical process of Italian
                    unification. The Austrians were defeated by the French and Piedmontese at
                    Magenta and Solferino, and thus relinquished Lombardy. By the end of the year
                    Lombardy was added to the holdings of Piedmont-Sardinia. </p>
                <p> The northern Italian states held elections in 1859 and 1860 and voted to join
                    the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia, a major step towards unification, while
                    Piedmont-Sardinia ceded Savoy and Nice to France. Giuseppi Garibaldi, a native
                    of Piedmont-Sardinia, was instrumental in bringing the southern Italian states
                    into the unification process. In 1860, Garibaldi cobbled together an army
                    (referred to as the “Thousand”) to march into the southern part of the
                    peninsula. Landing first in Sicily and then moving onwards into Naples,
                    Garibaldi and his men overthrew the Bourbon monarchy and turned over the
                    southern territories to Victor Emmanuel II, King of Piedmont-Sardinia. In early
                    1861 a national parliament convened and proclaimed the Kingdom of Italy, with
                    Victor Emmanuel II as its king. At this point, there were only two major
                    territories outside of the parameters of the new Kingdom of Italy: Rome and
                    Venetia. </p>
                <p> In 1866 Italy joined Prussia in a campaign against Austria (the 1866
                    Austro-Prussian War) and thus won Venetia. In 1870, taking advantage of the fact
                    that France (the country responsible at the time for guarding the Papal States)
                    was distracted by involvement in the Franco-Prussian War (1870-71), the Italian
                    army entered Rome. That year, Rome and the Papal States were incorporated into
                    Italy and the Risorgimento completed. During the summer of 1871, the Italian
                    capital moved to Rome from Florence (it was moved from Turin to Florence in
                    1865). </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="major-events">
                <head>Major Events </head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Franco-Austrian War, <date when="1859">1859</date>.</head>
                    <p> After striking an alliance with Napoleon III’s France, Piedmont-Sardinia
                        provoked Austria to declare war in 1859, thus launching the conflict that
                        served to unify the northern Italian states together against their common
                        enemy: the Austrian Army. The Austrians suffered military defeats at Magenta
                        and Solferino, and a ceasefire was agreed to at Villafranca. In the peace
                        negotiations, Austria ceded Lombardy to France, which then ceded it to
                        Piedmont-Sardinia. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Proclamation of the Kingdom of Italy, <date when="1861">1861</date>.</head>
                    <p> The aftermath of the Franco-Austrian War brought about a series of
                        plebiscites in the northern Italian states. By going to the ballot box, the
                        states voted to join Piedmont-Sardinia, with the ultimate goal of unifying
                        the entire peninsula. It should be noted that Piedmont-Sardinia was one of
                        the more powerful states in the peninsula, as well as having one of the most
                        liberal political systems. Garibaldi’s march to “liberate” the Kingdom of
                        the Two Sicilies in 1860 brought the southern peninsula into the fold, and
                        the new Kingdom of Italy was proclaimed on March 17, 1861, with the royal
                        family of Piedmont-Sardinia as the new ruling monarchs of Italy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Italian Independence, <date when="1861">1861</date>.</head>
                    <p> The United States officially recognized the Kingdom of Italy when it
                        accepted the credentials of Chevalier Joseph Bertinatti as Minister
                        Plenipotentiary of the Kingdom of Italy on April 11, 1861.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Addition of Venetia, <date when="1866">1866</date>. </head>
                    <p> The Kingdom of Italy added Venetia to its holdings in 1866 following the
                        Austrian defeat in the 1866 Austro-Prussian War.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Incorporation of Rome, <date when="1870">1870</date>.</head>
                    <p> French troops were the main barrier to Italian occupation of the Papal
                        States after 1867; however, when Prussia declared war upon France in the
                        summer of 1870, the Italians took advantage of the situation. With French
                        resources allocated to the struggle of the Franco-Prussian War (1870-71),
                        Napoleon III ordered his troops out of the Italian peninsula. The Italians
                        entered the Papal States in September 1870 and, through the backing of a
                        plebiscite held in early October, annexed the Papal States and Rome to the
                        Kingdom of Italy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Legation to the Kingdom of Italy moves to Florence and then Rome,
                            <date from="1865" to="1871">1865-71</date>.</head>
                    <p> When the Kingdom of Italy moved its seat of government from Turin to
                        Florence in 1865, the U.S. Legation followed. During the summer of 1871, the
                        Italian capital moved from Florence to Rome, reflecting the completion of
                        unification. George P. Marsh, as U.S. Minister Plenipotentiary, oversaw the
                        move of the U.S. Legation from Turin to Florence in 1865 and from Florence
                        to Rome in 1871.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="impact">
                <head>Overall Impact upon U.S. Foreign Policy </head>
                <p>The history of recognitions (and the establishment of relations, where
                    applicable) between the United States and the Italian states impacted several
                    different areas of U.S. policy, including: </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Trade and Commerce.</hi> The industrialization process that
                    swept through the northern United States in the early nineteenth century spread
                    through the northern and central Italian states in the mid-nineteenth century.
                    As a result, the Italian states (and after 1861, the Kingdom of Italy) and the
                    United States both sought to cultivate trade and commercial ties for mutual
                    benefit. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Immigration and Citizenship.</hi> By the 1870s Italian
                    immigration to the New World (both to the United States as well as to Argentina,
                    amongst other South American countries) began to increase. Indeed, some of the
                    “fathers” of modern Italy spent time in the United States. Garibaldi spent
                    enough time in the U.S. to gain a U.S. passport, and was offered a commission in
                    the U.S. Army during the Civil War. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong"> U.S. Civil War.</hi> The unification of the Italian states
                    impacted the foreign policy of the United States in numerous ways. Perhaps the
                    issue that had the most immediate impact upon U.S. foreign policy in the early
                    1860s was over the question of recognition of the U.S. Confederacy. The Kingdom
                    of Italy was proclaimed just as the U.S. Civil War began. U.S. President Abraham
                    Lincoln wanted to ensure that the new Italian state did not recognize the U.S.
                    Confederacy. Washington also worried that, with Italy’s long coastline,
                    Confederate ships might seek shelter in Italian waters. With this in mind, the
                    Italian government gave “strong assurances that no Confederate ship would be
                    admitted to Italian ports unless it was a question of adverse weather conditions
                    or other vis major.” </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>