<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Albania</title>
                <title type="short">Albania</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Emily Horne, January 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>U.S.-Albanian diplomatic relations, first established in 1922, were interrupted
                    when <placeName>Italy</placeName> took control of <placeName key="al"
                        >Albania</placeName>’s foreign affairs in 1939. After Italy’s defeat in
                    World War II, an informal US mission was sent to Albania in 1945 to study the
                    possibility of reestablishing relations with the National Liberation Front
                        (<abbr>NLF</abbr>) regime; however, disagreements led the United States to
                    withdraw the mission in November 1946. Following World War II, Albania under
                    Communist ruler <persName>Enver Hoxha</persName> was one of the most
                    diplomatically isolated nations in the world. After Hoxha’s death and subsequent
                    liberal political and social reforms, Albania and the United States
                    reestablished diplomatic relations. Albania received an invitation to join <ref
                        target="/milestones/1945-1952/nato">NATO</ref> in April 2008 and is expected
                    to become a full member in 2009. <figure>
                        <graphic url="albania-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Albania</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1922">1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>In a July 25, 1922 telegram Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hughes-charles-evans">Charles Evans
                            Hughes</ref> informed the American Commissioner in Albania, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/blake-maxwell">Maxwell Blake</ref>,
                        that on July 28, 1922 Blake <quote>“may extend to the Minister of Foreign
                            Affairs of Albania written notification of the de jure recognition of
                            Albania by the United States.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1922">1922.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on December 4, 1922, when Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/grant-smith-ulysses">Ulysses
                            Grant-Smith </ref> presented credentials to the government of Albania in
                            <placeName key="tirana">Tirana</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Ended and American Legation Closed, <date when="1939"
                            >1939.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Italian forces invaded Albania in 1939 and occupied <placeName key="tirana"
                            >Tirana</placeName> on April 8, 1939. U.S.-Albanian diplomatic relations
                        ended on June 5, 1939, when Albanian Minister for Foreign Affairs notified
                        the American Minister in Albania that Italy had taken control of Albania’s
                        foreign affairs. Legation Tirana was officially closed on September 16,
                        1939.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Reestablished, <date when="1991">1991.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The United States and Albania resumed diplomatic relations on March 15, 1991,
                        when Albanian Foreign Minister <persName>Muhamet Kapllani</persName> and
                        Assistant Secretary <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/seitz-raymond-george-hardenbergh"
                            >Raymond Seitz</ref> signed a Memorandum of Understanding in
                        Washington.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Most-Favored-Nation Status, <date when="1922"
                            >1922.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Prior to mutual official recognition, American Commissioner Maxwell Blake
                        exchanged notes with Albanian President of the Council and Minister of
                        Foreign Affairs <persName>Djafer Upi</persName> to ensure mutual
                        most-favored-nation status in future commercial treaties between Albania and
                        the United States.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Relief Assistance, <date when="1945">1945.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Following the expulsion of Italian and German occupying troops by Albanian
                        nationalist groups, the United States signed a treaty with the Albanian
                        military authority promising relief supplies via military operation.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl> Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-albania/">Albania</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/albania/">Albania</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> CIA World Factbook: <ref
                            target="https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/al.html"
                            >Albania</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Country Study: <ref
                            target="http://memory.loc.gov/frd/cs/altoc.html">Albania</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
