<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Andorra</title>
                <title type="short">Andorra</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Emily Horne, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The Principality of <placeName key="ad">Andorra</placeName> is a co-principality,
                    with the Bishop of Urgell (<placeName>Spain</placeName>) serving as one of its
                    co-princes and the French president serving as the other. The governing
                    arrangement dates back centuries and helps to explain why, in conjunction with
                    its geographic location, Andorra has traditionally been isolated from European
                    and international affairs. This began to change, however, with the ratification
                    of its constitution in 1993, which established Andorra’s sovereignty as a
                    “modern” representative democracy.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="andorran-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Andorra</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Since then the principality has become progressively more active within the
                    international community. The United States and Andorra established diplomatic
                    relations in 1995. All Ambassadors to Andorra have also been accredited to Spain
                    and resident in <placeName>Madrid</placeName>. United States Consulate General
                    Officials based in Barcelona are responsible for day-to-day conduct of relations
                    with Andorra.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Andorra</head>
                    <p>Andorra has considered itself independent since medieval times, and therefore
                        was already independent when the United States declared independence from
                        the British Empire in 1776. Unlike many other independent states in the late
                        eighteenth century, Andorra never signed a bilateral treaty with the United
                        States, which would have legally constituted recognition of the new
                        republic.</p>
                    <p>Andorra ratified a modern constitution on March 14, 1993, which provided for
                        its independence and sovereignty as a “modern” representative democracy.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1995"
                        >1995</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established diplomatic relations with Andorra on February
                        21, 1995, with an exchange of letters between the Andorran government
                        (requesting to establish full diplomatic relations) and the U.S. Secretary
                        of State. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/christopher-warren-minor">Warren
                            Christopher</ref> reciprocated by appointing the U.S. Consul General in
                            <placeName>Barcelona</placeName> to also represent the United States to
                        Andorra for diplomatic and consular affairs.</p>
                    <p>The first U.S. Ambassador to Andorra, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/romero-edward-l">Edward L.
                            Romero</ref>, presented his credentials on October 30, 1998. All
                        Ambassadors to Andorra have also been accredited to
                            <placeName>Spain</placeName> and resident in
                            <placeName>Madrid</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Andorran Embassy, <date when="1996">1996</date>.</head>
                    <p>On February 6, 1996, <persName>Juli F. Minoves-Triquell</persName> presented
                        credentials as Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary to the United
                        States. Ambassador Minoves-Triquell, at 26 years old, was the youngest
                        ambassador on record to represent a foreign country at the time and was also
                        accredited to the <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945/un">United
                            Nations</ref>. The Andorran mission to the United Nations serves as the
                        Andorran Embassy in the United States.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl> Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-andorra/">Andorra</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/andorra/">Andorra</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> CIA World Factbook: <ref
                            target="https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/an.html"
                            >Andorra</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
