<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Angola</title>
                <title type="short">Angola</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Emily Horne, March 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The Portuguese first landed in what is today northern <placeName key="ao"
                        >Angola</placeName> in 1482, encountering the Kingdom of the Congo
                    stretching from modern-day Gabon in the north to the Kwanza River in the south.
                    The Portuguese gradually took control of the coastal area by a series of
                    treaties and wars throughout the 16th century, and their interest in Angola
                    quickly turned to the slave trade. Many scholars agree that by the 19th century,
                    Angola was the largest source of slaves for the Americas. Portugal eventually
                    secured administrative control over the interior in the beginning of the 20th
                    century.</p>
                <p>As post-World War II decolonization progressed elsewhere in Africa, Portugal
                    continued to treat its African colonies as overseas provinces. Consequently,
                    three Angolan independence movements emerged. A 1974 military coup d’etat in
                    Portugal established a military government that agreed, in the Alvor Accords, to
                    hand power to a coalition of the three movements. Ideological clashes led to
                    armed conflict between the movements, with the Eastern Bloc-backed Popular
                    Movement for the Liberation of Angola (MPLA) eventually taking power when the
                    Portuguese abandoned the capitol city Luanda in 1975. Angola remained aligned
                    with the Soviet Union and Cuba for the duration of the Cold War. <figure>
                        <graphic url="angolan-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Angola</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Response to Angolan Independence, <date when="1975"
                        >1975</date>.</head>
                    <p>Portugal granted Angola independence on <date when="1975-11-11">November 11,
                            1975</date>, at a time when multiple Angolan nationalist forces were
                        fighting among themselves to establish control over the newly liberated
                        state. Although the United States acknowledged the independence of the
                        former Portuguese colony, the U.S. Government (like Portugal itself) did not
                        recognize the Government of Angola declared by the <abbr>MPLA</abbr>. The
                        United States continued to withhold recognition of a Government of Angola
                        because of continuing concerns about the presence of Cuban combat troops in
                        Angola and their involvement in regional conflicts. After years of civil
                        war, Angola held its first multiparty elections in 1992. The elected
                        government agreed to sign a peace agreement with <abbr>UNITA</abbr>, the
                        party that had been in power prior to the election. In response, U.S.
                        President <persName>Bill Clinton</persName> formally recognized the new
                        Government of Angola on <date when="1993-05-19">May 19, 1993</date>, using
                        his announcement to urge UNITA to accept a negotiated settlement.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Liaison Office Established at Luanda, <date when="1992">1992.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The U.S. Liaison Office in <placeName key="luanda">Luanda</placeName> was
                        opened <date when="1992-01-10">January 10, 1992</date>, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/millington-jeffrey">Jeffrey
                            Millington</ref> as Director.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in Angola,
                            <date when="1994">1994.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on July 14, 1994, when American
                        Ambassador <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/dejarnette-edmund-t"
                            >Edmund T. De Jarnette</ref> presented his credentials to Angolan
                        authorities.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/6619.htm">Angola</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/p/af/ci/ao/index.htm">Angola</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
