<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Argentina</title>
                <title type="short">Argentina</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, March 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>After <placeName key="ar">Argentina</placeName> gained independence from the
                    Spanish in 1816, the nation was paralyzed by tension between Centralist and
                    Federalist forces. In 1854 the Federalist provinces ratified a constitution that
                    established the Argentine Confederation, which Centralists in <placeName>Buenos
                        Aires</placeName> repudiated while declaring themselves independent.
                    Resistance forces expelled a brief Federalist incursion into Buenos Aires and
                    the Confederation collapsed in 1861, paving way for the national rule under the
                    Argentine Republic that same year.<figure>
                        <graphic url="argentinian-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Argentina</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States Recognition of Buenos Ayres, <date when="1823"
                        >1823</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Government of Buenos Ayres (predecessor of
                        Argentina) on January 27, 1823, when <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/rodney-caesar-augustus">Caesar
                            Rodney</ref> was appointed as American Minister Plenipotentiary to that
                        government. <placeName key="buenos-aries">Buenos Ayres</placeName> had
                        declared independence from <placeName>Spain</placeName> on <date
                            when="1816-07-09">July 9, 1816</date>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Mission in Buenos
                        Ayres, <date when="1823">1823.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on December 27, 1823, when American
                        Minister Plenipotentiary <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/rodney-caesar-augustus">Caesar
                            Rodney</ref> presented his credentials to the Government of Buenos
                        Ayres.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Mission Moved to Parana, <date when="1857">1857.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/peden-james-a">James A. Peden</ref>
                        was commissioned as Chargé d’Affaires to the Republic of Buenos Aires on May
                        22, 1854 but did not proceed to post in that capacity. Soon after Peden was
                        nominated as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to the
                        Argentine Confederation, eventually receiving a commission in 1856 with
                        letters of credence to both Buenos Aires and the Confederation. Peden
                        resided at <placeName key="buenos-aires">Buenos Aires</placeName> until
                        about May 1, 1857, when he closed the Legation at that city and moved to
                            <placeName key="parana">Parana</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Mission Returned to Buenos Aires, <date when="1862">1862.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Following the collapse of the Argentine Confederation and national
                        reunification as the Argentine Republic, Peden returned the U.S. Legation to
                            <placeName key="buenos-aires">Buenos Aires</placeName> on February 25,
                        1862.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Interrupted, <date when="1944">1944.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>After a 1942 military coup, General <persName>Pedro Ramirez</persName>
                        assumed power and maintained Argentinean neutrality in World War II, causing
                        the United States to refuse Argentine requests for Lend-Lease aid. Ramirez
                        eventually broke relations with Germany and Japan on January 26, 1944, but
                        resigned in favor of his vice-president, General <persName>Edelmiro
                            Farrell</persName> a few weeks later on February 25, 1944. The United
                        States believed the Farrell regime was <quote>“not in sympathy to the
                            declared Argentine policy of joining the defense of the
                            hemisphere,”</quote> and instructed Ambassador <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/armour-norman">Norman Armour</ref> to
                        refrain from entering official relations with the new government. Armour was
                        instructed to return to Washington on June 27, 1944. <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/reed-leslie-edgar">Edward L.
                            Reed</ref> subsequently became Chargés d’Affaires of the Embassy in
                        Buenos Aires.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Resumed, <date when="1945">1945.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The United States resumed normal diplomatic relations with Argentina and
                        formally recognized the Farrell government on April 19, 1945, according to a
                        State Department notice released that same day. The decision came from a
                        meeting of the Inter-American Conference in <placeName>Mexico
                            City</placeName>, where all the participants agreed to resume relations
                        with Argentina following its declaration of war against the Axis powers.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/26516.htm">Argentina</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/p/wha/ci/ar/index.htm ">Argentina</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
