<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Armenia</title>
                <title type="short">Armenia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, March 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Between the 4th and the 19th centuries Armenia was conquered and ruled by, among
                    others, Persians, Arabs, Byzantines, Mongols and Turks. While Armenia was under
                    Ottoman rule the United States established a consulate in Ezerum, Armenia
                    (present-day Ezurum, Turkey) in 1896. The consulate was transferred to
                    Trebizond, Turkey in 1904.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="armenian-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Armenia</head>
                </figure>
                <p>For a brief period from 1918 to 1920 Armenia became an independent republic. In
                    late 1920, local communists came to power following an invasion of Armenia by
                    the Soviet Red Army, and in 1922, Armenia became part of the Trans-Caucasian
                    Soviet Socialist Republic. In 1936, it became the Armenian Soviet Socialist
                    Republic. The dissolution of the Soviet Union in 1991 created the opportunity
                    for bilateral relations between Armenia and the United States.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of the Armenian Republic, <date when="1920"
                        >1920</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the independence of the Armenian Republic on
                            <date when="1920-04-23">April 23, 1920</date>, when Secretary of State
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/colby-bainbridge">Bainbridge
                            Colby</ref> delivered a note to the Representative of the Armenian
                        Republic (<persName>Pasdermadjian</persName>) in Washington, informing him
                        of President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>’s decision. The note
                        specified that this recognition <quote>“in no way predetermines the
                            territorial frontiers, which…are matters for later
                        delimitation</quote>.” </p>
                    <p>The territory expected to compose the independent Armenian Republic
                        previously had been under the sovereignty of the Ottoman and Russian
                        Empires. At the request of the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Paris Peace
                            Conference’s</ref> Supreme Council of the Allied Powers, President
                        Wilson arbitrated the boundary to be set between Armenia and Turkey, and
                        submitted his determinations to the Supreme Council on November 22, 1920.
                        Prior to Wilson’s decisions, however, the territory expected to compose the
                        Armenian Republic had been attacked by Turkish and Bolshevik troops. By the
                        end of 1920 the Armenian Republic had ceased to exist as an independent
                        state, with its territory either seized by Turkey or established as the
                        Armenian Soviet Republic, which subsequently joined the Soviet Union.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Armenia, <date when="1991">1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Armenia’s independence on December 25, 1991,
                        when President <persName>George H.W. Bush</persName> announced the decision
                        in an address to the nation regarding the dissolution of the Soviet Union.
                        Armenia previously had been a constituent republic of the USSR.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1991"
                        >1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on <date when="1991-12-25">December 25,
                            1991</date>, when President <persName>George H.W. Bush</persName>
                        announced the decision in an address to the nation regarding the dissolution
                        of the <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Embassy in Yerevan, <date when="1992"
                            >1992</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Embassy in <placeName key="yerevan">Yerevan</placeName> was
                        opened on February 3, 1992, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/mann-steven-robert">Steven Mann</ref>
                        as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl> Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5275.htm">Armenia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/am ">Armenia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> CIA World Factbook: <ref
                            target="https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/am.html"
                            >Armenia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Country Study <ref
                            target="http://memory.loc.gov/frd/cs/amtoc.html">Armenia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
