<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Austrian
                    Empire</title>
                <title type="short">Austrian Empire</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, March 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Note: This entry is for the former state, the Austrian Empire.
                        Please <ref target="http://history.state.gov/countries/austria">click
                            here</ref> for information on the modern Republic of Austria.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Austria was the German-speaking heartland of the Holy Roman Empire (until 1806),
                    the Austrian Empire (until 1867), and the Austro-Hungarian Empire (until 1918).
                    Relations between the United States and the Austrian Empire (and subsequently,
                    the Austro-Hungarian Empire) were friendly. An exception was the period 1849-50
                    in the aftermath of Austrian suppression of the 1848 Hungarian revolt. At the
                    time there was widespread sympathy for Hungarian national aspirations and
                    Hungarian exiles were warmly received by the United States. This changed during
                    World War I. After the United States declared war on Germany, Austria-Hungary
                    severed diplomatic relations with the United States on <date when="1917-04-08"
                        >April 8, 1917</date>. The United States did not declare war on
                    Austria-Hungary until December 7, 1917.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Austrian Empire Recognition of the United States, <date when="1797"
                            >1797</date>.</head>
                    <p>Austria recognized the United States in 1797 by accepting <persName>Conrad
                            Frederick Wagner</persName> as U.S. Consul at <placeName key="trieste"
                            >Trieste</placeName>, a city under the jurisdiction of the Habsburg
                        Empire. Unfortunately no correspondence from this earliest appointee has
                        survived. The earliest surviving correspondence is from the second U.S.
                        Consul at Trieste, <persName>John Lamson</persName>, who although appointed
                        on December 24, 1799, did not arrive in Trieste until December 29, 1801. By
                        March 18, 1802, Lamson had received an exchequer from the Habsburg Emperor
                            <persName>Francis I</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Prior to the Empire’s recognition of the United States, Congress commissioned
                            <persName>William Lee</persName> on July 1, 1777, as U.S. representative
                        to <placeName key="vienna">Vienna</placeName>; however, Austria did not
                        officially receive him at that time. One explanation for why Austria did not
                        recognize the United States during the 1780s was that it would have put them
                        in the difficult position of recognizing a country that had rebelled against
                        a monarchy – a dangerous precedent given the internal difficulties posed by
                        unrest in the Habsburg domains (Austrian Netherlands and Hungary) at the
                        time.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="consular_relations">
                    <head>Consular Presence</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>U.S. Consulates in Venice, Trieste, and Vienna, <date from="1797"
                                to="1917">1797-1917</date>, with interruptions.</head>
                        <p>U.S. consuls were appointed to <placeName key="venice">Venice</placeName>
                            and <placeName key="trieste">Triest</placeName>e in 1797. In the case of
                            Venice, the first appointee declined the assignment and was reassigned
                            to Barcelona. There was no record that a second appointee in 1807 ever
                            served. There was no permanent U.S. presence in the Austrian Empire
                            until 1830. Venice first passed into Austrian control as the result of
                            the Treaty of Campo Formio of October 17, 1797, and became part of the
                            Kingdom of Italy in 1866.</p>
                        <p>In the case of Trieste, no dispatches from the earliest appointee have
                            survived. There were consuls serving there between 1801 and 1809, but
                            there was no permanent U.S. presence there until 1816. Trieste was part
                            of the Austrian Empire until its breakup in 1918.</p>
                        <p>A U.S. Consulate was established in Vienna on October 10, 1829. It became
                            a Consulate General on June 17, 1874. It was closed April 9, 1917, after
                            the Austro-Hungarian Empire severed diplomatic relations with the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>Consulates in other parts of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire (i.e.
                            Hungary and the former Czechoslovakia) will be mentioned under the
                            countries in which they are presently located.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in
                                <placeName key="vienna">Vienna</placeName>, <date when="1838"
                                >1838</date>.</head>
                        <p>
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/muhlenberg-henry-augustus-philip"
                                >Henry A. Muhlenberg</ref> was appointed as the first U.S. Minister
                            to Austria on February 8, 1838. He presented his credentials on November
                            7, 1838.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of the Austrian Legation in Washington, <date
                                when="1838">1838</date>.</head>
                        <p>The Austrian Empire’s first Minister to the United States,
                                <persName>Baron de Mareschal</persName>, presented his credentials
                            October 13, 1838.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1902"
                                >1902</date>.</head>
                        <p>U.S. Minister <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/mccormick-robert-sanderson">Robert
                                S. McCormick</ref>, who had been appointed Minister on March 7,
                            1901, was appointed Ambassador on May 27, 1902. He presented his new
                            credentials on June 26, 1902.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Termination of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1917"
                            >1917</date>.</head>
                        <p>On April 8, 1917, Austro-Hungarian Empire severed diplomatic relations
                            with the United States. Several months later, on December 7, 1917, <ref
                                target="/milestones/1914-1920/wwi">the United States declared war
                                upon Austria-Hungary</ref>.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="treaties_agreements">
                    <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <p>On December 20, 1825, Secretary of State <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/clay-henry">Henry Clay</ref>
                            announced that the United States was ready to conclude a commerce and
                            navigation convention with the Austrian Empire. On March 18, 1828,
                            Emperor <persName>Francis I</persName> appointed <persName>Lewis, Baron
                                de Lederer</persName>, the Austrian Consul in New York, to negotiate
                            a treaty. A Treaty of Commerce and Navigation between the United States
                            and Austria was signed in Washington on August 27, 1829, and entered
                            into force February 10, 1831 after the exchange of ratifications.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="appendix">
                    <head>Resources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Bevans, Charles I. <hi rend="italic">Treaties and Other International
                                Agreements of the United States of America, 1776-1949. Volume 5:
                                Afghanistan-Burma.</hi> Department of State Publication 8543,
                            October 1970. </bibl>
                        <bibl> Miller, Hunter. <hi rend="italic">Treaties and Other International
                                Acts of the United States of America: Volume 3, Documents 41-79:
                                1819-35</hi>. Washington: Government Printing Office, 1933. </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
