<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Australia</title>
                <title type="short">Australia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and Written by Kathleen Rasmussen, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>On <date when="1901-01-01">January 1, 1901</date>, six colonies were joined
                    together to create the <placeName key="au">Commonwealth of
                    Australia</placeName>, a self-governing Dominion in the British Empire. While
                    the new nation was sovereign when it came to its domestic affairs, the
                        <placeName>United Kingdom</placeName> maintained control over its relations
                    with the wider world.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="austrialian-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Australia</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Over the next four decades, Australia gradually gained control over its external
                    policy. The Balfour Declaration of 1926, issued at the end of the Imperial
                    Conference held in London that year, recognized that the United Kingdom and the
                    Dominions were <quote>“autonomous Communities within the British Empire, equal
                        in status, in no way subordinate one to another in any aspect of their
                        domestic or external affairs.”</quote>
                </p>
                <p>In December 1931, the United Kingdom approved the Statute of Westminster,
                    codifying this relationship; the statute specified, however, that its provisions
                    would not come into effect until formally adopted by the government of
                    Australia. On October 9, 1942, Australia’s Statute of Westminster Adoption Act
                    became law. The act was made effective retroactive to September 3, 1939, the
                    date of <quote>“the Commencement of the War between His Majesty the King and
                        Germany.”</quote>
                </p>
                <p>The year 2010 marks the 70th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic
                    relations between the United States and Australia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Australian Independence, <date>1940</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Australia on <date when="1940-01-08">January 8,
                            1940</date>, when the Governments of the United States and Australia
                        announced the establishment of bilateral diplomatic relations.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date>1940</date>.</head>
                    <p>On January 8, 1940, the Governments of the United States and Australia
                        announced the establishment of bilateral diplomatic relations.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the Australian Legation in the United States,
                            <date>1940</date>.</head>
                    <p>On March 1, 1940, <persName>Richard Gardiner Casey</persName> presented his
                        credentials as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to the
                        Government of the United States.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Legation in Australia,
                        <date>1940</date>.</head>
                    <p>On July 17, 1940, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/gauss-clarence-edward">Clarence E.
                            Gauss</ref> presented his credentials as Envoy Extraordinary and
                        Minister Plenipotentiary to the Government of Australia.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of Legations to Embassy Status, <date when="1946"
                        >1946</date>.</head>
                    <p>On July 9, 1946, the White House announced the elevation of the Australian
                        and American legations to embassy status. On September 11, 1946,
                            <persName>Norman J. O. Makin</persName> presented his credentials as
                        Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary of Australia to the Government
                        of the United States. On September 25, 1946, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/butler-robert">Robert Butler</ref>
                        presented his credentials as Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary of
                        the United States to the Government of Australia.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>70th Anniversary of Establishment of Diplomatic Relations.</head>
                    <p>The year 2010 marks the 70th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic
                        relations between the United States and Australia.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <!--<bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-australia/">Australia</ref></bibl>-->
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/australia/"
                            >Australia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>CIA World Factbook: <ref
                            target="https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/as.html"
                            >Australia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
