<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Austria (The
                    Republic of)</title>
                <title type="short">Austria</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Evan Duncan, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Note: This entry is for the modern state, the Republic of
                        Austria. Please <ref
                            target="http://history.state.gov/countries/austrian-empire">click
                            here</ref> for information on the Austrian Empire.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">World War I drew to a
                        close</ref>, Austria-Hungary concluded an armistice with the Allied powers
                    on November 3, 1918; several of its minorities (the Czechoslovaks, Yugoslavs,
                    and Hungarians) had already declared their independence. Emperor
                        <persName>Charles I</persName> abdicated on November 12, 1918, and an
                    Austrian Republic was proclaimed on November 13, 1918. Since the post-World War
                    II period, the United States and Austria have enjoyed strong relations. <figure>
                        <graphic url="austria-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Austria</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Austrian Independence, <date when="1921"
                        >1921</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the <placeName key="at">Republic of
                            Austria</placeName> on August 24, 1921, with the signing of a Treaty
                        Establishing Friendly Relations in <placeName key="vienna"
                            >Vienna</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>Austria-Hungary had severed diplomatic relations with the United States on
                        April 8, 1917, after the <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/wwi">United
                            States declared war on Germany</ref>. The United States did not declare
                        war on Austria-Hungary until December 7, 1917. The tenth of President
                            <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>’s <ref
                            target="/milestones/1914-1920/fourteen-points">Fourteen Points</ref>
                        called for free opportunities for the “autonomous development” of the
                        peoples of Austria-Hungary. The United States did not ratify the Treaty of
                        St-Germain (September 10, 1919) which recognized the independence of
                            <placeName>Hungary</placeName>, <placeName>Czechoslovakia</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Yugoslavia</placeName>, and <placeName>Poland</placeName> and
                        formally dissolved the Dual Monarchy. Congress passed a Joint Resolution
                        ending the state of war with Austria-Hungary on July 2, 1921, opening the
                        way for the establishment of relations with the Austrian Republic.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <p>After the Anschluss of 1938 incorporated Austria into Nazi
                            <placeName>Germany</placeName>, the U.S. Legation in <placeName
                            key="vienna">Vienna</placeName> was closed and became a Consulate
                        General. The Vienna Consulate General was closed July 9, 1941, along with
                        all other U.S. consulates in Germany.</p>
                    <p>A U.S. consular post has been intermittently maintained in <placeName
                            key="salzburg">Salzburg</placeName> since World War II. It opened as a
                        Consulate in 1948 and was upgraded to a Consulate General in 1961, only to
                        close in 1963. It reopened in 1973 and closed again in 1980. It reopened as
                        a Consulate General in 1983, became a Consular Agency in 1996, and closed on
                        March 31, 2006.</p>

                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1921">1921.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>A Treaty Establishing Friendly Relations was signed between the Republic of
                        Austria and the United States Government in <placeName key="vienna"
                            >Vienna</placeName> on August 24, 1921. It was proclaimed to be in
                        effect on November 8, 1921.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of American Legation in Austria <date when="1921"
                            >1921.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/frazier-arthur-hugh">Arthur Hugh
                            Frazier</ref> was appointed Chargé d’Affaires to Austria and presented
                        his credentials on November 26, 1921. The first U.S. Minister, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/washburn-albert-henry">Albert Henry
                            Washburn</ref>, was appointed on February 10, 1922, and presented his
                        credentials on June 19, 1922. He served until his death on April 29,
                        1930.</p>
                    <p>The Austrian Republic’s first diplomatic representative in the United States
                        was <persName>Edgar L. G. Prochnik</persName>, who presented his credentials
                        on December 27, 1921. Prochnik was promoted to Minister and presented his
                        new credentials on May 7, 1925.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The Anschluss, Closure of the American Legation in <placeName key="vienna"
                            >Vienna</placeName>, and post-World War II Revival of Austrian
                        Independence, <date from="1936" to="1948">1936-48.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Nazi Germany annexed Austria in March 1938. The senior U.S. representative in
                            <placeName key="vienna">Vienna</placeName> was Chargé d’Affaires <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/wiley-john-cooper">John C. Wiley</ref>
                        (Minister <persName>Grenville T. Emmett</persName> had died September 26,
                        1937). He closed the Legation on April 30, 1938, and it became a Consulate
                        General, a step that Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hull-cordell">Cordell Hull</ref> noted
                        had to be taken “as a practical measure.” On November 1, 1943, at the end of
                        the Moscow Conference, the Foreign Ministers of the United States, Great
                        Britain, and the Soviet Union agreed that Austria’s annexation by Germany
                        was “null and void,” and that they favored the re-establishment of <quote>“a
                            free and independent Austria.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>A provisional government was established in Austria on April 25, 1945, and a
                        Democratic Republic of Austria was proclaimed on May 14. On August 8, 1945,
                        Austria and Vienna were divided into four occupation zones, with an Allied
                        Council for Austria assuming authority over matters affecting the whole
                        country. On January 7, 1946, the Four Powers recognized the Austrian
                        Republic within its 1937 boundaries.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Re-establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1946">1946.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/erhardt-john-george">John G.
                            Erhardt</ref> was appointed as the U.S. Political Representative to the
                        Austrian Government on January 21, 1946. He was appointed Minister to
                        Austria on August 3. He presented his credentials on September 7, and served
                        until June 27, 1950.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName>Ludwig Kleinwaechter</persName> was recognized as Austria’s first
                        postwar representative to the United States on January 21, 1946. He was
                        promoted to Minister and presented his new credentials on December 4, 1946.
                        He was promoted to Ambassador and presented his new credentials on December
                        19, 1951.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1951"
                            >1951.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>American Minister <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/donnelly-walter-joseph">Walter J.
                            Donnelly</ref> was promoted to Ambassador on November 16, 1951. He
                        presented his credentials on November 28, and served until July 19,
                        1952.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Other U.S. Diplomatic Missions in Vienna</head>
                    <p>Vienna is the headquarters of the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA).
                        The United States has had a representative there since 1957.</p>
                    <p>The United States also appointed a Representative to the United Nations
                        Industrial Development Organization (UNIDO) in 1968. In 1983, both missions
                        were combined into the U.S. Mission to International Organizations in
                        Vienna.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="treaties_agreements">
                    <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <p>The U.S. treaty “establishing friendly relations” with the Austrian
                            Republic was signed in <placeName key="vienna">Vienna</placeName> on
                            August 24, 1921, and entered into force on November 8, 1921. It opened
                            the way for the resumption of diplomatic relations.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_event">
                        <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                        <div type="timeline">
                            <p>On May 15, 1955, the Four Powers (the United States, Great Britain,
                                France, and the Soviet Union) signed the Austrian State Treaty in
                                    <placeName key="vienna">Vienna</placeName>, which ended the
                                four-power occupation and declared Austria to be a free,
                                independent, and neutral state.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="appendix">
                        <head>Resources</head>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl>Bevans, Charles I. <hi rend="italic">Treaties and Other
                                    International Agreements of the United States of America,
                                    1776-1949. Volume 5: Afghanistan-Burma</hi>. Department of State
                                Publication 8543, October 1970. </bibl>
                            <bibl> CIA World Factbook: <ref
                                    target="https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/au.html"
                                    >Austria </ref>
                            </bibl>
                            <bibl> Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                    target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-austria/"
                                    >Austria</ref>
                            </bibl>
                            <bibl> Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                    target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/austria/"
                                    >Austria</ref>
                            </bibl>
                            <bibl>Department of State. <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the
                                    United States</hi>, 1921. Volume I. Washington: Government
                                Printing Office, 1936. </bibl>
                            <bibl>Library of Congress Country Study: <ref
                                    target="http://memory.loc.gov/frd/cs/attoc.html">Austria</ref>
                            </bibl>
                            <bibl>Miller, Hunter. <hi rend="italic">Treaties and Other International
                                    Acts of the United States of America: Volume 3, Documents 41-79:
                                    1819-35)</hi>. Washington: Government Printing Office,
                                1933.</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
