<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Baden</title>
                <title type="short">Baden*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States announced its independence from Great Britain in 1776,
                        <placeName xml:id="xu">Baden</placeName> was a sovereign, independent state.
                    The Grand Duchy of Baden emerged from the Napoleonic Wars strengthened and
                    enlarged, and in 1818 became one of the first German states to institute a
                    constitutional monarchy. The first act of mutual recognition between the Grand
                    Duchy of Baden and the United States came in 1832, and relations between the two
                    countries expanded through 1871, when Baden joined the German Empire. From this
                    point forward, foreign policy of the German Empire was made in Berlin, with the
                    German Kaiser (who was also the King of Prussia) accrediting ambassadors of
                    foreign nations. Relations were severed when the U.S. declared war upon Imperial
                    Germany in 1917.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1832">1832</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first known act of mutual recognition between the United States and the
                        Grand Duchy of Baden occurred on July 13, 1832, when the first U.S.
                        Consulate in the Grand Duchy of Baden opened in <placeName
                            xml:id="baden-baden">Baden-Baden</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The first U.S. Consulate in the Grand Duchy of Baden was opened on <date
                            when="1832-07-13">July 13, 1832</date> in Baden-Baden.</head>
                    <p>It closed on June 21, 1946. Other consulates in Baden included: <placeName
                            xml:id="frieburg">Frieburg</placeName>, which opened on March 5, 1891
                        and closed on May 11, 1908; <placeName xml:id="kehl">Kehl</placeName>, which
                        opened on April 30, 1872, and closed on February 5, 1915; <placeName
                            xml:id="carlsruhe">Carlsruhe</placeName> (Karlsruhe), which opened on
                        March 3, 1855 and closed on February 18, 1872; and <placeName
                            xml:id="mannheim">Mannheim</placeName> on October 26, 1843, and closed
                        on July 8, 1916.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The first Consulate of the Grand Duchy of Baden, <date when="1833-12-20"
                            >December 20, 1833</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first Consulate of the Grand Duchy of Baden in the United States was
                        established in New York on December 20, 1833, with <persName>C.F.
                            Hoyer</persName> as Consul.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Expansion of Relations, <date when="1868">1868</date>.</head>
                    <p>The relationship between the United States and the Grand Duchy of Baden
                        continued to expand through the 1860s. On July 19, 1868, specially
                        accredited U.S. Minister to the Grand Duke of Baden <persName>George
                            Bancroft</persName> and the Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Grand
                        Duchy of Baden <persName>Rudolph von Freydorf</persName> signed a treaty of
                        naturalization between the United States and the Grand Duchy of Baden. At
                        the time, Bancroft was also accredited to Prussia and the North German
                        Confederation and, after 1871, to the German Empire. Yet, although Bancroft
                        was recalled from his position in Berlin in 1874 (at his own request), he
                        was never officially recalled from the court of Baden. For several years
                        after Bancroft’s death in 1891, he remained listed as U.S. Minister to
                        Baden. See entry on <ref target="/countries/issues/german-unification"
                            >German Unification</ref> for further details.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Relations, <date when="1917">1917</date>.</head>
                    <p>On February 3, 1917, U.S. President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>
                        instructed the Secretary of State to notify the German Ambassador to the
                        United States that all diplomatic relations between the U.S. and the German
                        Empire were severed. As the foreign affairs of Imperial Germany were run out
                        of Berlin and decided upon by the Kaiser, this constituted the severance of
                        relations with Baden, as part of the German Empire. On April 6, 1917, Wilson
                        declared war upon Imperial Germany.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Extradition Convention, <date when="1857">1857</date>.</head>
                    <p>An Extradition Convention was signed on January 30, 1857, by U.S. Minister to
                        Prussia <persName>Peter D. Vroom</persName> and <persName>Baron Marschall de
                            Bieberstein</persName>, the Grand Duke of Baden’s Minister at the Court
                        of the King of Prussia.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty on Naturalization, <date when="1868">1868</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Treaty on Naturalization between citizens of the United States and the
                        Grand Duchy of Baden was signed on July 19, 1868, and allowed for the
                        naturalization of American citizens in Baden and that of Baden citizens in
                        the United States.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Baden Joins the German Empire, <date when="1871">1871</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Grand Duchy of Baden was one of the founding states of the German Empire,
                        which was proclaimed on January 18, 1871.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>German Unification.</head>
                    <p>Baden was one of the states involved in the process of German unification
                        during the mid-nineteenth century. (See “<ref
                            target="/countries/issues/german-unification">Unification of German
                            States</ref>” for greater detail.)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The Second Reich, Trade, Citizenship, and Extradition.</head>
                    <p>As with other German states that the United States had treaties with, after
                        Baden joined the Second Reich in 1871 there were questions as to whether
                        U.S. officials abided by treaties concluded with Baden or with Prussia in
                        dealing with issues of trade, citizenship, or extradition with subjects of
                        the Grand Duchy of Baden. It was decided that a variety of different
                        circumstances would guide U.S. foreign policy towards the German states.
                        First, <quote>“where a State has lost its separate existence, as in the case
                            of Hanover and Nassau, no questions can arise.”</quote> Second,
                            <quote>“where no treaty has been negotiated with the Empire, the
                            treaties with the various States which have preserved a separate
                            existence have been resorted to.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Despite the Constitution of the German Empire of 1871, which stipulated that
                        the Empire was responsible for treaties, alliances, and representing the
                        Empire amongst nations, the smaller states still retained the right of
                        legation. This included the right to legislate, to grant exequaturs to
                        foreign consuls in their territories (though not to send German consuls
                        abroad), and to enter into conventions with foreign nations as long as they
                        did not concern matters already within the jurisdiction of the Empire or the
                        Emperor.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi> (Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law</hi>
                        (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">Four Phases of American
                            Development</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, 1912).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Elmer Plischke, <hi rend="italic">U.S. Department of State: A Reference
                            Book</hi> (Greenport, CT: Westwood Press, 1999).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
