<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Brunei</title>
                <title type="short">Brunei</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Emily Horne, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p> Friendly relations between the United States and Brunei date to the 1800s. By
                    1865, the United States had a consular presence in Brunei. The U.S. maintained
                    diplomatic relations with the Sultan of Brunei’s government until it became a
                    British protectorate in 1888, at which time the United Kingdom assumed
                    responsibility for Bruneian foreign affairs. Brunei reacquired its full
                    independence in 1984.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="brunei-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Brunei</head>
                </figure>
                <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                    <head>Recognition</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>U.S. Recognition of Brunei Darussalami Independence, <date when="1984">1984</date>. </head>
                        <p> The United States recognized the full independence of Brunei Darussalam
                            from the United Kingdom on January 1, 1984, and opened the American
                            Embassy in <placeName key="bandar-seri-begawan">Bandar Seri
                                Begawan</placeName> on that same date. Since 1888, Brunei had been a
                            British protectorate. Although Brunei adopted a constitution in 1959
                            that declared it a self-governing state, responsibility for its foreign
                            affairs, security, and defense remained the prerogative of the United
                            Kingdom until 1984.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                    <head>Consular Presence</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Consulate in Brunei, <date when="1865">1865</date>.</head>
                        <p> After signing a bilateral treaty of Peace, Friendship, Commerce, and
                            Navigation in 1850, the United States maintained a Consulate in Brunei
                            from 1865 to 1868. Consul Captain <persName>C. Lees Moses</persName>,
                            the first Consul to serve at the post, presented his credentials in
                            Brunei on July 18, 1865. The post was called <placeName key="borneo">“Brunei, Borneo”</placeName> at the time. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in
                            Brunei, <date when="1984">1984</date>.</head>
                        <p> Diplomatic relations and the American Embassy in Brunei were established
                            on May 28, 1984, when U.S. Ambassador <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/king-barrington">Barrington
                                King</ref> presented credentials to the government at Bandar Seri
                            Begawan.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties &amp; Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the Treaty of Peace, Friendship, Commerce and Navigation,
                            <date when="1850">1850</date>.</head>
                    <p> The Treaty of Peace, Friendship, Commerce and Navigation between the United
                        States and Brunei was signed by both countries in Brunei on June 23, 1850,
                        and entered into force on July 11, 1853. The treaty is still in effect
                        today.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2700.htm">Brunei</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/p/eap/ci/bx/index.htm">Brunei</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>