<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Brunswick and
                    Lüneburg</title>
                <title type="short">Brunswick and Lüneburg</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States announced its independence from Great Britain in 1776, the
                    Duchy of <placeName xml:id="b-l">Brunswick and Lüneburg</placeName> was a
                    sovereign, independent state. Incorporated into the Kingdom of Westphalia during
                    the Napoleonic wars of the early nineteenth century, the Duchy of Brunswick and
                    Lüneburg regained independence in 1813. Mutual recognition between Brunswick and
                    Lüneburg and the United States was established in 1848. </p>
                <p> The Duchy of Brunswick and Lüneburg joined the <placeName xml:id="xc">North
                        German Confederation</placeName> in 1867, to which the U.S. appointed <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/bancroft-george">George Bancroft</ref>,
                    then U.S. Minister to Prussia, to serve as the U.S. Minister to the North German
                    Confederation. From this point forward, foreign policy of the North German
                    Confederation, and later, after 1871 the German Empire, was made in <placeName xml:id="berlin">Berlin</placeName>, with the German Kaiser (who was also the
                    King of Prussia) accrediting ambassadors of foreign nations. Relations with
                    Imperial Germany were severed when the U.S. declared war in 1917.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1848">1848</date>.</head>
                    <p> On April 5, 1848 U.S. Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/buchanan-james">James Buchanan</ref>
                        acknowledged the Consul-General of Brunswick and Lüneburg at New York as
                            <persName>John Dreyer Esq.</persName>, which constitutes the first known
                        act of mutual recognition between the United States and the Duchy of
                        Brunswick and Lüneburg. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Consulate opened in the Duchy of Brunswick and Luneburg, <date when="1856-03-17">March 17, 1856</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States opened its first consulate in the Duchy of Brunswick and
                        Lüneburg on March 17, 1856. This post closed on July 25, 1916. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations. </head>
                    <p>The United States and the Duchy of Brunswick and Lüneburg never established
                        diplomatic relations.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="treaties">
                    <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Convention Respecting the Disposition of Property, <date when="1854">1854</date>.</head>
                        <p> On August 21, 1854, the U.S. Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/marcy-william-learned">William L.
                                Marcy</ref> and the Consul of the Duke of Brunswick and Lüneburg at
                            Mobile, Ala., Dr. <persName>Julius Samson</persName>, signed a
                            Convention Respecting the Disposition of Property, as they were
                            “animated by the desire to secure and extend, by an amicable convention,
                            the relations happily existing between the two countries.” The treaty
                            was negotiated and signed in Washington, DC.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                    <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Brunswick and Lüneburg Join the North German Confederation, <date when="1867">1867</date>.</head>
                        <p> On July 1, 1867, the Duchy of Brunswick and Lüneburg joined the North
                            German Confederation. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>German Empire, <date when="1871">1871</date>.</head>
                        <p> The Duchy of Brunswick and Lüneburg joined the German Empire, which was
                            proclaimed on January 18, 1871.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>German Unification.</head>
                        <p> Brunswick and Lüneburg was involved in the process of German unification
                            during the mid-nineteenth century. See <ref target="/countries/issues/german-unification">“Unification of German
                                States</ref>” for greater detail.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Charles I. Beavans, <hi rend="italic">Treaties and Other International
                            Agreements of the United States of America, 1776-1949,</hi> (Department
                        of State: Washington, DC, 1971), Volume 8.</bibl>
                    <bibl> William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi> (Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910). </bibl>
                    <bibl> John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law</hi>
                        (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906). </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>