<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Bulgaria</title>
                <title type="short">Bulgaria</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Evan Duncan, March 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Bulgaria revolted against Ottoman Turkish rule in 1876. The Treaty of San
                    Stefano, which ended the Russo-Turkish War of 1877-78, established a large
                    Bulgarian state. The Treaty of Berlin (1878), however, established a smaller
                    Bulgarian principality north of the Balkan Mountains. Its boundaries were not
                    finalized until after World War I. Bulgaria became independent of the Ottoman
                    Empire on October 5, 1908, after which its reigning Prince, Ferdinand of
                    Saxe-Coburg, proclaimed himself Tsar.<figure>
                        <graphic url="bulgarian-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Bulgaria</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Bulgarian Independence, <date when="1909"
                        >1909</date>.</head>
                    <p>Bulgaria declared its independence on <date when="1908-10-05">October 5,
                            1908</date>. The United States recognized Bulgaria on <date
                            when="1909-05-03">May 3, 1909</date>, when Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/knox-philander-chase">Philander
                            Knox</ref> instructed Chargé Norman Hutchinson to convey a message from
                        President William H. Taft to Tsar Ferdinand, which offered the president’s
                        congratulations “upon the admission of Bulgaria to the community of
                        sovereign and independent States.”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <p>A Consular Agency was established in <placeName key="sofia">Sofia</placeName>
                        on January 12, 1912. It reported to the Consulate General in Bucharest. It
                        became a Consulate General on February 22, 1915.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1903"
                        >1903</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. diplomatic representative in Bulgaria was <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/dickinson-charles-monroe">Charles M.
                            Dickinson</ref>, who was appointed Agent on April 24, 1901. He held the
                        position until June 30, 1903. Dickinson served concurrently as Consul
                        General at Constantinople, and there is no record that he ever presented
                        credentials in Sofia.</p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/jackson-john-brinkerhoff">John B.
                            Jackson</ref>, who was Minister to Greece, Romania, and Serbia, was the
                        first Diplomatic Agent to Bulgaria, and the first U.S. representative to
                        present his credentials there, which he did on September 19, 1903. This date
                        marks the establishment of diplomatic relations between Bulgaria and the
                        United States. He was re-appointed in 1911 as Minister to Romania, Serbia,
                        and Bulgaria. Later Diplomatic Agents to Bulgaria (1907-10) were also
                        Ministers to Romania and Serbia. Only one of them, <persName>Horace G.
                            Knowles</persName> (1907-09) presented his credentials in Bulgaria. Only
                        after World War I was a U.S. representative commissioned solely to
                        Bulgaria.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Bulgarian Legation in the United States, <date
                            when="1914">1914</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 22, 1914, <persName>Stefan Panaretov</persName> presented his
                        credentials as Bulgaria’s first Minister to the United States. He served
                        until 1925.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of American Legation in Sofia, <date when="1919"
                        >1919</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation in Sofia was established on March 18, 1919, when <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/wilson-charles-stetson">Charles S.
                            Wilson</ref> presented his credentials as Chargé d’Affaires <hi
                            rend="italic">ad interim at Sofia</hi>. Wilson later was appointed
                        Minister to Bulgaria on October 8, 1921, and presented his credentials on
                        December 5.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed, <date when="1941">1941</date>.</head>
                    <p>Bulgaria declared war on the United States on December 13, 1941. U.S.
                        Minister <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/earle-george-howard">George
                            H. Earle III</ref> left Sofia and arrived in Istanbul on December 27,
                        1941. The United States did not declare war on Bulgaria until June 5, 1942.
                        President <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName> believed that Bulgaria
                        would not have declared war without pressure from Nazi Germany.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Resumed and American Legation Reopened, <date
                            when="1947">1947</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Soviet Union declared war on Bulgaria on September 5, 1944, and occupied
                        the country despite Bulgaria’s acceptance of an armistice on September 8,
                        1944. The Sovietization of the country proceeded apace, with the country
                        being proclaimed a People’s Republic on September 15, 1946. However, the
                        United States still recognized the pre-war Bulgarian government. The U.S.
                        Legation in Sofia was reopened on September 27, 1947, and <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/heath-donald-read">Donald R.
                            Heath</ref> presented his credentials on November 8 as U.S. Minister to
                        Bulgaria.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Bulgarian Legation in the United States Reopened, <date when="1947"
                            >1947</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Bulgarian Legation in Washington reopened November 21, 1947, with
                            <persName>Stoyan Athanassov</persName> as Chargé d’Affaires <hi
                            rend="italic">ad interim</hi>. Minister <persName>Nissim
                            Mevorah</persName> presented his credentials on December 29, 1947.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed by Bulgaria, <date when="1950"
                        >1950</date>.</head>
                    <p>In 1950, the Bulgarian Government accused U.S. Minister Heath of espionage
                        and declared him <hi rend="italic">persona non grata</hi> on January 19.
                        Bulgaria severed diplomatic relations with the United States on February 20,
                        1950. The United States announced the suspension of diplomatic relations
                        with Bulgaria on February 21, and Heath left the country on February 24,
                        1950.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Reestablished and American Legation Reopened, <date
                            from="1959" to="1960">1959-1960</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States and Bulgaria agreed to resume diplomatic relations on March
                        24, 1959. <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/page-edward">Edward Page,
                            Jr.</ref> was appointed Minister to Bulgaria on November 23, 1959, and
                        presented his credentials on March 14, 1960.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Bulgarian Legation in the United States Reopened, <date when="1960"
                            >1960</date>.</head>
                    <p>
                        <persName>Peter Voutov</persName> was appointed as Bulgaria’s Minister to
                        the United States on December 2, 1959, and presented his credentials on
                        January 15, 1960.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of America Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1966"
                            >1966</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Legation in Bulgaria was elevated to Embassy status on November 28, 1966.
                        Minister <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/mcsweeney-john-morgan">John
                            M. McSweeney</ref>, who had been originally appointed on May 16, 1966,
                        was appointed Ambassador on April 7, 1967. He presented his new credentials
                        on April 19, 1967.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Bulgarian Legation Raised to Embassy Status, <date when="1966"
                        >1966</date>.</head>
                    <p>Bulgarian Minister <persName>Luben Guerassimov</persName>, who had served
                        since September 1, 1965, was promoted to Ambassador and presented his new
                        credentials on December 14, 1966.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="treaties_agreements">
                    <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Most-Favored-Nation Status, <date when="1906">1906</date>.</head>
                        <p>The first agreement between the United States and Bulgaria dealt with
                            reciprocal trade on a most-favored-nation basis. Diplomatic Agent
                                <persName>John B. Jackson</persName> concluded the agreement in
                            Sofia on June 6, 1906, and it was proclaimed to be in force on September
                            15, 1906.</p>
                        <p>The first treaty between the United States and Bulgaria dealt with
                            naturalization, and was signed at Sofia on November 23, 1923, and
                            entered into force on April 5, 1924.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_event">
                        <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                        <div type="timeline">
                            <p>In 1876, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/schuyler-eugene"
                                    >Eugene Schuyler</ref>, U.S. Consul General in Constantinople,
                                was sent to Bulgaria to investigate what would now be called a human
                                rights issue: Turkish suppression of a Bulgarian revolt. He reported
                                at length on “the Bulgarian Horrors,” and helped shift British
                                policy away from unconditional support for the Ottoman Empire.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="appendix">
                        <head>Resources</head>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl> Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                    target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-bulgaria/"
                                    >Bulgaria</ref>
                            </bibl>
                            <bibl> Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                    target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/bulgaria/"
                                    >Bulgaria</ref>
                            </bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
