<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Burma</title>
                <title type="short">Burma</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, March 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>In an unconventional sequence of events, the United States and Burma established
                    diplomatic relations prior to Burma’s formal independence from the British
                    Empire. The multistage independence process agreed to by the Burmese and the
                    British allowed for the creation of a provisional government with the authority
                    to conduct relations with other states before Burma attained full, sovereign
                    independence.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="burmese-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Burma</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Burmese Independence, <date when="1948"
                        >1948</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Union of Burma as an “independent sovereign
                        state” on January 4, 1948, when President <persName>Harry S.
                            Truman</persName> sent a congratulatory message to President
                            <persName>Sao Shwe Thaike</persName>, Saopha of Yawnghae. Burma had
                        previously been a part of the British Empire and in January 1947, Burmese
                        political leaders reached agreement with the British government on the
                        process by which Burma would achieve independence. During 1947, the Burmese
                        selected a Constituent Assembly, devised a Constitution, and established a
                        provisional Government of Burma with which the United States established
                        diplomatic relations prior to Burma’s formal independence (see Diplomatic
                        Relations below).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in Burma,
                            <date when="1947">1947</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations and the American Legation in Burma were established on
                        September 18, 1947, when the U.S. Department of State announced that the
                        governments of Burma and the United States had <quote>“agreed to exchange
                            representatives with the rank of ambassador.”</quote> The announcement
                        also stated that the Consulate General of the United States in <placeName
                            xml:id="rangoon">Rangoon</placeName> was being raised to the status of
                        Embassy.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-burma/">Burma</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/burma/">Burma</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
