<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Canada</title>
                <title type="short">Canada</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The Dominion of Canada formed in 1867, but as an integral part of the British
                    Empire its foreign relations remained under the control of London. Over the next
                    six decades Canada gradually won greater control over its external affairs,
                    spurred in part by the demands of managing its relationship with the United
                    States. American and Canadian government officials increasingly interacted
                    through joint commissions and military cooperation, and the two governments even
                    negotiated a bilateral fisheries treaty in 1923. It was not until 1926, however,
                    that the United Kingdom acknowledged that Canada was fully autonomous in the
                    conduct of its foreign affairs.<figure>
                        <graphic url="canada-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Canada</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Canadian Independence, <date when="1927"
                        >1927</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Canada as an independent state with autonomous
                        control over its foreign relations on <date when="1927-02-18">February 18,
                            1927</date>, when <persName>Vincent Massey</persName> presented his
                        credentials in Washington as Canadian Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                        Plenipotentiary. This action followed the 1926 British Imperial Conference
                        that produced the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/creation-israel"
                            >Balfour Declaration</ref>, which stated the United Kingdom and the
                        Dominions <quote>“are autonomous Communities within the British Empire,
                            equal in status, in no way subordinate one to another in any aspect of
                            their domestic or external affairs.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1927"
                        >1927</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on February 18, 1927, when
                            <persName>Vincent Massey</persName> presented his credentials in
                        Washington as Canadian Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of American Legation in Ottawa, <date when="1927"
                            >1927</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation in <placeName key="ottawa">Ottawa</placeName> was
                        established on June 1, 1927, when <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/phillips-william">William
                            Phillips</ref> presented his credentials as Envoy Extraordinary and
                        Minister Plenipotentiary.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1943"
                        >1943</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation in Ottawa was elevated to Embassy status on November
                        19, 1943, when <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/atherton-ray">Ray
                            Atherton</ref> presented his credentials as Ambassador Extraordinary and
                        Plenipotentiary.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>CIA World Factbook: <ref
                            target="https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ca.html"
                            >Canada</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-canada/">Canada</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/canada/">Canada</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Langer, William L. <hi rend="italic">An Encyclopedia of World
                        History</hi>. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1968.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
