<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: The Cayman
                    Islands</title>
                <title type="short">The Cayman Islands</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Derived from U.S. Department of State, Background Note, November 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="history">
                <head>Historical Overview</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Early History:</hi> The Cayman Islands remained largely
                    uninhabited until the 17th century. A variety of people settled on the islands,
                    including pirates, refugees from the Spanish Inquisition, shipwrecked sailors,
                    deserters from Oliver Cromwell’s army in Jamaica, and slaves. The majority of
                    Caymanians are of African and British descent, with considerable interracial
                    mixing. Great Britain took formal control of the Cayman Islands, along with
                    Jamaica, under the Treaty of Madrid in 1670. Following several unsuccessful
                    attempts, permanent settlement of the islands began in the 1730s.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="cayman-islands-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Cayman Islands</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The 20th Century:</hi> The Cayman Islands, initially
                    administered as a dependency of Jamaica, became an independent colony in 1959;
                    they now are a self-governing British Overseas Territory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Foreign-Relations">
                <head>Foreign Relations</head>
                <p>Although the United Kingdom is responsible for the Cayman Islands’ defense and
                    external affairs, important bilateral issues are often resolved by negotiations
                    between the Cayman Government and foreign governments, including the United
                    States. Despite close historic and political links to the U.K. and Jamaica,
                    geography and the rise of tourism and international finance in the Cayman
                    Islands’ economy has made the United States its most important foreign economic
                    partner. Following a dip in tourists from the United States after September 11,
                    2001, over 200,000 U.S. citizens traveled by air to the Cayman Islands in 2004;
                    some 4,761 Americans were resident there as of 2005.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
