<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Central American
                    Federation</title>
                <title type="short">Central American Federation*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The states that composed the Central American Federation (also referred to as the
                    Federation of the Centre of America) were the states known today as Costa Rica,
                    El Salvador, Guatemala, Honduras, and Nicaragua. These areas declared
                    independence from Spain on September 15, 1821. In 1823, the United Provinces of
                    Central America was formed of the five Central American states under Gen. Manuel
                    Jose Arce.</p>
                <p>The federation began to dissolve in 1838 and by the early 1840s was all but
                    defunct. Throughout the 1840s, the United States recognized the independence of
                    the five former components of the Central American Federation in their own
                    right: Costa Rica, El Salvador, Guatemala, Honduras, and Nicaragua.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of the Federation of the Centre of America’s
                        Independence, <date when="1824-08-04">1824</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the independence of the Federation of Central
                        American States from Spain on August 4, 1824, when President James Monroe
                        received Antonio Jose Cañas as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                        Plenipotentiary.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, 1824.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations between the United States and the Federation of the
                        Centre of America were established when U.S. President James Monroe received
                        Antonio Jose Cañas as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of
                        the Federation of the Centre of America on August 4, 1824.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Legation in Guatemala City, 1826.</head>
                    <p>U.S. Chargé d’Affaires John Williams presented his credentials to the
                        Federation of Central American States on May 3, 1826.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Relations, 1838-40.</head>
                    <p>The Central American Federation began to dissolve during 1838-40 due to civil
                        war, although the last U.S. diplomatic representative accredited to the
                        Central American Federation, Special and Confidential Agent of the United
                        States to Central America William S. Murphy, did not take formal leave of
                        his post until March 1842. From April 1844 through April 1853, the United
                        States recognized the various members of the Central American Federation as
                        separate states. See individual country entries for <ref
                            target="/countries/guatemala">Guatemala</ref>,
                            <ref target="/countries/el-salvador">El
                            Salvador</ref>, <ref
                            target="/countries/nicaragua">Nicaragua</ref>,
                            <ref target="/countries/costa-rica">Costa
                            Rica</ref>, and <ref
                            target="/countries/honduras">Honduras</ref>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Peace, Amity, Commerce, and Navigation, 1825.</head>
                    <p>On December 5, 1825, the United States and the Central American Federation
                        signed a Treaty of Peace, Amity, Commerce, and Navigation in Washington,
                        D.C. The agreement was signed by U.S. Secretary of State Henry Clay and
                        Antonio Jose Cañas, Minister of San Salvador to the United States on behalf
                        of the Federation of the Centre of America. The treaty was modeled on a
                        similar one signed by the United States and Colombia of October 3, 1824.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law
                        </hi>(Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906). </bibl>
                    <bibl>History of Recognition and Relations, <ref
                            target="/countries/costa-rica">Costa Rica</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>History of Recognition and Relations, <ref
                            target="/countries/el-salvador">El
                            Salvador</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>History of Recognition and Relations, <ref
                            target="/countries/guatemala">Guatemala</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>History of Recognition and Relations, <ref
                            target="/countries/honduras">Honduras</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>History of Recognition and Relations, <ref
                            target="/countries/nicaragua">Nicaragua</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>A Century of Lawmaking: <ref
                            target="http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/amlaw/lawhome.html">U.S.
                            Congressional Documents, 1775-1874.</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
