<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Chile</title>
                <title type="short">Chile</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Evan Duncan, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The United States and Chile have had a long, dynamic relationship. While a
                    Spanish colony and as a new nation, Chile’s distance from the East Coast of the
                    United States impeded extensive interaction because ships had to sail around
                    Cape Horn, the southern tip of South America, to reach Chile’s primary seaport,
                        <placeName key="valparaíso">Valparaíso</placeName>. The key diplomatic
                    events during the course of the U.S.-Chilean relationship often have exerted a
                    profound influence upon U.S. policy. As signified by the landmark 2003 United
                    States-Chile Free Trade Agreement, the two governments have consulted frequently
                    on issues of mutual concern, and have worked together on many areas of interest
                    and agreement. <figure>
                        <graphic url="chile-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Chile</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Chilean Independence, <date when="1823"
                        >1823</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Republic of Chile on January 27, 1823, when
                        the U.S. Senate confirmed President <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/monroe-james">James Monroe’s</ref>
                        nomination of <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/allen-heman">Heman
                            Allen</ref> of Vermont as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                        Plenipotentiary to Chile.</p>
                    <p>A colony of Spain, Chile previously had been an audiencia of the Viceroyalty
                        of <placeName>Peru</placeName>. <persName>Napoleon’s</persName> French
                        armies invaded Spain in 1808 and captured the Spanish monarch, Ferdinand
                        VII. The invasion sparked revolutionary movements in Spain’s American
                        colonies. Chilean revolutionaries declared Chile’s independence on September
                        18, 1810. Several years of fighting followed, but by 1822 U.S. President
                        Monroe concluded that Spain could not recover its American colonies, and on
                        March 8, sent a message to Congress asking that Congress appropriate the
                        funds for Ministers Plenipotentiary for Chile, La Plata (Argentina),
                        Colombia, Peru, and Mexico. Spain protested, but Congress passed the
                        appropriations bill and President Monroe signed it on May 4, 1822. On
                        January 20, 1823, President Monroe nominated <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/allen-heman">Heman Allen</ref> of
                        Vermont as Minister Plenipotentiary and Envoy Extraordinary to Chile, and
                        Congress approved the nomination a week later on January 27, 1823.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations with Chile and the U.S. Legation,
                            <date when="1824">1824.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The United States established diplomatic relations with Chile when Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/allen-heman">Heman Allen</ref> of
                        Vermont presented his credentials to <persName>Ramón Freire
                            Serrano</persName>, who had replaced <persName>Bernardo
                            O’Higgins</persName> as Supreme Director, on April 23, 1824.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of U.S. Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1914"
                            >1914.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The United States elevated its Legation in <placeName key="santiago"
                            >Santiago</placeName> to Embassy status on October 1, 1914, when U.S.
                        Minister to Chile <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/fletcher-henry-prather">Henry P.
                            Fletcher</ref> was appointed as U.S. Ambassador Extraordinary and
                        Plenipotentiary.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="treaties_agreements">
                    <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>The United States - Chile Free Trade Agreement, <date when="2003"
                                >2003</date>.</head>
                    </div>
                    <div type="appendix">
                        <head>Resources</head>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                    target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-chile/"
                                    >Chile</ref>
                            </bibl>
                            <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                    target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/chile/"
                                    >Chile</ref>
                            </bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
