<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: China</title>
                <title type="short">China</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, March 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>After the American Revolution ended, a Philadelphia financier in 1784 sent the
                    ship <hi rend="italic">Empress of China</hi> for the first voyage of direct
                    trade between the United States and China. In the 60 years following the <hi
                        rend="italic">Empress of China’s</hi> voyage, relations among U.S. citizens
                    and Chinese were private and largely commercial. Nevertheless, Sino-American
                    trade grew under the Chinese system that limited foreign traders’ access to a
                    single port city, Guangzhou (Canton). <figure>
                        <graphic url="china-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of China</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1844">1844</date>.</head>
                    <p>Formal recognition by the United States of the Empire of China, and by the
                        Empire of China of the United States, came on or about June 16, 1844, when
                        U.S. Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary Caleb Cushing
                        presented his credentials and met with Chinese official Qiying to discuss
                        treaty negotiations. Prior to this, the United States had dispatched consuls
                        to Guangzhou as early as 1784—the first was Samuel Shaw, the supercargo on
                        the Empress of China—but these had never been formally received by Chinese
                        officials as state representatives. The two countries had acknowledged each
                        other’s existence before 1844, but the negotiations and treaty of that year
                        marked the first recognition under international law. <figure>
                            <graphic url="china_greatwall.jpg"/>
                            <head>Section of the Great Wall in Beijing, China.</head>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_relations">
                <head>Consular Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Consular Relations, <date when="1844">1844</date>.</head>
                    <p>Beginning with Samuel Shaw in 1784, the United States appointed a number of
                        consuls to serve the interests of U.S. merchants in Guangzhou. The
                        appointees were themselves usually merchants. However, these consuls served
                        intermittently and without instructions from Washington, and never received
                        formal acknowledgment of their limited consular credentials from the Chinese
                        Government until after 1843. Thus the start of official consular relations
                        dates to the appointment of a U.S. consul to the ports of Fuzhou (Foochow)
                        and Xiamen (Amoy) in 1844.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Consular Posts, <date from="1844" to="1947"
                            >1844-1947</date>.</head>
                    <p>Fuzhou (Foochow) 1844; Shanghai 1847; Macao 1847; Xiamen (Amoy) 1849; Ningbo
                        (Ningpo) 1853; Whampoa 1853; Guangzhou (Canton) 1853; Shantou (Swatow) 1860;
                        Beijing (Peking) 1861; Niuzhuang (Newchwang) 1862; Yantai (Chefoo) 1863;
                        Hankou (Hankow) 1863; Zhenjiang (Chinkiang) 1864; Jiujiang (Kiukiang) 1867;
                        Tianjin (Tientsin) 1871; Chongqing (Chungking) 1896; Dalian (Dairen) 1904;
                        Hangzhou (Hangchow) 1904; Nanjing (Nanking) 1904; Shenyang (Mukden) 1904;
                        Qingdao (Tsingtao) 1906; Harbin 1907; Andong (Antung) 1914; Changsha 1915;
                        Jinan (Tsinanfu) 1918; Kunming (Yunnanfu) 1921; Guilin (Kweilin) 1943;
                        Chengdu (Chengtu) 1945; Changchun 1947. The United States established a
                        consular post in the British colony of Hong Kong in 1843. The United States
                        also established consular posts in Taiwan during the time that it was a
                        colony of the Empire of Japan, in Danshui (then called Tansui or Tamshui) in
                        1898 and in Taipei (then called Taihoku) in 1914. The above dates reflect,
                        as accurately as possible, the date when a full consul (as opposed to vice
                        consul or consular agent) was either first assigned to or arrived at each
                        post.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1844">1844.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were first established on or about June 16, 1844, when
                        Caleb Cushing presented his credentials as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                        Plenipotentiary and Commissioner to the Chinese authorities in Macao. He
                        concluded the Treaty of Wangxia (Wang-hsia) on July 3, 1844, after which the
                        United States maintained diplomatic representation in China at
                        Guangzhou.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Legation Moved to Beijing (Peking), <date when="1862">1862.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The U.S. Legation was established in Beijing (Peking) in 1862. This followed
                        the Treaties of Tianjin of 1858, by which agreements China for the first
                        time allowed Western diplomats to reside in the capital city, Beijing.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Relations Interrupted, <date when="1912">1912.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were interrupted on February 12, 1912, when, as a result
                        of the Chinese Revolution, the Manchu Emperor abdicated his throne in favor
                        of a provisional republican government. The United States withheld
                        recognition of this new provisional government while awaiting the
                        organization of a permanent government.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Relations Resumed, <date when="1913">1913.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were resumed on May 2, 1913, when the Legation in
                        Beijing communicated a message from President Woodrow Wilson to President
                        Yuan Shikai of China upon the convening of the National Assembly for the new
                        Republic of China.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Relations Interrupted, <date when="1924">1924.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were interrupted on December 9, 1924, when the Legation
                        in Beijing informed the newly declared Provisional Government of the
                        Republic of China that the United States would maintain “de facto relations”
                        with it, pending the establishment of a formal government.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Relations Resumed, <date when="1928">1928.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>On July 25, 1928, following a period of governmental instability and the
                        emergence of the Nationalist Government of the Republic of China, U.S.
                        diplomatic representatives in China signed a tariff revision treaty with
                        Nationalist officials. The Department of State declared that this act
                        constituted full recognition of the Nationalist Government of China, with
                        which diplomatic relations would be conducted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Subordinate Diplomatic Mission at Nanjing (Nanking),
                            <date when="1928">1928.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The Nationalist Government established its capital in Nanjing (Nanking), in
                        1928; however, the United States kept its Legation in Peking and set up
                        “sub-embassy” facilities in Nanjing to facilitate official diplomatic
                        contact with the Nationalist government. The Department of State wanted the
                        official U.S. diplomatic mission to remain in close proximity to the
                        diplomatic representatives of other foreign powers in Peking. It also was
                        skeptical of the Nanjing regime’s long-term viability.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Legation Raised to Embassy, <date when="1935">1935.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The Legation in Beijing was elevated to the level of Embassy on June 18,
                        1935.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Diplomatic Representation during the Chinese-Japanese “undeclared
                        war,” <date from="1937" to="1941">1937–1941.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Throughout the “undeclared war” between Japan and China (1937–1941), the
                        United States maintained its official diplomatic mission in Beijing. The
                        U.S. Ambassador, however, began in August 1936 to reside intermittently near
                        the Chinese government in Nanjing. The Ambassador subsequently moved on
                        November 27, 1937 to Hankou. On August 2, 1938, he went to Chongqing
                        (Chungking), after the government of the Republic of China moved in response
                        to Japan’s invasion and capture of Beijing and Nanjing.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Embassy Moved to Chongqing, <date when="1941">1941.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>On or about December 8, 1941, the official U.S. Embassy was moved to
                            <placeName key="chongqing">Chongqing</placeName> . The move followed the
                        outbreak of war between Japan and the United States on December 7, 1941, and
                        the Japanese capture of U.S. Embassy facilities in Peking.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Embassy Moved to Nanjing, <date when="1946">1946.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>On or about May 1, 1946, the U.S. Embassy was moved to <placeName
                            key="nanjing">Nanjing</placeName> after the government of the Republic
                        of China had moved there following the defeat of Japan in World War II.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Embassy Moved to Guangzhou, <date when="1949">1949.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>On August 5, 1949, the U.S. Embassy was moved to <placeName key="guangzhou"
                            >Guangzhou</placeName> after the government of the Republic of China had
                        moved there in response to advances by Chinese Communist forces during the
                        Chinese Civil War.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Embassy Moved to Chongqing, <date when="1949">1949.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>On October 18, 1949, the U.S. Embassy was moved to <placeName key="chongqing"
                            >Chongqing</placeName> , after the government of the Republic of China
                        had moved there in response to advances by Chinese Communist forces during
                        the Chinese Civil War.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Embassy Moved to Taipei, Formosa (Taiwan), <date when="1949">1949.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>On December 19, 1949, the U.S. Embassy was moved to <placeName key="taipei"
                            >Taipei</placeName>, Formosa (Taiwan), after the government of the
                        Republic of China had moved there in response to advances by Chinese
                        Communist forces on the mainland during the Chinese Civil War. The Chinese
                        Communists established the People’s Republic of China (PRC) on the mainland
                        on October 1, 1949; however, the United States refused to recognize or
                        establish relations with the PRC. The United States continued to recognize
                        the Republic of China government located on Formosa as the legitimate
                        government of China and maintained diplomatic relations only with the
                        Republic of China.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of U.S. Liaison Office in Beijing, <date when="1973"
                            >1973.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>President Nixon visited the People’s Republic of China in 1972 and agreed to
                        the joint “Shanghai Communiqué” of February 27, 1972, in which both nations
                        pledged to work toward the full normalization of diplomatic relations. As
                        part of the effort toward normalization, on May 1, 1973, the United States
                        opened the U.S. Liaison Office in <placeName key="beijing"
                            >Beijing</placeName> to handle all matters in the U.S.-PRC relationship
                        “except the strictly formal diplomatic aspects of the relationship.” The
                        People’s Republic of China created a counterpart PRC office in Washington,
                        DC in the same year.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations with PRC/Termination of Diplomatic
                        Relations with the Republic of China, <date when="1979">1979.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>On January 1, 1979, the United States recognized the PRC and established
                        diplomatic relations with it as the sole legitimate government of China. On
                        the same day, the United States withdrew its recognition of, and terminated
                        diplomatic relations with, the Republic of China as the government of
                        China.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Closing of U.S. Embassy at Taipei, <date when="1979">1979.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The U.S. embassy in <placeName>Taipei</placeName> was closed on February 28,
                        1979.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Opening of U.S. Embassy at Beijing, <date when="1979">1979.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The U.S. Liaison Office in <placeName>Beijing</placeName> was converted to an
                        Embassy on March 1, 1979, and Leonard F. Woodcock, who had been head of the
                        Liaison Office, was appointed Ambassador.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/18902.htm">China</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/p/eap/ci/ch/index.htm">China</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
