<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Colombia</title>
                <title type="short">Colombia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and Written by Christopher Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Colombia effectively achieved its independence from <placeName>Spain</placeName>
                    by 1819, and the country was recognized by the United States in 1822, when
                    President Monroe received a Colombian diplomatic representative in Washington.
                    The United States established a diplomatic mission in Colombia in 1823. At that
                    time, the Colombian federation included the territory of the present-day
                    republics of Colombia, Ecuador, Venezuela, and Panama. U.S. relations with the
                    government in <placeName key="bogota">Bogotá</placeName> were not interrupted
                    when Ecuador and Venezuela left the federation in 1830. From 1830 to 1856, the
                    country was known as New Granada, and from 1856 to 1863, it was known as the
                    Grenadine Confederation. The country became the United States of Colombia in
                    1863, and it changed its name to the Republic of Colombia in 1886. Panama
                    separated from Colombia in 1903.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="colombia-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Colombia</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Colombia, <date when="1822">1822</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Colombia on June 19, 1822, when President
                            <persName>James Monroe</persName> received <persName>Manuel
                            Torres</persName> as the Colombian Chargé d’affaires.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="consular_relations">
                    <head>Consular Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Consulates in Cartagena and Santa Marta, <date
                                when="1823">1823</date>.</head>
                        <p>The first U.S. consulates in the present-day territory of Colombia were
                            established in the Caribbean port cities of Cartagena and Santa Marta in
                            1823. In Cartagena, where a commercial agent had been appointed in 1821
                            and a consular agent appointed in 1822, <persName>James
                                Macpherson</persName> was appointed Consul on March 3, 1823.
                                <persName>Harris Fudger</persName> was appointed Consul in Santa
                            Marta on July 11, 1823. The Consulate in Cartagena closed in 1948, and
                            the Consulate in Santa Marta closed in 1933.</p>
                        <p>Consular posts were also established at different times in <placeName
                                key="barranquilla">Barranquilla</placeName>, <placeName
                                key="bucaramanga">Bucaramanga</placeName>, <placeName
                                key="buenaventura">Buenaventura</placeName>, Cali, and <placeName
                                key="medellín">Medellín</placeName>. None remain in operation.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1822"
                            >1822</date>.</head>
                        <p>Diplomatic relations were established in 1822 by President Monroe’s
                            reception of Colombian Chargé <persName>Manuel Torres</persName>.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of the U.S. Legation in Colombia, <date when="1823"
                                >1823</date>.</head>
                        <p>
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/anderson-richard-clough">Richard
                                Anderson</ref> of Kentucky was named U.S. Minister to Colombia on
                            January 27, 1823, and he presented his credentials to the Colombian
                            Government on December 16, 1823, thus establishing the U.S. Mission in
                            Colombia.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Elevation of Status of Legation in Bogotá to Embassy, <date
                                when="1939">1939</date>.</head>
                        <p>The U.S. Legation in Colombia was raised to the rank of Embassy in 1939.
                                <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/braden-spruille">Spruille
                                Braden</ref> became the first U.S. Ambassador to Colombia.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>General Convention of Peace, Amity, Navigation, and Commerce, <date
                            when="1824">1824</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first commercial treaty between the United States and the Republic of
                        Colombia (then comprising present-day Colombia, Panama, Ecuador, and
                        Venezuela) was signed in 1824 and ratified and proclaimed in 1825. It
                        expired in 1836.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>General Treaty of Peace, Amity, Navigation, and Commerce, <date
                            when="1846">1846</date>.</head>
                    <p>A treaty of friendship and commerce between the United States and New Granada
                        (present-day Colombia), still in force, was concluded in 1846 and proclaimed
                        in 1848.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/35754.htm">Colombia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/p/wha/ci/co/index.htm">Colombia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
