<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Republic of the
                    Congo</title>
                <title type="short">Republic of the Congo</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Prior to its independence in 1960, the Republic of Congo was part of French
                    Equatorial Africa (AEF). During World War II, the AEF administration sided with
                        <persName>Charles DeGaulle</persName>, and <placeName key="brazzaville"
                        >Brazzaville</placeName> became the symbolic capital of Free France during
                    1940-43.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="congo-republic-flag.png"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of the Republic of Congo</head>
                </figure>
                <p>For the last two decades of the Cold War, the Republic of Congo allied
                    principally with the Soviet Union and other Eastern bloc nations. Educational,
                    economic, and foreign aid links between Congo and its Eastern bloc allies were
                    extensive, with the Congolese military and security forces receiving significant
                    Soviet, East German, and Cuban assistance. After the worldwide collapse of
                    communism and Congo’s adoption of multi-party democracy in 1991, Congo’s
                    relations with the United States improved and were cooperative. The United
                    States has enthusiastically supported Congolese democratization efforts,
                    contributing aid to the country’s electoral process. Relations between the
                    United States and the government of President <persName>Denis
                        Sassou-Nguesso</persName> are strong, positive, and cooperative.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of the Republic of Congo’s Independence, <date
                            when="1960">1960</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Republic of the Congo on August 15, 1960, in
                        a congratulatory message from President <persName>Dwight D.
                            Eisenhower</persName> to President <persName>Fulbert Youlou</persName>.
                        On that date, the Republic of the Congo’s independence from French
                        Equatorial Africa was proclaimed.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in
                        Brazzaville, <date when="1960">1960.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on August 15, 1960, when Embassy
                        Brazzaville was established with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/lukens-alan-wood">Alan W. Lukens</ref>
                        as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Suspension of Diplomatic Relations and the Closure of Embassy Brazzaville,
                            <date when="1965">1965.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations between the United States and Congo were disrupted
                        during the most radical Congolese-Marxist period, 1965-77. The United States
                        withdrew its diplomatic and consular representatives from the Republic of
                        Congo (Brazzaville) in August 1965, citing instances of “serious
                        mistreatment by the Congolese authorities of American diplomats and
                        officials,” that included “arrest, detention, incommunicado interrogation,
                        and forced departure.” Once the diplomatic and consular staff departed
                        Brazzaville by August 15, 1965, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/rives-lloyd-michael">Lloyd M.
                            Rives</ref> served as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                            interim</hi> until the Embassy closed. The Republic of Congo closed
                        their embassy in Washington (August 8, 1965), and relocated them to New
                        York.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Resumption of Diplomatic Relations and Reopening of Embassy Brazzaville,
                            <date when="1977">1977.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>On June 7, 1977, the United States and the Republic of Congo agreed to resume
                        diplomatic relations, hoping that <quote>“this step will strengthen
                            relations between their countries and contribute substantially to
                            bettering their mutual understanding and cooperation based upon the
                            principles of reciprocal respect, sovereign equality, and
                            non-interference in internal affairs.”</quote> The U.S. Embassy reopened
                        on October 30, 1977, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/katzen-jay-kenneth">Jay Katzen</ref>
                        as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>. This marked the
                        restoration of relations, which remained distant until the end of the
                        socialist era.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="appendix">
                    <head>Resources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Boyd, John A. <hi rend="italic">Digest of United States Practice in
                                International Law</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing
                            Office, 1979), 21-22.</bibl>
                        <bibl> Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2825.htm">Republic of the
                                Congo</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl> Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/p/af/ci/cf/">Republic of the
                                Congo</ref>
                        </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
