<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Czech
                    Republic</title>
                <title type="short">The Czech Republic</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Evan Duncan, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The Czech Republic was established on January 1, 1993, out of the former Czech
                    and Slovak Federal Republic (commonly known as <ref target="/countries/czechoslovakia">Czechoslovakia</ref>) which ceased to
                    exist as of December 31, 1992. Since independence, the Czechs have made
                    integration into Western institutions their chief foreign policy objective and
                    are part of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) and the European Union
                    (EU). Relations between the U.S. and the Czech Republic are excellent and
                    reflect the common approach both have to the many challenges facing the world at present.<figure>
                        <graphic url="czech-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of the Czech Republic</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of the Independence of the Czech Republic, <date when="1993">1993</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States formally recognized the Czech Republic on January 1, 1993.
                        At the time, White House Press Secretary <persName>Marlin
                            Fitzwate</persName>r noted that <quote>“the United States looks forward
                            to full and mutually productive relations with the new Czech
                            state.</quote>”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1993">1993.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>The Czech and Slovak Federal Republic (CSFR) ceased to exist on December
                            31, 1992, an event commonly referred to as the ‘Velvet Divorce.’ The
                            United States established diplomatic relations with the Czech Republic
                            on January 1, 1993. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of American Embassy in <placeName key="prague">Prague</placeName>, <date when="1993">1993.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p> Ambassador <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/basora-adrian-a">Adrian A.
                            Basora</ref>, who had served as Ambassador to the CSFR since June 1992,
                        served as Ambassador to the Czech Republic from January 1, 1993 until July
                        15, 1995. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/3237.htm">Czech Republic</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/ez/">Czech Republic</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>