<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Ecuador</title>
                <title type="short">Ecuador</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Tiffany Hamelin, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The United States recognized the independence from Spain of Colombia, of which
                    present-day Ecuador then formed a part, on June 19, 1822, when President
                        <persName>James Monroe</persName> received <persName>Manuel
                        Torres</persName> as the Colombian Chargé d’Affaires. Ecuador withdrew from
                    the Colombian federation in 1830 and received U.S. recognition as a separate
                    state in 1832. The two countries concluded a treaty of peace, friendship,
                    navigation, and commerce in 1839, and the United States sent its first resident
                    diplomatic agent to <placeName key="quito">Quito</placeName> in 1848. Diplomatic
                    relations have continued since that time, with the United States and Ecuador
                    participating together in inter-American institutions.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="ecuador-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Ecuador</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Ecuador, <date when="1832">1832</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States effectively recognized Ecuador in a June 4, 1832, letter
                        from Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/livingston-edward">Edward
                            Livingston</ref> to Ecuadorian President <persName>Juan José
                            Flores</persName>. Writing at the direction of President
                            <persName>Andrew Jackson</persName>, Livingston acknowledged a letter
                        from Flores dated January 13, 1832, in which Flores had announced that he
                        was <quote>“at the head of the Government of the State of the
                            Equator.”</quote> Livingston also conveyed President Jackson’s gratitude
                        for Flores’s assurance that U.S. citizens in Ecuador would continue to enjoy
                        the rights and privileges guaranteed to them under an existing treaty with
                        Colombia. Though Livingston expressed Jackson’s hope that Ecuador, New
                        Granada (present-day Colombia and Panama), and Venezuela might reunite and
                        thus achieve domestic tranquility, the letter indicated a recognition of
                        Ecuador’s separation from the Colombian federation.</p>
                    <p>Another indication of U.S. recognition of Ecuador came in May 12, 1834,
                        instructions to <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/mcafee-robert-breckinridge">Robert B.
                            McAfee</ref>, Chargé d’Affaires in New Granada, with which the
                        Department of State transmitted the commission of <persName>Seth
                            Sweetser</persName> as consul in <placeName key="guayaquil"
                            >Guayaquil</placeName>. The dispatch referred to Guayaquil as a city “in
                        Ecuador,” and it asked McAfee to tell Sweetser to <quote>“apply to the
                            Government of that State for his Exequatur.”</quote> Sweetser
                        subsequently presented his commission to the President of Ecuador and
                        accepted his exequatur from him on February 24, 1835. Sweetser’s
                        unconditional acceptance of his recognition as a consular representative
                        from the Ecuadorian authorities constituted further U.S. recognition of
                        Ecuador as a sovereign state. Moreover, in instructions dated April 21,
                        1836, Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/forsyth-john">John Forsyth</ref>
                        authorized Chargé McAfee to negotiate a treaty with the Ecuadorian minister
                        expected in <placeName>Bogota</placeName>, confirming once again U.S.
                        recognition of Ecuador’s status as an independent republic.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Consulate in <placeName>Guayaquil</placeName>, <date
                            when="1825">1825</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. consular representative to serve in what is today Ecuador was
                            <persName>William Wheelwright</persName>, appointed on June 9, 1824, as
                        the U.S. Consul in Guayaquil. The Senate confirmed his appointment on April
                        8, 1825, and he was recognized by the Intendente of the Department of
                        Guayaquil, General <persName>Juan Paz Castillo</persName>, on July 5,
                        1825.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of Status of the Consulate in Guayaquil to Consulate General,
                            <date when="1884">1884</date>.</head>
                    <p>At the urging of Consul <persName>Horatio N. Beach</persName>, the Department
                        of State raised the rank of the Consulate in Guayaquil to Consulate General
                        in 1884. The Consulate General continues to operate today. It is the only
                        consular post in the Western Hemisphere outside of
                            <placeName>Canada</placeName>, <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and
                            <placeName>Brazil</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1848"
                        >1848</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established diplomatic relations with Ecuador on August 12,
                        1848, when Chargé d’Affaires <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/livingston-van-brugh">Van Brugh
                            Livingston</ref> presented his credentials to the Ecuadorian Government.
                        He became the first resident U.S. diplomatic agent in Ecuador.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of Status of Legation in <placeName>Quito</placeName> to
                        Embassy, <date when="1942">1942</date>.</head>
                    <p>The rank of the U.S. Legation in Ecuador was raised to Embassy on March 5,
                        1942. The Minister to Ecuador, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/long-boaz-walton">Boaz Long</ref>, was
                        raised in rank to Ambassador.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Peace, Friendship, Navigation, and Commerce, <date when="1839"
                            >1839</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first major agreement between the United States and Ecuador was a
                        commercial treaty signed by U.S. Special Agent <persName>James D.
                            Pickett</persName> and Ecuadorian Finance Minister <persName>Luis de
                            Saá</persName> on June 13, 1839. The two Governments exchanged
                        ratifications of the treaty at Quito on April 9, 1842, and it became
                        effective on September 23, 1842.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/35761.htm">Ecuador</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/p/wha/ci/ec/index.htm">Ecuador</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
