<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Egypt</title>
                <title type="short">Egypt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States became independent, Egypt was part of the Ottoman Empire
                    and its foreign relations were conducted through the Sultan’s government at
                        <placeName>Istanbul (Constantinople)</placeName>. In 1882, Great Britain
                    established a protectorate over Egypt, which imposed effective British control
                    over Egypt’s foreign affairs despite the fact that it continued to be nominally
                    part of the Ottoman Empire. Beginning with Daniel Smith McCauley on March 17,
                    1849, and until Egypt’s independence, the United States maintained a consular
                    and quasi-diplomatic presence in Cairo through an “Agent and Consul
                    General.”</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="egypt-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Egypt</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Egyptian Independence, <date when="1922"
                        >1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Egypt’s independence on April 26, 1922, in a
                        letter from President <persName>Warren G. Harding</persName> to King
                            <persName>Ahmed Fuad</persName>, delivered by American Diplomatic Agent
                        and Consul General at <placeName key="cairo">Cairo</placeName>, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/howell-joseph-morton">J. Morton
                            Howell</ref>. Egypt had been under British control as a
                        protectorate.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Formation, Recognition, and Dissolution of the United Arab Republic, <date
                            from="1958" to="1961">1958-1961</date>.</head>
                    <p>Egypt and Syria united to form a new state, the <placeName>United Arab
                            Republic (UAR</placeName>), on February 22, 1958. The United States
                        recognized the UAR on February 25, 1958, when U.S. Ambassador <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hare-raymond-arthur">Raymond
                            Hare</ref> delivered a note to that effect to the UAR Ministry of
                        Foreign Affairs. The UAR’s capital was established at
                            <placeName>Cairo</placeName>, where the United States maintained its
                        embassy, while the American Embassy in <placeName>Damascus</placeName> was
                        reclassified as a Consulate General. Syria seceded from the Union in 1961;
                        however, Egypt continued to be known officially as the “United Arab
                        Republic” until 1971.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in
                            Egypt, <date when="1922">1922</date>.</head>
                        <p>Diplomatic relations were established on April 26, 1922, upon American
                            recognition of Egyptian independence. American Diplomatic Agent and
                            Consul General at Cairo, <persName>J. Morton Howell,</persName> had
                            conducted unofficial relations with Egypt as a “semi-independent state”
                            prior to this date, as had been U.S. practice since 1849. Upon
                            recognition, Howell served as the American diplomatic representative to
                            Egypt, and the position of Diplomatic Agent was raised to the rank of
                            Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary on June 24, 1922,
                            thereby establishing the American Legation in Egypt.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed by the United Arab Republic, <date
                                when="1967">1967</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United Arab Republic severed diplomatic relations with the United
                            States on June 6, 1967, in the wake of the <ref
                                target="/milestones/1961-1968/arab-israeli-war-1967">June 1967
                                Arab-Israeli War</ref>.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of U.S. Interest Section in Cairo, <date when="1967"
                                >1967</date>.</head>
                        <p>A U.S. Interests Section was established in the Spanish Embassy in Cairo
                            on June 7, 1967.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Re-establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in
                            Egypt, <date when="1974">1974</date>.</head>
                        <p>The Governments of Egypt and the United States agreed to resume
                            diplomatic relations on February 28, 1974, and the United States named
                            Ambassador-designate <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/eilts-hermann-frederick">Hermann
                                F. Eilts</ref> in charge of the American Embassy in Cairo, which was
                            reopened on the same date.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <!--<bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-egypt/">Egypt</ref></bibl>-->
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/egypt/">Egypt</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
