<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: El Salvador</title>
                <title type="short">El Salvador</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Tiffany Hamelin, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summaryy">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>In 1821, El Salvador and the other Central American provinces declared their
                    independence from Spain. In 1823, the United Provinces of Central America was
                    formed of the five Central American states under Gen. <persName>Manuel Jose
                        Arce</persName>. El Salvador declared itself an independent republic in
                    1839, although the next several decades were marked by frequent revolutions.
                    Following a coup in 1931, normal relations between the United States and El
                    Salvador were interrupted. During the 1980s, the United States supported the
                    Salvadoran Government against Socialist forces.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="els-salvador-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of El Salvador</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Salvadoran Independence, <date when="1824">1824</date>
                        &amp; <date when="1849">1849</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the independence of the Federation of Central
                        American States from Spain on August 4, 1824, when President <persName>James
                            Monroe</persName> received Mr. <persName>Canaz</persName> as Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary. The Federation consisted of the
                        States of <placeName>Honduras</placeName>, <placeName>Guatemala</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Nicaragua</placeName>, <placeName>Costa Rica</placeName>, and
                            <placeName>Salvador</placeName>. After the breakup of the Federation
                        from 1838-1840, the United States recognized Salvador (El Salvador) as a
                        separate, independent state on May 1, 1849, when <persName>E. George
                            Squier</persName>, U.S. Chargé d’affaires to Guatemala, was issued a
                        full power and letter of credence to negotiate a treaty with Salvador.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1863"
                        >1863</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on June 15, 1863, when <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/partridge-james-rudolph">James R.
                            Partridge</ref> presented his credentials in <placeName
                            key="san-salvador">San Salvador</placeName> as U.S. Envoy Extraordinary
                        and Minister Plenipotentiary.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Legation in San Salvador, <date when="1863"
                            >1863</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation in <placeName>San Salvador</placeName> opened on June
                        15, 1863, under Minister Resident <persName>James R.
                        Partridge</persName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Handled through Greater Republic of Central America,
                            <date from="1869" to="1898">1896-1898</date>.</head>
                    <p>In September 1896, the Republics of <placeName>Honduras</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Nicaragua</placeName>, and <placeName>Salvador</placeName>
                        agreed to form the Greater Republic of Central America to exercise their
                        external sovereignty. The United States adjusted its diplomatic relations
                        accordingly by receiving a minister from the organization on December 24,
                        1896; however, upon doing so, President <persName>Grover
                            Cleveland</persName> noted that the responsibilities of the individual
                        republics toward the United States remained “wholly unaffected.” On November
                        29, 1898, the union was dissolved and the individual states promptly resumed
                        the independent conduct of diplomatic relations.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Interrupted, <date when="1931">1931</date>.</head>
                    <p>Normal relations were interrupted on December 4, 1931, when the United States
                        did not recognize the new revolutionary Government of El Salvador. Secretary
                        of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/stimson-henry-lewis">Henry
                            Stimson</ref> based this policy on the guidelines of a 1923 treaty
                        regarding the non-recognition of governments coming into power through
                        revolution.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Normalized, <date when="1934">1934</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Martinez Government of El Salvador via
                        Telegram from Secretary <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hull-cordell"
                            >Cordell Hull</ref> on January 26, 1934. <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/corrigan-francis-patrick">Frank P.
                            Corrigan</ref> presented his credentials to the Government of El
                        Salvador on April 30, 1934.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1943"
                            >1943</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following a joint announcement on March 23, 1943, between the United States
                        and seven American Republics that included El Salvador, the Legations in the
                        respective nations and the United States were raised to the status of
                        Embassy. <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/thurston-walter-clarence"
                            >Walter Thurston</ref> was promoted to Ambassador Extraordinary and
                        Plenipotentiary and presented his credentials to the Government of El
                        Salvador on April 16, 1943.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2033.htm">El Salvador</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/p/wha/ci/es/index.htm">El Salvador</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back> </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
