<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Estonia</title>
                <title type="short">Estonia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Tiffany Hamelin, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The United States first established diplomatic relations with
                        <placeName>Estonia</placeName> on July 28, 1922. The U.S. representative to
                    Estonia was stationed at the Legation in <placeName>Riga, Latvia</placeName>
                    until Legation <placeName key="tallinn">Tallinn</placeName> in Estonia was
                    established on June 30, 1930. The Soviet invasion and annexation of Estonia and
                    the other Baltic States of Latvia and Lithuania in 1940 forced the closure of
                    the American legation, but Estonian representation in the United States
                    continued uninterrupted. The United States never recognized the forcible
                    incorporation of Estonia into the Soviet Union and views the present Government
                    of Estonia as a legal continuation of the interwar republic.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="estonia-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Estonia</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States Recognition of Estonia, <date when="1922"
                        >1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Estonia on July 28, 1922, when the U.S.
                        Commissioner at Riga, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/young-evan-erastus">Evan Young</ref>,
                        informed the Foreign Office of Estonia of the United States’ decision.
                        Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hughes-charles-evans">Charles Evans
                            Hughes</ref> had instructed Young in a telegram dated July 25, 1922, to
                        advise the Foreign Offices of <placeName>Estonia</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Latvia</placeName>, and <placeName>Lithuania</placeName> of
                        this decision on the 28th.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1922"
                        >1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on July 28, 1922, when U.S.
                        Commissioner at Riga, Evan Young, informed the Foreign Office of Estonia
                        that the United States recognized its independence and that he would
                        continue as the American representative to the three Baltic States, with the
                        new rank of Minister.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Legation established at Tallinn, <date when="1922"
                        >1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation at Tallinn was established on June 30, 1930, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/carlson-harry-edwin">Harry E.
                            Carlson</ref> as Charge d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.
                        Previous U.S. diplomatic representatives to Estonia also had been accredited
                        to Latvia and Lithuania, and had resided in Riga.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Legation at Tallinn Closed, <date when="1940">1940</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Legation at Tallinn was closed on September 5, 1940, after the USSR
                        occupied and annexed Estonia, as well as Latvia and Lithuania, in August
                        1940. Although the Soviet actions forced the closure of the American
                        Legation and ended the de facto independence of Estonia, the United States
                        never recognized the state’s forcible incorporation into the
                            <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName>. The U.S. Government permitted
                        Estonian representatives accredited by the last independent government to
                        remain in the United States with diplomatic status, and the U.S. position
                        remained that diplomatic relations continued uninterrupted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Recognition of Estonian Independence from the USSR, <date when="1991"
                            >1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. recognized the restoration of Estonia’s independence on September 2,
                        1991, in an announcement by President <persName>George H.W.
                        Bush</persName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Resumption of Normal Relations, <date when="1991">1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States and Estonia resumed normal diplomatic relations on
                        September 4, 1991, when U.S. Deputy Assistant Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/kamman-curtis-w">Curtis Kamman</ref>
                        and the Estonian Minister of Foreign Affairs, <persName>Lennart
                            Meri</persName>, signed a memorandum of understanding concerning
                        diplomatic relations.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy at Tallinn Opened, <date when="1991">1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Embassy in Tallinn was established on October 2, 1991, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/frasure-robert-c">Robert C.
                            Frasure</ref> as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                        interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5377.htm">Estonia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/en/">Estonia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back> </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
