<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Federal Government
                    of Germany (1848-49)</title>
                <title type="short">Federal Government of Germany (1848-49)*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The revolutionary year 1848 did not bypass the German states. Once news of the
                    February 1848 revolution in Paris spread, many felt that the time was finally at
                    hand for German unification. Rural riots broke out in Central Europe that spring
                    and spread to the urban areas. Throughout the German states revolutionaries
                    advocated for freedom of the press, a national militia, a national German
                    parliament, and trial by jury. Other ideas that were championed during the heady
                    days of 1848 were the abolition of privilege of the aristocracy, constitutions
                    in several of the German states that still lacked such, a more fair system of
                    taxation, and freedom of religion.</p>
                <p>On May 18, 1848, the German National Assembly met at <placeName
                        xml:id="frankfurt">Frankfurt</placeName> am Main, representing the first
                    assembly to be freely elected by the German people. Yet, despite electing an
                    imperial vice regent (Reichsverweser), the government was flawed from the
                    beginning by its lack of a strong executive power.</p>
                <p>In September 1848, U.S. Minister to Prussia <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/donelson-andrew-jackson">Andrew J.
                        Donelson</ref> presented credentials as the new U.S. Minister to the Federal
                    Government of Germany. However, with the revolution’s disintegration and failure
                    by the autumn of 1849, Donelson presented his notice of recall, fully
                    terminating any relations with and recognition of the Federal Government of
                    Germany.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of the German Federation, <date when="1848"
                        >1848</date>.</head>
                    <p>On July 8, 1848, Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/clayton-john-middleton">John M.
                            Middleton</ref> informed the former U.S. Minister to Prussia and current
                        Minister to the German Federal Parliament at Frankfurt, Andrew J. Donelson,
                        that the United States was prepared to recognize any unified, de facto
                        German Government that <quote>“appeared capable of maintaining its
                            power.</quote>” The United States recognized the Federal Government of
                        Germany on August 9, 1848, when Donelson was commissioned as the new U.S.
                        Minister to the Federal Government of Germany.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1848"
                        >1848</date>.</head>
                    <p>On August 9, 1848, U.S. Minister to Prussia Andrew J. Donelson was
                        commissioned as the new U.S. Minister to the Federal Government of Germany,
                        reflecting the developments of that revolutionary year. Donelson presented
                        his credentials on September 13, 1848.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Termination of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1849">1849</date>.</head>
                    <p>Donelson served as U.S Minister until November 2, 1849, when he was recalled
                        following the dissolution of the German revolutionary movement. This
                        constituted full termination of diplomatic relations with the Federal
                        Government of Germany, the U.S. having already accredited a new minister to
                        Prussia, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hannegan-edward-a">Edward A.
                            Hannegan</ref>, on March 22, 1849.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>German Unification.</head>
                    <p>The Federal Government of Germany was an early stepping stone in the process
                        of German unification during the mid-nineteenth century. See “<ref
                            target="/countries/issues/german-unification">Unification of German
                            States</ref>” for greater detail.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law
                        </hi>(Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Charles I. Beavans, Treaties and Other International Agreements of the
                        United States of America, 1776-1949, (Department of State: Washington, DC,
                        1971), Volume 8. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mark R. Cheathem, <hi rend="italic">Old Hickory’s Nephew: The Political
                            and Private Struggles of Andrew Jackson Donelson</hi> (Louisiana State
                        University Press, 2007).</bibl>
                    <bibl>William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi> (Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910). </bibl>
                    <bibl>History of Recognition and Relations: <ref target="/countries/germany"
                            >Germany</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>History of Recognition and Relations: <ref
                            target="/countries/issues/german-unification">German Unification</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>A Century of Lawmaking: <ref
                            target="http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/amlaw/lawhome.html">U.S.
                            Congressional Documents, 1775-1874.</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
