<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Finland</title>
                <title type="short">Finland</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Emily Horne, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>After the upheavals of Finnish independence in 1917 and a civil war, the United
                    States and Finland enjoyed friendly diplomatic relations. The two countries
                    entered into several agreements regarding trade, debt, extradition and other
                    commercial and cultural ties during the 1920s. During the <ref target="/milestones/great-depression">Great Depression</ref> of the
                    1930’s, Finland was the only nation to continue to pay off debts it owed to the
                    United States from <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/wwi">World War
                        I</ref>.</p>
                <p>Following the 1939 Soviet attack on Finland and subsequent “Winter War,” Finland
                    allied with <placeName>Germany</placeName> to obtain supplies and military
                    assistance in continued conflict with the <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName>.
                    This alliance led the United States to sever diplomatic relations with Finland
                    in June 1944, though informal relations were reestablished a few months later
                    and formally reinstated within one year. Between World War II and the
                    dissolution of the Soviet Union in 1991, Finland pursued a strict policy of <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/worldin1945">Cold War</ref>
                    neutrality. The United States, aware of Finland’s precarious geographical
                    position, supported Finnish neutrality while maintaining and reinforcing Finnish
                    ties with the West. <figure>
                        <graphic url="finland-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Finland</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Finnish Independence, <date when="1919">1919</date>.</head>
                    <p>Finland declared its independence from the Russian Empire on December 6,
                        1917, shortly after the Bolshevik Revolution. The United States recognized
                        Finland on May 7, 1919, in a letter from Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Robert Lansing</ref>
                        to Finnish Foreign Minister <persName>Rudolf Holsti</persName>. The United
                        States had delayed its decision due to concerns over Finland’s political
                        instability and ties with Germany.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1919">1919</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United States established diplomatic relations with Finland on May
                            27, 1919, when Acting Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/polk-frank-lyon">Frank L.
                                Polk</ref> recognized Armas <persName>Herman Saastamoinen</persName>
                            as provisional Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of the
                            de facto Government of Finland as U.S. President <persName>Woodrow
                                Wilson</persName> was still in Europe for the Paris Peace
                            Conference. Saastamoinen was recognized as Envoy Extraordinary and
                            Minister Plenipotentiary on August 21, 1919, upon the return of
                            President Wilson.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of the American Legation in Helsingfors, <date when="1920">1920</date>.</head>
                        <p>U.S. Legation in <placeName key="helsingfors">Helsingfors</placeName> was
                            established on March 19, 1920, when Chargé d’Affaires pro tem <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/magruder-alexander-richardson">Alexander R. Magruder</ref> presented his credentials.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>United States Severs Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1944">1944.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>The United States severed diplomatic relations with Finland on June 30,
                            1944, and closed the legation on the same day. A statement by the
                            Department of State noted that this action was taken in response to the
                            Finnish government’s formal admission of a military partnership with
                            Nazi Germany to fight against the Allies of the United States.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of American Mission at Helsinki, <date when="1945">1945.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>After Finland signed an armistice with American allies in September 1944
                            and expelled German nationals from its territory, the United States
                            established a Special Mission at <placeName key="helsinki">Helsinki</placeName> on January 16, 1945. Foreign Service officer
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hamilton-maxwell-mcgaughey">Maxwell M. Hamilton</ref> was appointed Minister at the Mission.
                            This was not a resumption of formal diplomatic relations.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Reestablishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in
                            Finland, <date when="1945">1945.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>Diplomatic relations and the American Legation in Helsinki were
                            reestablished on September 1, 1945, with <persName>Benjamin M.
                                Hulley</persName> as Chargé d'Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                                    interim</hi>.</p>
                        <div type="timeline">
                            <head>Elevation of the American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1952">1952</date>.</head>
                            <p>The U.S. elevated its legation in Helsinki to Embassy status when
                                <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/mcfall-jack-kirkham">Jack
                                    K. McFall</ref> presented his credentials as Ambassador
                                Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary on November 15, 1952. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/3238.htm">Finland</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/fi">Finland</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>