<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: France</title>
                <title type="short">France</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and Written by Lindsay Krasnoff, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>France is one of the oldest U.S. allies, dating to 1778 when the French monarchy
                    recognized the independence of the United States. <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/french-alliance">French military and economic
                        assistance during the American War of Independence</ref> (1775-81) was
                    crucial to the American victory. Since then, relations between the two countries
                    have remained active, despite periods that have tested this long friendship. <figure>
                        <graphic url="france-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of France</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/french-rev">The French Revolution</ref> began
                    in May 1789 and eventually overthrew the government of Louis XVI. In 1792 <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas Jefferson</ref>
                    stated that the U.S. should <quote>“acknowledge any Government to be rightful,
                        which is formed by the will of nation, substantially declared.”</quote> This
                    has been U.S. policy ever since. Consequently, formal diplomatic relations with
                    France were not broken upon the constitution of new French governments after
                    1789 (the majority of which occurred during the nineteenth century). Each time
                    this happened, the resident American diplomatic representative usually submitted
                    new credentials to the appropriate authorities.</p>
                <p>Today, relations between the United States and France are active and friendly.
                    France and the United States share common values and have parallel policies on
                    most political, economic, and security issues. Differences are discussed frankly
                    and have not generally been allowed to impair the pattern of close cooperation
                    that characterizes relations between the two countries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>French Recognition of the Independence of the United States, <date
                            when="1778">1778</date>.</head>
                    <p>France recognized the United States as an independent state on February 6,
                        1778, when France’s Secretary of His Majesty’s Council of State,
                            <persName>Conrad Alexandre Gérard</persName>, and American Commissioners
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/franklin-benjamin">Benjamin
                            Franklin</ref>, <persName>Silas Deane</persName>, and <persName>Arthur
                            Lee</persName> signed two treaties in Paris.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>First U.S. Consular Post Established in France, <date when="1778"
                            >1778</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. consular post was established in <placeName key="bordeaux"
                            >Bordeaux</placeName>, France in March 1778. It was closed in 1996 and
                        re-opened in 2000.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1778"
                        >1778</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on August 6, 1778, when Conrad
                        Alexandre Gérard, presented to Congress his credentials as France’s
                        Minister-Plenipotentiary and Consul-General. <ref
                            target="/milestones/1776-1783/b-franklin">Benjamin Franklin</ref> was
                        appointed as the first U.S. Minister Plenipotentiary to France on September
                        14, 1778, and was accredited by the French Government on March 23, 1779.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of American Diplomatic Mission in France, <date when="1779"
                            >1779</date>.</head>
                    <p>An American diplomatic mission in Paris was first established on March 23,
                        1779, when Benjamin Franklin presented to the French court his letter of
                        credence as Minister-Plenipotentiary.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Interrupted, <date when="1798">1798</date>.</head>
                    <p>In July 7, 1798, following the so-called <ref
                            target="/milestones/1784-1800/xyz">“XYZ affair,”</ref> the U.S. Congress
                        abrogated the treaties of 1778 and a pre-existing consular convention. The
                        French, however, did not accept the abrogation as legally-binding until
                        after the ratification of the 1800 Treaty of Friendship and Commerce.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Resumption of Diplomatic and Cultural Relations with France, <date
                            when="1801">1801</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following the outbreak of the Quasi-War, the U.S. and France signed a Treaty
                        of Friendship and Commerce on September 30, 1800 (also known as the Treaty
                        of <placeName key="morfontaine">Morfontaine</placeName>), which was revised
                        and then later ratified by both sides on July 31, 1801.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1893"
                            >1893</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation in Paris was elevated to embassy status on April 8,
                        1893. <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/eustis-james-biddle">James B.
                            Eustis</ref>, who had served as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                        Plenipotentiary since March 20, 1893, was the first American Ambassador to
                        France. He continued to serve as ambassador until recalled on May 24,
                        1897.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Ambassador Separated from the French Government, <date
                            when="1940">1940</date>.</head>
                    <p>Germany invaded France on May 15, 1940, and as French resistance collapsed,
                        the French Government left Paris on June 10 to make its way to Bordeaux. The
                        American Ambassador, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/bullitt-william-christian">William C.
                            Bullitt</ref>, remained in <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> to
                        oversee the evacuation of American and British civilians, while the American
                        Embassy staff followed the French government. U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hull-cordell">Cordell Hull</ref>
                        designated <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/biddle-anthony-joseph-drexel-jr"
                            >Anthony J. Drexel Biddle, Jr.</ref>, on June 13 as Deputy Ambassador of
                        the U.S. Government near the seat of the French Government, a role that he
                        filled until June 24, when the Department directed him to leave France and
                        resume his duties as Ambassador to the Polish Government in exile. Following
                        the occupation of Bordeaux, the Embassy staff moved with the French
                        government to the vicinity of <placeName key="clermont-ferrand"
                            >Clermont-Ferrand</placeName>, where Bullitt rejoined it on or about
                        June 29, before departing on July 11.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy Moved to Vichy, <date when="1940">1940</date>.</head>
                    <p>On June 16, 1940, French Prime Minister <persName>Paul Reynaud</persName>
                        resigned in favor of <persName>Marshal Henri Philippe Pétain</persName>, who
                        requested terms for an armistice from Germany and oversaw France’s surrender
                        on June 22, 1940. On July 10, 1940, the French Parliament met in <placeName
                            key="vichy">Vichy</placeName> and granted full and extraordinary powers
                        to Marshal Pétain, including the power to write a new Constitution. The
                        American Embassy relocated near the seat of the new Vichy regime in the
                        summer of 1940. <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/leahy-william-daniel"
                            >William D. Leahy</ref> presented his credentials as Ambassador
                        Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary to the French Government in Vichy on
                        January 8, 1941, a position he held until May 1, 1942.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed by France, <date when="1942"
                        >1942</date>.</head>
                    <p>Vichy France severed diplomatic relations with the United States on November
                        8, 1942, when Prime Minister <persName>Pierre Laval</persName> informed the
                        U.S. Chargé in Vichy, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/tuck-somerville-pinkney">S. Pinkney
                            Tuck</ref>, of his government’s decision. This French decision followed
                        the Anglo-American invasion of French North Africa.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Limited U.S. Recognition of the French Committee of National Liberation,
                            <date when="1943">1943</date>.</head>
                    <p>On June 3, 1943, the French Committee of National Liberation (FCNL) was
                        established in <placeName key="algiers">Algiers</placeName> under the
                        leadership of co-Presidents <persName>Charles de Gaulle</persName> and
                            <persName>Henri Giraud</persName>. On August 24, 1943, President
                        Roosevelt instructed Acting-Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/berle-adolf-augustus">Adolf A.
                            Berle</ref> to forward a message to U.S. Minister <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/murphy-robert-daniel">Robert D.
                            Murphy</ref> (Roosevelt’s personal representative in Algiers) that was
                        to be distributed to members of the FCNL two days later. The message
                        announced that the U.S. Government <quote>“recognizes the French Committee
                            of National Liberation as administering those territories which
                            acknowledge its authority.”</quote> The message, however, did
                            <quote>“not constitute recognition of a government of France or of the
                            French Empire by the Government of the United States,” but rather
                            signified “recognition of the French Committee of National Liberation as
                            functioning within specific limitations during the war,” after which
                            “the people of France… will proceed in due course to select their own
                            government and their own officials to administer it.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of the Provisional Government of the French Republic,
                            <date when="1944">1944</date>.</head>
                    <p>On May 16, 1944, the Acting American Representative to the FCNL at Algiers,
                        Selden Chapin, informed Secretary Hull that the FCNL’s Provisional
                        Consultative Assembly had passed a unanimous resolution to the effect that
                        the FCNL would now be referred to as the Provisional Government of the
                        French Republic (PGFR). On October 19, 1944, Secretary Hull informed the
                        American Representative to the FCNL, <persName>Jefferson Caffery</persName>,
                        that the President had decided to recognize the PGFR as <quote>“the de facto
                            authority established in Paris under the leadership of General De
                            Gaulle, at the time of [the] announcement by the French of the creation
                            of a zone of the interior.”</quote> On October 23, 1944, the Department
                        of State issued a press release announcing the recognition of the PGFR by
                        the U.S. Government, and that Caffery would assume the position of U.S.
                        Ambassador to France. On the same day, in Paris, Caffery and representatives
                        from the British, Soviet, and Canadian Governments called on French Foreign
                        Minister, <persName>Georges Bidault</persName>. They provided him with
                        letters extending diplomatic recognition from their Governments and Bidault
                        reciprocated by acknowledging them as duly-accredited ambassadors to
                        France.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Reopening of American Embassy in Paris, <date when="1944"
                        >1944</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following the liberation of Paris at the end of the Summer of 1944, the
                        American Embassy in Paris was reopened to the public on December 1, 1944.
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/caffery-jefferson">Jefferson
                            Caffery</ref> was appointed Ambassador to France on November 25, 1944,
                        and was in charge pending presentation of his letter of credence, which
                        occurred on December 30, 1944.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties_agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Amity and Commerce, <date when="1778">1778</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. treaty to be signed was a Treaty of Amity and Commerce with
                        France that was signed in Paris on February 6, 1778.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/3842.htm">France</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/fr/">France</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Benjamin Franklin</hi> (New Haven, 1959-),
                        XXVII </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
