<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: The Republic of
                    Genoa</title>
                <title type="short">Republic of Genoa*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The <placeName xml:id="xo">Republic of Genoa</placeName> was an independent and
                    sovereign state in 1776 when the United States declared its independence from
                    Great Britain. Genoa recognized the United States in 1791 when it appointed
                        <persName>Joseph Ravara</persName> to act as Consul General for the Doge and
                    Governors of the Republic of Genoa at Philadelphia. The U.S. sent its first
                    consular official to Genoa in 1799; however, the relationship was short-lived as
                    Genoa was annexed by France in 1805. Although it was briefly reconstituted in
                    1814 with the first defeat of <persName>Napoleon</persName>, the Congress of
                    Vienna awarded Genoa to the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia in 1815.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Republic of Genoa’s Recognition of the United States, <date when="1791"
                            >1791</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Republic of Genoa recognized the United States when it sent its first
                        consular agent to the United States. Joseph Ravara was accredited by U.S.
                        President <persName>George Washington</persName> on October 25, 1791, as
                        Consul General of the Doge and Governors of the Republic of Genoa at
                        Philadelphia.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The first Genovese consulate in the United States was established at
                        Philadelphia in October <date when="1791-10">1791</date>.</head>
                    <p>Although the U.S. appointed its first Consul at Genoa on February 27, 1797,
                        U.S. Department of State archival evidence suggests that the appointee never
                        reached Genoa. The first U.S. consulate was established in Genoa in
                        1799.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>No diplomatic relations established.</head>
                    <p>The Republic of Genoa and the United States never established diplomatic
                        relations.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>No treaty or agreement signed.</head>
                    <p>No bilateral treaty or agreement between the United States and the Republic
                        of Genoa was ever signed prior to the republic’s incorporation into the
                        Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia in 1815.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Incorporation of the Republic of Genoa into the Kingdom of
                        Piedmont-Sardinia, <date when="1815">1815</date>.</head>
                    <p>Although the Republic of Genoa was under the rule of France during the
                        Napoleonic Wars, in the post-Napoleonic peace settlement, Genoa was given to
                        the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia in 1815.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Proclamation of the Kingdom of Italy, <date when="1861"
                        >1861</date>.</head>
                    <p>The aftermath of the Franco-Austrian War brought about a series of
                        plebiscites in the northern Italian states. By going to the ballot box, the
                        states voted to join Piedmont-Sardinia, with the ultimate goal of unifying
                        the entire peninsula. It should be noted that Piedmont-Sardinia was one of
                        the more powerful states in the peninsula, as well as having one of the most
                        liberal political systems. Garibaldi’s march to “liberate” the Kingdom of
                        the Two Sicilies in 1860 brought the southern peninsula into the fold, and
                        the new Kingdom of Italy was proclaimed on March 17, 1861, with the royal
                        family of Piedmont-Sardinia as the new ruling monarchs of Italy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Italian Independence, <date when="1861"
                        >1861</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States officially recognized the Kingdom of Italy when it accepted
                        the credentials of <persName>Chevalier Joseph Bertinatti</persName> as
                        Minister Plenipotentiary of the Kingdom of Italy on April 11, 1861.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="relevant-issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Trade and Commerce.</head>
                    <p>During the early years of the republic, the United States sought to promote
                        trade abroad and to ensure that American vessels, both public and private,
                        would be welcomed in ports around the world. As Genoa was one of the larger
                        Mediterranean ports on the Italian peninsula in the late eighteenth century,
                        Genovese recognition of the United States early-on was beneficial to U.S.
                        trade and commerce.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Howard R. Marraro, <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic Relations Between the
                            United States and the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies.</hi> Volume I:
                        1816-1850, (New York: S.F. Vanni (Ragusa), 1951. </bibl>
                    <bibl>History of U.S. Recognition and Relations: <ref target="/countries/italy"
                            >Italy </ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>A Century of Lawmaking: <ref
                            target="http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/amlaw/lawhome.html">U.S.
                            Congressional Documents, 1775-1874</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
