<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: East Germany (German
                    Democratic Republic)</title>
                <title type="short">East Germany (German Democratic Republic)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, March 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>After World War II, Germany was occupied and divided into four zones administered
                    by the main Allied powers. After tensions mounted between the Soviet Union on
                    the one side, and the United States, Great Britain, and France on the other, the
                    Western powers combined their zones and allowed the establishment of the Federal
                    Republic of Germany. The Soviets responded by forming the German Democratic
                    Republic (GDR) to govern their occupation zone. The United States refused to
                    recognize the GDR until 1974. The GDR was absorbed by the FRG in 1990 when
                    Germany reunified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Division of Germany and U.S. Non-Recognition of GDR, <date when="1949"
                            >1949</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following the German surrender to the Allied powers on May 8, 1945, Germany
                        was occupied and divided into four zones. Each of the main Allied powers
                        (the United States, the Soviet Union, Great Britain, and France) was
                        responsible for the administration of its zone. In 1947, the United States
                        and Great Britain merged their zones. After tensions arose between Soviets
                        and the Western powers, the German Federal Republic (FRG, commonly known as
                        West Germany) was created out of the American, British, and French zones on
                        September 21, 1949. The Soviets then oversaw the creation of the German
                        Democratic Republic (<abbr>GDR</abbr>, commonly known as East Germany) out
                        of their zone of occupation on October 7, 1949. The United States responded
                        by stating its position that the GDR was <quote>“without any legal
                            validity,”</quote> and that the United States would <quote>“continue to
                            give full support to the Government of the German Federal Republic at
                                <placeName key="bonn">Bonn</placeName> in its efforts to restore a
                            truly free and democratic Germany.”</quote> As prospects for early
                        reunification of Germany dimmed, the United States established full
                        diplomatic relations with the FRG on May 6, 1955.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Recognition of the German Democratic Republic, and the Establishment of
                        Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in <placeName key="berlin"
                            >Berlin</placeName>, <date when="1974">1974</date>.</head>
                    <p>In response to the improvement of relations between the two German
                        governments, representatives of the United States and GDR negotiated
                        arrangements for U.S. recognition of the GDR and the establishment of
                        diplomatic relations, which occurred on <date when="1974-09-04">September 4,
                            1974</date>, when the United States and East Germany released a joint
                        communiqué to that effect. Despite this step taken to deal with the reality
                        of the German situation, the United States continued until German
                        reunification in 1990 to view the FRG as the sole legitimate successor
                        government of the historical German state and a future reunified
                        Germany.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations with East Germany and the American
                        Embassy in Berlin,<date when="1974"> 1974.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The American Embassy in Berlin was established on December 9, 1974, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/grove-brandon-hambright-jr">Brandon H.
                            Grove, Jr.</ref>, as Chargé d'Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                        interim</hi>. <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/cooper-john-sherman"
                            >John Sherman Cooper</ref> presented his credentials as the first U.S.
                        Ambassador to the GDR on December 20, 1974.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Germany Reunified under Auspices of the FRG, <date from="1990" to="1991"
                            >1990-1991.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Following the collapse of one-party rule in East Germany in late-1989, the
                        signing of a Unification Treaty by East and West German Governments on
                        August 31, 1990, and a series of meetings between the foreign ministers of
                        East and West Germany, the United States, Great Britain, France, and the
                        Soviet Union in Bonn, Berlin, Paris, and Moscow, a Treaty on the Final
                        Settlement with Respect to Germany (the so-called “Two Plus Four Agreement”)
                        was signed in Moscow on September 12, 1990.</p>
                    <p>On September 25, 1990, President <persName>George H.W. Bush</persName>
                        submitted the treaty for ratification, and the U.S. Senate obliged
                        unanimously on October 10. The treaty finally went into effect on March 15,
                        1991. Since the five constituent federal states of the German Democratic
                        Republic were technically absorbed by the Federal Republic of Germany under
                        the terms of Article 23 of the “Basic Law” (which was subsequently abolished
                        under the terms of the Unification Treaty so as to limit any further changes
                        to the borders of Germany), there was no reason for the United States to
                        recognize the reunified Germany as a “new state.” The United States
                        maintained its embassy in <placeName key="bonn">Bonn</placeName>; however,
                        it closed its embassy in <placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName> on
                        October 2, 1990.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Chiefs of Mission: <ref
                            target="http://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/chiefsofmission/german-democratic-republic"
                            >East Germany (German Democratic Republic)</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
