<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Germany</title>
                <title type="short">Germany</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Written by Office of the Historian staff, November 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>From a conglomeration of more than 300 independent kingdoms, duchies,
                    principalities, and free cities in the eighteenth century, the country that is
                    today known as Germany took form in Central Europe throughout the course of the
                    nineteenth century under the helmsmanship of one of its largest and strongest
                    monarchies, Prussia. The establishment of the German Empire in 1871 recognized
                    the Prussian King as the German Emperor. The history of U.S.-German relations in
                    the first half of the twentieth century was rocky, reflecting the two world wars
                    in which the United States and Germany fought on opposite sides. Since the end
                    of World War II in 1945, U.S.-German relations have been a focal point of
                    American involvement in Europe. This relationship has changed significantly over
                    the past six decades, reflecting the tensions of the Cold War. The historic
                    reunification of Germany in 1990 and the role the United States played in that
                    process have served to strengthen ties between the two countries. Today,
                    German-American political, economic, and security relationships continue to be
                    based on close consultation and coordination at the most senior levels.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="germany-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Germany</head>
                </figure>
                <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                    <head>Recognition</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Prussian Recognition of the Independence of the United States, <date
                                when="1785">1785</date>.</head>
                        <p>The Kingdom of Prussia recognized the United States when it signed the
                            September 18, 1785 Treaty of Amity and Commerce with the United
                            States.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                    <head>Consular Presence</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Consular Convention in <placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName>,
                                <date when="1871">1871</date>.</head>
                        <p>On December 11, 1871, U.S. Minister to the German Empire <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/bancroft-george">George
                                Bancroft</ref> and German Privy Councillor of the Legation
                                <persName>Bernard König</persName> signed a Consular Convention in
                            Berlin. The Convention was ratified by the Senate on January 18, 1872,
                            and proclaimed by President <persName>Ulysses S. Grant</persName> on
                            June 1, 1872.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations with Prussia and the American
                            Diplomatic Mission in Berlin, <date when="1797">1797</date>.</head>
                        <p>On June 1, 1797, <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john-quincy">John Quincy
                                Adams</ref> (the former U.S. Minister to the Netherlands and current
                            Minister to Portugal) was nominated by U.S. President <persName>John
                                Adams</persName> to serve as the Minister to Prussia. According to
                            his instructions from the President, Adams’ task in Berlin was to renew
                            the aforementioned 1785 Treaty of Amity and Commerce, which had expired
                            in 1796. Unfortunately, Adams’ letters of credence had been addressed to
                            King <persName>Frederick William II</persName>, who had died on November
                            16, 1797, before Adams could have an audience with him. During a private
                            audience on December 5, however, the new king, <persName>Frederick
                                William III</persName>, formally recognized Adams as the accredited
                            U.S. Minister to his father.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations with the German Empire, <date
                                when="1871">1871.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>On July 8, 1849, Secretary of State <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/clayton-john-middleton">John M.
                                Middleton</ref> stated that the United States was prepared to
                            recognize any unified, de facto German Government that <quote>“appeared
                                capable of maintaining its power.”</quote> Therefore, following the
                            establishment of the German Empire on January 18, 1871, the United
                            States recognized the new German Empire by changing the accreditation of
                            its Minister to Prussia to become Minister to the German Empire. On
                            April 8, 1871, U.S. Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to
                            Prussia <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/bancroft-george">George
                                Bancroft</ref> presented the new German Emperor <persName>Wilhelm
                                I</persName> (who was concurrently King of Prussia) with letter from
                            U.S. President <persName>Ulysses S. Grant</persName> dated March 16,
                            1871. The letter from the President congratulated the Emperor on his
                            assumption of the German throne and recognized him as the head-of-state
                            of a federal Germany.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1893"
                                >1893</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United States raised the American Legation in Berlin to Embassy
                            status when <persName>Theodore Runyo</persName>n, U.S. Minister to
                            Germany, presented his credentials to the German regime as Ambassador
                            Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary on October 26, 1893.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Termination of Relations During the First World War, <date when="1917"
                                >1917</date>.</head>
                        <p>Germany’s resumption of unrestricted submarine warfare in early 1917 led
                            to the termination of diplomatic relations between Germany and the
                            United States. On February 3, 1917, U.S. Secretary of State
                                <persName>Robert Lansing</persName> informed the German Ambassador
                            in Washington, D.C., <persName>Count Johann von Bernstorff</persName>
                            that U.S. President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> had severed
                            diplomatic relations with Germany, that the U.S. Ambassador in Berlin
                                (<persName>James W. Gerrard</persName>) had been withdrawn, and that
                            the U.S. Government would be returning von Bernstorff’s passports.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>U.S. Declaration of War Against Germany, <date when="1917"
                            >1917</date>.</head>
                        <p>Following a series of attacks against American merchant ships on the high
                            seas by German U-boats, the receipt, on February, 24, 1917, by the U.S.
                            Ambassador in London, <persName>Walter Hines Pages</persName>, of the
                            infamous “Zimmerman telegram” from British Foreign Secretary
                                <persName>Arthur Balfour</persName>, and the decision to abandon the
                            plan to adopt “armed neutrality” by placing U.S. naval personnel on
                            civilian ships to guard them against German attacks, President Wilson
                            went before Congress on April 2 to ask for a declaration of war against
                            Germany in order to make the world “safe for democracy.” Following the
                            passage of a Joint Resolution by Congress on April 6, President Wilson
                            issued on the same day a proclamation to the effect that a state of war
                            existed between Germany and the United States.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Reestablishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1921"
                            >1921</date>.</head>
                        <p>Following the failure of the U.S. Senate in 1919-20 to ratify the
                            Versailles Treaty with Germany that had been negotiated by President
                            Wilson during the Paris Peace Conference of 1919, the U.S. Congress
                            passed a Joint Resolution on July 2, 1921, stipulating an end to the
                            state of war between the United States and Germany. On August 25, 1921,
                            the United States High Commissioner to Germany, <persName>Ellis Loring
                                Dresel</persName>, and the German Minister for Foreign Affairs,
                                <persName>Dr. Friedrich Rosen</persName>, signed the “Treaty
                            Restoring Friendly Relations” (the Treaty of Berlin). Full diplomatic
                            relations were reestablished on December 10, 1921, when Dresel presented
                            his credentials as U.S. Ambassador to Germany.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Withdrawal of Ambassadors following the Reichskristallnacht, <date
                                when="1938">1938</date>.</head>
                        <p>Following the murder of the Third Secretary of the German Embassy in
                            Paris by a Polish Jew whose parents had been forcibly deported from
                            Germany in October 1938, the Nazi Party orchestrated a nationwide pogrom
                            against the German Jewish community during the night of November 9-10.
                            In retaliation, President Franklin Roosevelt recalled his ambassador in
                            Berlin, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/wilson-hugh-robert">Hugh
                                R. Wilson</ref>, on November 15 for consultation and did not
                            dispatch another ambassador to take his place. One week after Ambassador
                            Wilson’s recall, the German Ambassador in Washington, <persName>Hans
                                Heinrich Dieckhoff</persName>, informed U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/hull-cordell">Cordell Hull</ref>
                            that he had been recalled to Germany.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed by Germany, <date when="1941"
                            >1941</date>.</head>
                        <p>The German Government announced on December 11, 1941, that it had severed
                            diplomatic relations and declared war on the United States. Following
                            the German announcement, President <persName>Franklin
                                Roosevelt</persName> sent a message to the U.S. Congress requesting
                            that it <quote>“recognize a state of war between the United States and
                                Germany….”</quote> Later that same day, the U.S. Congress resolved
                            that <quote>“the state of war between the United States and [Germany]
                                which has been thrust upon the United States is hereby formally
                                declared,”</quote> and that the President was authorized to all
                            military and government resources to bring to the war to a “successful
                            termination.”</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>End of Hostilities between the United States and Germany, <date
                                when="1951">1951</date>.</head>
                        <p>On October 19, 1951, the U.S. Congress passed a Joint Resolution
                            declaring that the state of war that had existed between the United
                            States and Germany since December 11, 1941, was terminated upon the
                            enactment of the aforementioned resolution.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Division of Germany and the Establishment of Diplomatic Relations with
                            the German Federal Republic (FRG), <date from="1949" to="1955"
                                >1949-1955</date>.</head>
                        <p>Following the German surrender to the Allied powers on May 8, 1945,
                            Germany was occupied and divided into four zones. Each of the main
                            Allied powers (the United States, the Soviet Union, Great Britain, and
                            France) was responsible for the administration of its zone. In 1947, the
                            United States and Great Britain merged their zones. After tensions arose
                            between Soviets and the western powers, the German Federal Republic
                            (FRG, commonly as West Germany) was created out of the American,
                            British, and French zones on September 21, 1949. The Soviets then
                            oversaw the creation of the German Democratic Republic (GDR, commonly
                            known as East Germany) out of their zone of occupation on October 7,
                            1949. The United States responded by stating its position that the GDR
                            was “without any legal validity,” and that the United States would
                                <quote>“continue to give full support to the Government of the
                                German Federal Republic at <placeName key="bonn">Bonn</placeName> in
                                its efforts to restore a truly free and democratic Germany.”</quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>As prospects for early reunification of Germany dimmed, the United States
                            established full diplomatic relations with the FRG on May 6, 1955, when
                            the FRG Diplomatic Mission in Washington was raised to Embassy status
                            under Ambassador <persName>Heinz L. Krekeler</persName>. The American
                            Embassy in Bonn was established on May 14, 1955, when <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/conant-james-bryant">James
                                Conant</ref>, U.S. High Commissioner, presented his credentials as
                            the first U.S. Ambassador to the FRG.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Recognition of the German Democratic Republic, and the Establishment
                            of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in Berlin, <date
                                when="1974">1974</date>.</head>
                        <p>In response to the improvement of relations between the two German
                            governments, representatives of the United States and GDR negotiated
                            arrangements for U.S. recognition of the GDR and the establishment of
                            diplomatic relations, which occurred on September 4, 1974, when the
                            United States and East Germany released a joint communiqué to that
                            effect. The American Embassy in <placeName key="berlin"
                                >Berlin</placeName> was established on December 9, 1974, with <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/grove-brandon-hambright-jr"
                                >Brandon H. Grove, Jr.</ref>, as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic"
                                >ad interim</hi>. <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/cooper-john-sherman">John Sherman
                                Cooper</ref> presented his credentials as the first U.S. Ambassador
                            to the GDR on December 20, 1974. Despite this step taken to deal with
                            the reality of the German situation, the United States continued until
                            German reunification in 1990 to view the FRG as the sole legitimate
                            successor government of the historical German state and a future
                            reunified Germany.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>International Recognition of Reunified Germany, <date from="1909"
                                to="1991">1990-91</date>.</head>
                        <p>Following the collapse of one-party rule in East Germany in late-1989,
                            the signing of a Unification Treaty by East and West German Governments
                            on August 31, 1990, and a series of meetings between the foreign
                            ministers of East and West Germany, the United States, Great Britain,
                            France, and the Soviet Union in Bonn, Berlin, Paris, and Moscow, a
                            Treaty on the Final Settlement with Respect to Germany (the so-called
                            “Two Plus Four Agreement”) was signed in Moscow on September 12,
                            1990.</p>
                        <p>On September 25, 1990, President <persName>George H.W. Bush</persName>
                            submitted the treaty for ratification, and the U.S. Senate obliged
                            unanimously on October 10. The treaty finally went into effect on March
                            15, 1991. Since the five constituent federal states of the German
                            Democratic Republic were technically absorbed by the Federal Republic of
                            Germany under the terms of Article 23 of the “Basic Law” (which was
                            subsequently abolished under the terms of the Unification Treaty so as
                            to limit any further changes to the borders of Germany), there was no
                            reason for the United States to recognize the reunified Germany as a
                            “new state.” The United States maintained its embassy in Bonn; however,
                            it closed its embassy in Berlin on October 2, 1990.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>American Embassy Moves from Bonn to Berlin, <date when="1999"
                                >1999</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United States moved its embassy in Germany from Bonn to Berlin on
                            July 7, 1999. Upon this move, the former-Embassy Bonn became the U.S.
                            Office Bonn, and finally closed on April 3, 2000.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/3997.htm">Germany</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/gm">Germany</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back> </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
