<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: The Grand Duchy of
                    Tuscany</title>
                <title type="short">The Grand Duchy of Tuscany*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, February 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The <placeName xml:id="qu">Grand Duchy of Tuscany</placeName> was an independent
                    and sovereign state in 1776 when the United States declared independence from
                    Great Britain. Although the U.S. Continental Congress appointed a Commissioner
                    to the Court of the Grand Duke of Tuscany on July 1, 1777, the U.S.
                    representative, <persName>Ralph Izard</persName>, was never officially received
                    in Florence. He was recalled on June 8, 1779. The U.S. established a consular
                    office in the Tuscan port of <placeName xml:id="livorno">Leghorn
                        (Livorno)</placeName> as early as 1794, thus obtaining official recognition
                    from the Grand Duchy; yet, full diplomatic relations were never established
                    prior to Tuscany’s incorporation into the Kingdom of Italy in 1860.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Grand Duchy of Tuscany’s Recognition of the United States, <date
                            when="1794">1794</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Grand Duchy of Tuscany recognized the United States when it received the
                        first U.S. consular agent to serve within the grand duchy, Philip Felicchi
                        (sometimes spelled as Feliechy), who was stationed at Leghorn (Livorno) from
                        May 29, 1794 through on December 7, 1796.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The first U.S. consulate was established in the Tuscan port city of
                        Leghorn (Livorno).</head>
                    <p>U.S. Consular agent <persName>Philip Felicchi</persName> was appointed on May
                        29, 1794. The Government of the Grand Duchy of Tuscany refused to recognize
                        U.S. consular agents posted in Florence; thus the first U.S. consular agent
                        to serve Florence was Vice Consular Agent <persName>James
                        Ombrosi</persName>, who was under mandate from the U.S. consulate at Leghorn
                        (Livorno). Ombrosi was accredited on May 15, 1819.</p>
                    <p>The first representative of Tuscany in the United States was <persName>John
                            F. Mansony</persName>, whose exequatur as Consul for the States of New
                        Hampshire, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, Vermont, and Connecticut (with
                        residence at Boston) was signed by President <persName>James
                            Monroe</persName> on November 6, 1817. The representatives of the Grand
                        Duchy of Tuscany in the United States continued to be consular officers. The
                        last representative of Tuscany in the United States was <persName>G.B.
                            Tagliaferri</persName>, whose exequatur as Consul at New York was signed
                        by President <persName>Franklin Pierce</persName> on November 1, 1854.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>No Diplomatic Relations Established.</head>
                    <p>The Grand Duchy of Tuscany and the United States never established diplomatic
                        relations.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>No bilateral treaties or agreements between the United States and the
                        Grand Duchy of Tuscany.</head>
                    <p>There were no bilateral treaties or agreements between the United States and
                        the Grand Duchy of Tuscany signed prior to the Grand Duchy’s incorporation
                        into the Kingdom of Italy in 1860. There were, however, several attempts to
                        sign a treaty of commerce with the Grand Duchy. The earliest of such
                        attempts was in 1784 when U.S. Ministers Plenipotentiary <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/franklin-benjamin">Benjamin
                            Franklin</ref>, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john">John
                            Adams</ref>, and <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas
                            Jefferson</ref> tried to negotiate a treaty of amity and commerce
                        between the two states. By January 1785, the process of negotiating such an
                        agreement ground to a halt, for reasons unknown.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Appointment of First U.S. Representative to the Grand Duchy of Tuscany,
                            <date when="1777">1777</date>.</head>
                    <p>In the early years of the American Revolution, the Continental Congress
                        appointed senator and diplomat <persName>Ralph Izard</persName> as
                        Commissioner to the Court of the Grand Duke of Tuscany on July 1, 1777.
                        Izard was charged on February 4, 1778, with trying to secure a loan from the
                        Grand Duke of $1,000,000 to help finance the war. Learning in advance of the
                        high probability that the Grand Duke would refuse to receive him in Florence
                        for fear of upsetting the British, Izard never proceeded to Tuscany. For
                        Tuscany, good ties with the British Navy in the Mediterranean were a
                        necessity in order to maintain trade and commercial ties. Once it became
                        clear that the Grand Duke would not recognize the United States, Izard’s
                        mission was terminated on June 8, 1779.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Proclamation of the Kingdom of Italy, <date when="1861"
                        >1861</date>.</head>
                    <p>The aftermath of the Franco-Austrian War brought about a series of
                        plebiscites in the northern Italian states. By going to the ballot box, the
                        states voted to join Piedmont-Sardinia, with the ultimate goal of unifying
                        the entire peninsula. It should be noted that Piedmont-Sardinia was one of
                        the more powerful states in the peninsula, as well as having one of the most
                        liberal political systems. Garibaldi’s march to “liberate” the Kingdom of
                        the Two Sicilies in 1860 brought the southern peninsula into the fold, and
                        the new Kingdom of Italy was proclaimed on March 17, 1861, with the royal
                        family of Piedmont-Sardinia as the new ruling monarchs of Italy.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Trade and Commerce.</head>
                    <p>During the early years of the republic, the United States sought to promote
                        trade abroad and to ensure that American vessels, both public and private,
                        would be welcomed in ports around the world. Therefore, Tuscan recognition
                        of the United States early-on was beneficial to U.S. trade and commerce.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Howard R. Marraro, <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic Relations Between the
                            United States and the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies. Volume I:
                            1816-1850</hi>, (New York: S.F. Vanni (Ragusa), 1951.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
