<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Greece</title>
                <title type="short">Greece</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by David Nickles, March 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The United States recognized the independence of Greece with its decision on
                    November 7, 1837 to empower the American minister at London to negotiate a
                    treaty with that country.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="greece-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Greece</head>
                </figure>
                <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                    <head>Recognition</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>U.S. Recognition of Greek Independence, <date when="1837"
                            >1837</date>.</head>
                        <p>On April 26, 1837, the Greek Minister at London sent a note to <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/stevenson-andrew">Andrew
                                Stevenson</ref>, the U.S. Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                            Plenipotentiary at London, expressing a desire to establish relations of
                            navigation with the United States. In response, the United States
                            government on November 7, 1837, empowered Stevenson, <quote>“to enter
                                upon the negotiation of a treaty of commerce and navigation between
                                the United States and his Majesty the King of Greece.”</quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>In an earlier episode in April 1833, <placeName>Great
                            Britain</placeName>, <placeName>France</placeName>, and
                                <placeName>Russia</placeName> sent the United States an invitation
                            to acknowledge Prince <persName>Otho</persName> (or Otto) of Bavaria as
                            King of Greece. In response, Secretary of State <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/livingston-edward"> Edward
                                Livingston</ref> sent an ambiguous reply on April 30, 1833,
                            expressing willingness to recognize Prince Otho without actually doing
                            so: <quote> “This note has been laid before the President of the United
                                States, who has directed the Undersigned to inform the Ministers
                                Plenipotentiary of the said three Powers that it has been the
                                principle, and the invariable practice of the U.S. to recognize that
                                as the legal Government of another nation, which, by its
                                establishment in the actual exercise of political power might be
                                supposed to have received the express or implied assent of the
                                people, and that he is therefore happy that the assurance given by
                                the three mediating powers, that they were duly authorized to make
                                the arrangement they announce, by the people of Greece, will enable
                                him on the part of the United States, without departing from their
                                known principles in similar cases, to acknowledge the Prince Otho of
                                Bavaria, as the King of Greece, and to comply with the request of
                                the high mediating powers, on his reception by the people of that
                                country as their Sovereign.”</quote>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                    <head>Consular Presence</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Consular Relations, <date when="1837"
                            >1837</date>.</head>
                        <p>On June 27, 1837, the United States appointed <persName>Gregory A.
                                Perdicaris</persName> to be its first Consul to Greece. He took up
                            his post at <placeName key="athens">Athens</placeName> on January 7,
                            1838.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in
                            Greece, <date when="1868">1868</date>.</head>
                        <p>On March 11, 1868, the United States appointed <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/tuckerman-charles-keating">Charles
                                K. Tuckerman</ref> as its first Minister Resident in Athens. He
                            presented his credentials on June 16, 1868.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Closure of American Legation in Athens and Opening of Legation in
                            London, <date when="1941">1941</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United State closed its Legation in Athens on July 14, 1941, due to
                            the German occupation of Greece. <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/biddle-anthony-joseph-drexel-jr"
                                >Anthony J. Drexel Biddle, Jr.</ref>, who was appointed Envoy
                            Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Greece on November 13,
                            1941, served near the Government of Greece established in England. He
                            was also commissioned to the exile governments of Belgium,
                            Czechoslovakia, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, Norway, Poland, and
                            Yugoslavia.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1942"
                                >1942</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United States promoted <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/biddle-anthony-joseph-drexel-jr"
                                >Anthony J. Drexel Biddle, Jr.</ref>, to be the new Ambassador
                            Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary to the Government of Greece on
                            September 29, 1942. Biddle had previously served as Envoy Extraordinary
                            and Minister Plenipotentiary of the United States to that government.
                            Biddle presented his credentials on October 30, 1942.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>American Embassy Moved to Cairo, <date when="1943">1943</date>.</head>
                        <p>The Government of Greece relocated from Great Britain to Egypt. <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/kirk-alexander-comstock">Alexander
                                C. Kirk</ref> was appointed Ambassador Extraordinary and
                            Plenipotentiary to Greece on June 4, 1943, and resided in Cairo in order
                            to be near the Government of Greece established in Greece. Kirk was also
                            accredited to Egypt and Saudi Arabia.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>American Embassy Returned to Athens, <date when="1944"
                            >1944</date>.</head>
                        <p>
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/macveagh-lincoln">Lincoln
                                MacVeagh</ref>, who was appointed the Ambassador Extraordinary and
                            Plenipotentiary to Greece on November 12, 1943, initially resided in
                            Cairo, but transferred the Embassy to <placeName>Athens</placeName> on
                            October 27, 1944.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties &amp; Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Commerce and Navigation, <date when="1837">1837</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 22, 1837, the United States and Greece signed a Treaty of
                        Commerce and Navigation.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <!--<bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-greece/">Greece</ref></bibl>-->
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/greece/">Greece</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
