<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Guatemala</title>
                <title type="short">Guatemala</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Nathaniel Smith, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Guatemala and the United States first established relations in 1824 when
                    Guatemala was a member of the Federation of Central American States. The United
                    States established relations with an independent Guatemala in 1844. In response
                    to a devastating earthquake in Guatemala the U.S. Congress passed the Guatemala
                    Relief and Rehabilitation Act of 1976 to provide emergency relief,
                    rehabilitation, and humanitarian assistance.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="guatemala.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Guatemala</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States Recognition of the Federation of Central American States,
                            <date when="1824">1824</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following its independence from Spain in 1821, Guatemala joined the
                        Federation of Central American States in 1823 along with
                            <placeName>Honduras</placeName>, <placeName>Nicaragua</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Costa Rica</placeName>, and <placeName>El
                            Salvador</placeName>. The United States recognized the Federation when
                        President <persName>James Monroe</persName> received <persName>Antonio José
                            Cañaz</persName> as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary on
                        August 4, 1824.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>States Recognition of Independent Guatemala, <date when="1844"
                        >1844</date>.</head>
                    <p>Independent Guatemala was recognized on April 5, 1844 by the issuance of an
                        exequatur to a Guatemalan Consul-General <persName>Antonío de
                            Aycinena</persName>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1824"
                        >1824</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on August 4, 1824, when President James
                        Monroe received <persName>Antonio José Cañaz</persName> as Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary on August 4, 1824.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Legation in Guatemala, <date when="1826"
                            >1826</date>.</head>
                    <p>Chargé d’Affaires <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/williams-john">John
                            Williams</ref> presented his credentials to the Federation of Central
                        American States on May 3, 1826.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations with Independent Guatemala, <date
                            when="1849">1849</date>.</head>
                    <p>Chargé d’Affaires <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hise-elijah">Elijah
                            Hise</ref> presented his credentials to the Republic of Guatemala on or
                        shortly before January 21, 1849.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Legation Raised to Embassy, <date when="1882">1882</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation in Guatemala was raised to Embassy status when <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hall-henry-cook">Henry C. Hall</ref>,
                        Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary, presented his credentials
                        on August 10, 1882.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Normal Relations Interrupted, <date when="1954">1954</date>.</head>
                    <p>In June 1954 the U.S. Central Intelligence Agency, concerned about the threat
                        of communism in Guatemala, assisted in the overthrow of the government led
                        by President <persName>Jacobo Arbenz Guzmán</persName>, who had won election
                        in November 1950. On July 2, 1954, according to a pact concluded at San
                        Salvador, a five-member junta headed by Colonel <persName>Elfego H.
                            Monzon</persName> assumed power. Communications between the U.S.
                        Government and Guatemalan Foreign Minister <persName>Carlos Salazar
                            Gática</persName> confirmed the new Guatemalan Government’s intention to
                        fulfill international obligations. The Department of State consulted with
                        the Governments of all the other American Republics and determined that the
                        new Guatemalan government intended to fulfill international obligations, was
                        non-communist, enjoyed popular support, and controlled the entirety of
                        Guatemalan territory.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Relations Resumed, <date when="1954">1954</date>.</head>
                    <p>On July 12, 1954 Secretary of State <persName>John Foster Dulles</persName>
                        instructed the U.S. Embassy at <placeName key="guatemala-city">Guatemala
                            City</placeName> to establish diplomatic relations with the new
                        Guatemalan Government. The following day, Ambassador <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/peurifoy-john-emil">John E.
                            Peurifoy</ref> informed Foreign Minister Salazar of the U.S. recognition
                        of the new Government in Guatemala.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2045.htm">Guatemala</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/p/wha/ci/gt/index.htm">Guatemala</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
