<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Hanover</title>
                <title type="short">Hanover*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States announced its independence from Great Britain in 1776,
                        <placeName xml:id="xx">Hanover</placeName> was a sovereign, independent
                    state. Previously an Electorate, the Kingdom of Hanover was re-established in
                    1814 after the Napoleonic Wars. At the time, the King of Hanover was
                        <persName>George III</persName> of Britain. From 1814 until 1837 the King of
                    Hanover was the same man as the King of Britain (George III, George IV, and
                    William I). As Hanover (and most of the German States) observed Salic Law and
                    Great Britain did not, the passing of King William in 1837 meant that the
                    Hanovarian crown descended through the male bloodline to Ernest Augustus I of
                    Hanover, while the British crown went to Queen Victoria.</p>
                <p>Despite the fact that the Kings of Hanover had recognized the U.S. within their
                    capacity as Kings of Britain as early as 1783, the first act of mutual
                    recognition between the Kingdom of Hanover and the United States did not occur
                    until 1830. Between 1830 and 1861 no less than four different agreements were
                    negotiated and signed between the two countries. All ties came to an abrupt halt
                    when Hanover was defeated during the Austro-Prussian War of 1866 and
                    subsequently merged directly into Prussia. At this point, Hanover had relations
                    with the United States as a part of the Kingdom of Prussia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1830">1830</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first known act of mutual recognition between the Kingdom of Hanover and
                        the United States occurred on January 8, 1830, when U.S. Secretary of State
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/van-buren-martin">Martin Van
                            Buren</ref> granted an exequatur to <persName>Theodore Meyer
                            Esq.</persName> to serve as Consul for the Kingdom of Hanover at New
                        York.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations.</head>
                    <p>Despite the fact that the Kings of Hanover, acting as Kings of Britain, had
                        recognized the United States in 1783 with the signing of the peace treaty
                        that ended the war between Britain and the United States, the U.S. never
                        officially established diplomatic relations with the Kingdom of Hanover.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Commerce and Navigation, <date when="1840">1840</date>.</head>
                    <p>On May 20, 1840, U.S. Minister to Prussia <persName>Henry Wheaton</persName>
                        and Hanovarian Minister to Prussia <persName>Le Sieur Auguste de
                            Berger</persName> negotiated and signed a Treaty of Commerce and
                        Navigation between the United States and the Kingdom of Hanover,
                        establishing the rules and regulations of trade and commerce between the two
                        states.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Commerce and Navigation, <date when="1846">1846</date>.</head>
                    <p>The 1846 Treaty of Commerce and Navigation signed on June 10, 1846, by the
                        United States and the Kingdom of Hanover settled in a more definitive manner
                        the rules to be observed by the original Treaty of Commerce and Navigation
                        of 1840. This treaty was terminated when Hanover was forced to merge into
                        Prussia in 1866.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Extradition Treaty, <date when="1855">1855</date>.</head>
                    <p>On January 18, 1855, U.S. Minister to Great Britain <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/buchanan-james">James Buchanan</ref>,
                        and Hanovarian Minister to Britain <persName>Count Adolphus von
                            Kielmansegge</persName> negotiated an Extradition Treaty between their
                        two states. The treaty was signed in London and was terminated eleven years
                        later when Hanover merged into Prussia after the Austro-Prussian War of
                        1866.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention Abolishing Stade or Brunshausen Dues, <date when="1861"
                            >1861</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States and the Kingdom of Hanover signed the Convention Abolishing
                        Stade or Brunshausen Dues on November 6, 1861. The treaty was negotiated and
                        signed by U.S. Minister to Prussia <persName>Norman B. Judd</persName> and
                        Hanovarian Minister to Prussia Lt. Col. And Extrarodinary Aid-de-Camp
                            <persName>August Wilhelm von Reitzenstein</persName>. It abolished the
                        toll previously levied <quote>“on cargoes of American vessels ascending the
                            Elbe, and passing the mouth of the river called Schwinge, designated
                            under the name of the Stade or Brunshausen dues.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The Austro-Prussian War of <date when="1866">1866</date>.</head>
                    <p>In 1866 Prussia and her allies launched a war against Austria and her allied
                        German states. The war, also commonly referred to as the Seven Weeks’ War
                        for the rapidity with which the Prussians triumphed, enabled the Kingdom of
                        Prussia to absorb some of the smaller states that had sided with Austria –
                        in this case, the Kingdom of Hanover.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>German Unification.</head>
                    <p>Hanover participated in German unification during the mid-nineteenth century.
                        (See “<ref target="/countries/issues/german-unification">Unification of
                            German States</ref>” for greater detail.)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Charles I. Beavans, <hi rend="italic">Treaties and Other International
                            Agreements of the United States of America, 1776-1949,</hi> (Department
                        of State: Washington, DC, 1971), Volume 8..</bibl>
                    <bibl>William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909 </hi>(Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law</hi>
                        (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
