<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Hanseatic
                    Republics</title>
                <title type="short">Hanseatic Republics*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The <placeName xml:id="xp">Hanseatic Republics</placeName> were composed of the
                    three Free Hanseatic Cities that remained by the late eighteenth century:
                        <placeName xml:id="bremen">Bremen</placeName>, <placeName xml:id="lubeck"
                        >Lübeck</placeName>, and <placeName xml:id="hamburg">Hamburg</placeName>.
                    When the United States announced its independence from Great Britain in 1776,
                    these three Free Cities were sovereign, independent city-states within the Holy
                    Roman Empire. <persName>Napoleon Bonaparte</persName> dissolved the Holy Roman
                    Empire in 1806, and in 1811 annexed Bremen, Lübeck, and Hamburg directly to the
                    First French Empire. The three Hanseatic cities regained independence in 1813,
                    and the 1815 Congress of Vienna reaffirmed that Bremen, Lübeck, and Hamburg were
                    independent and sovereign city-states.</p>
                <p>Historically major trading hubs for the northern German States and Baltic Sea,
                    the three cities joined together to conduct one streamlined policy in their
                    relations with the United States during the nineteenth century. Yet, each
                    Hanseatic city remained independent of the others. After initial recognition in
                    the 1790s, relations were expanded in the following decades, driven by the
                    increased trade and commercial ties between the Hanseatic Cities and the United
                    States. By the late 1840s, Bremen was one of the main ports through which goods
                    moved between the United States and the German States.</p>
                <p>Direct diplomatic relations between the United States and the Hanseatic Republics
                    were established in 1853 but were severed in 1868 when the three republics
                    joined the North German Confederation. Three years later at the conclusion of
                    the process of German unification, the three republics entered into the German
                    Empire. From this point forward, foreign policy of the German Empire was made in
                    Berlin, with the German Kaiser (who was also the King of Prussia) accrediting
                    ambassadors of foreign nations. Relations with the German Empire were severed
                    when the U.S. declared war upon Imperial Germany in 1917.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Acts of Recognition, <date from="1790" to="1793"
                        >1790-1793</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first known act of recognition between the United States and Hamburg came
                        in 1790 when the Free City of Hamburg accepted the credentials of U.S. Vice
                        Consul <persName>John Parish</persName>, who was appointed to that position
                        on June 17, 1790. Additionally, on February 19, 1793, the U.S. Congress
                        resolved that John Parish was to be accredited as U.S. Consul in
                        Hamburg.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Recognition between the U.S. and Bremen, <date when="1794"
                        >1794</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first known act of recognition between the United States and Bremen was
                        in 1794 when <persName>Arnold Delius</persName>, who on May 28, 1794, was
                        appointed as U.S. Consul at Bremen, arrived to open the first U.S. consulate
                        in that city. The U.S. did not open a consulate in Lübeck until August 6,
                        1824.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Hanseatic Representation in the U.S., <date when="1827-12-04">December 4,
                            1827</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first time that the Hanseatic Republics were represented in the United
                        States Government as a joint delegation came on December 4, 1827, when the
                        U.S. received Hanseatic Republic Minister Plenipotentiary near the United
                        States of America <persName>Vincent Rumpff</persName>. Rumpff was sent to
                        the United States to negotiate and sign the first treaty between the United
                        States and the three Hanseatic Republics.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>First consulate opens in Bremen, <date when="1794-05-29">May 29,
                            1794</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. Consulate to open in Bremen was on May 29, 1794, which closed
                        in September 1985.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. consulate opens in Bremerhaven, <date when="1882-06-27">June 27,
                            1882</date>.</head>
                    <p>Another U.S. consulate was opened in nearby Bremerhaven on June 27, 1882,
                        which closed on May 1, 1949. (Bremerhaven became part of Bremen in 1947,
                        after the Second World War.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. consulate opens in Hamburg, <date when="1790-06-17">June 17,
                            1790</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. Consulate to open in Hamburg was on June 17, 1790. It closed
                        on January 2, 1967.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. consulate opens in Lübeck, <date when="1824-08-06">August 6,
                            1824</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Consulate in Lübeck opened on August 6, 1824 and closed on March 1,
                        1916.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. consulate opens in Hanseatic and Free Cities, <date when="1857-01-24"
                            >January 24, 1857</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Consulate to the Hanseatic and Free Cities opened on January 24,
                        1857 and closed on July 17, 1862.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1853"
                        >1853</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established diplomatic relations with the Hanseatic
                        Republics in October 1853 when it received <persName>Rudolph
                            Schleiden</persName> as Minister Resident of the Hanseatic Legation in
                        Washington D.C.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Relations, <date when="1868">1868</date>.</head>
                    <p>On September 25, 1868, the Hanseatic Republic Acting Chargé d’Affaires
                            <persName>A. Schumacker</persName> presented the letters of recall of
                            <persName>Dr. Johannes Rosing</persName>, the Hanseatic Republic’s
                        Chargé d’Affaires. The withdrawal of the Hanseatic mission was due to the
                        three Republics (Bremen, Hamburg, and Lübeck) joining the North German
                        Union.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention of Friendship, Commerce, and Navigation, <date when="1827"
                            >1827</date>.</head>
                    <p>A Convention of Friendship, Commerce, and Navigation was signed between the
                        United States and the Hanseatic Republics on December 20, 1827, which
                        facilitated commercial intercourse and navigational privileges. The
                        Convention was signed by U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/clay-henry">Henry Clay</ref> and the
                        Hanseatic Republic Minister Plenipotentiary near the United States of
                        America <persName>Vincent Rumpff</persName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Additional Article to Convention of <date from="1827" to="1828">1827,
                            1828</date>.</head>
                    <p>On June 7, 1828, and Additional Article to the Convention of 1827 was signed
                        by the United States and the Hanseatic Republics, which conferred greater
                        powers upon each other’s consuls and vice-consuls.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Consular Convention, <date when="1852">1852</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States and the Hanseatic Republics signed a Consular Convention on
                        April 30, 1852, which further extended the jurisdiction of their respective
                        Consuls. With this agreement, consuls and vice-consuls could now act as
                        judges and arbitrators to mediate differences between masters and crews of
                        vessels of their respective nations.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Declaration of Accession of the Senate of the Free Hanseatic City of
                        Bremen to the Convention for the Extradition of Criminals, Fugitives From
                        Justice, Between Prussia and Other States of the Germanic Confederation and
                        the United States, <date when="1853">1853</date>.</head>
                    <p>On September 6, 1853, the Declaration of Accession of the Senate of the Free
                        Hanseatic City of Bremen to the Convention for the Extradition of Criminals,
                        Fugitives from Justice, between Prussia and Other States of the Germanic
                        Confederation and the United States was signed by the President of the
                        Senate of Bremen, Herr Smidt.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Bremen, Lübeck, and Hamburg Join the North German Confederation, <date
                            when="1867" to="1868">1867-68</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following the Austro-Prussian War of 1866, several German states joined to
                        form the North German Confederation, with the King of Prussia acting as head
                        of the union. All three Hanseatic Republics joined the North German
                        Confederation, thus, diplomatic relations between Bremen, Lübeck, and
                        Hamburg and the United States drew to a close in 1868.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Bremen, Lübeck, and Hamburg Join the German Empire, <date when="1871"
                            >1871</date>.</head>
                    <p>The three Hanseatic Republics joined the German Empire, which was proclaimed
                        on January 18, 1871.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="relevant-issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Trade and Commerce.</head>
                    <p>Trade was a major element to shape U.S. foreign policy towards the three
                        Hanseatic Republics, especially as, in the first half of the nineteenth
                        century, Bremen, Hamburg, and Lübeck were the main ports for goods entering
                        or exiting the German states.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi> (Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910).</bibl>
                    <bibl>History of U.S. Recognition and Relations: <ref
                            target="/countries/germany">Germany</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>A Century of Lawmaking: <ref
                            target="http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/amlaw/lawhome.html">U.S.
                            Congressional Documents, 1775-1874</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
