<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Hawaii</title>
                <title type="short">Hawaii*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The <placeName xml:id="xl">Hawaiian Islands</placeName> were first discovered by
                    the West in 1778 by Captain <persName>James Cook</persName>. At the time, Cook
                    named the island chain the Sandwich Islands after the British Earl of Sandwich.
                    Hawaiian <persName>King Kamehameha </persName>I placed the not-yet-united
                    Hawaiian Kingdom under British protection during the British naval expeditions
                    led by <persName>George Vancouver</persName> from 1792 to 1794. However, the
                    British government took no formal action to enforce its sovereignty over Hawaii.
                    In 1810, Kamehameha I united the Hawaiian Islands under his rule when the island
                    of Kauai came under his suzerainty.</p>
                <p>In 1827, a council meeting to formulate a Hawaiian legal code decided to refrain
                    from seeking British approval for the new code, after which point the Hawaiian
                    government ceased to engage in formal actions which would place it under British
                    suzerainty. Great Britain issued a formal joint declaration with France on
                    November 28, 1843, guaranteeing Hawaiian independence.</p>
                <p>The United States pursued an independent policy with regards to Hawaii. In a
                    treaty signed December 23, 1826, the United States formally recognized Hawaiian
                    independence. The U.S. established diplomatic relations with Hawaii in 1853;
                    however, such relations and Hawaiian independence ended with the kingdom’s
                    annexation to the United States on August 12, 1898, following the Senate passage
                    of a joint Congressional resolution on July 6, which was signed by U.S.
                    President William McKinley the next day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Hawaiian Independence, <date when="1826"
                        >1826</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 23, 1826, the U.S. signed a treaty with the Kingdom of Hawaii
                        thus indirectly recognizing Hawaiian independence.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Port of Honolulu, <date when="1820-09-19">September 19,
                        1820</date>.</head>
                    <p>
                        <persName>John Coffin Jones, Jr.</persName> (also known in Hawaiian
                        documents as John Aluli) was appointed Agent for Commerce and Seamen on
                        September 19, 1820. He began to serve in October of 1820, at the <placeName
                            xml:id="honolulu">port of Honolulu</placeName>. The post of commercial
                        agent was raised to consul effective July 5, 1844, and held by
                            <persName>Peter A. Brinsmade</persName>, who had already been appointed
                        commercial agent on April 13, 1838.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head><placeName xml:id="hilo">Hilo</placeName>.</head>
                    <p>Earliest Date: <date when="1852-08-31">August 31, 1852</date>. Latest Date:
                            <date when="1898-09-12">August 12, 1898</date> (date of annexation).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Honolulu.</head>
                    <p>Earliest Date: <date when="1820-10">October, 1820</date>.Latest Date: <date
                            when="1863-06-19">June 19, 1863</date> (seems to indicate the elevation
                        of Consulate to Legation. Consular functions continued, with the last extant
                        consular officer date of June 1, 1897.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head><placeName xml:id="kahului">Kahului</placeName>.</head>
                    <p>Earliest Date: <date when="1880-09-20">August 20, 1880</date>. Latest Date:
                            <date when="1898-09-12">August 12, 1898</date>. Kahului is located on
                        the island of Maui.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head><placeName xml:id="lahaina">Lahaina</placeName> (Rahaina).</head>
                    <p>Earliest Date: <date when="1850-04-22">April 22, 1850</date> (confirmation of
                        appointment of consul) Latest Date: <date when="1869-04-09">April 9,
                            1869</date> (confirmation of appointment of consul). Before 1845,
                        Lahaina was the capital of Hawaii. Lahaina is located on the island of
                        Maui.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head><placeName xml:id="mahukona">Mahukona</placeName>.</head>
                    <p>Earliest Date: <date when="1882-09-15">September 15, 1882</date>. Latest
                        Date: <date when="1898-09-12">August 12, 1898</date> (date of annexation).
                        Mahukona is located on the island of Hawaii.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation at
                        Honolulu, <date when="1853">1853</date>.</head>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/gregg-david-l">David L. Gregg</ref>
                        presented his credentials as U.S. Commissioner to the Kingdom of Hawaii on
                        December 20, 1853. Gregg referred to the Mission at Honolulu as a Legation
                        in his first dispatch from Hawaii on December 27, 1853.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of the U.S. Representative to the Kingdom of Hawaii to Minister,
                            <date when="1863">1863</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. Minister Resident to the Kingdom of Hawaii was <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/mcbride-james">James McBride</ref>,
                        who presented his credentials on June 19, 1863. The first U.S. Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to the Kingdom of Hawaii was <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/stevens-john-leavitt">John L.
                            Stevens</ref>, who presented his credentials on September 8, 1890.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Relations and Closure of the American Legation, <date
                            when="1898">1898</date>.</head>
                    <p>Hawaiian independence ended with the formal U.S. annexation of Hawaii on
                        August 12, 1898, following the Senate passage of a joint Congressional
                        resolution on July 6, which was signed by U.S. President <persName>William
                            McKinley</persName> the next day. Owing to U.S. annexation of Hawaii,
                        the legation ceased to exist on August 12, 1898. <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/sewall-harold-marsh">Harold
                            Sewall</ref>, the last Envoy Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary, became
                        Special Agent.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Friendship, Commerce, and Navigation Between the United States
                        and the Sandwich Islands (Hawaii), <date when="1826">1826</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 23, 1826, the U.S. signed articles of arrangement in the typical
                        form of a treaty of friendship, commerce, and navigation with the Kingdom of
                        Hawaii in Honolulu, which confirmed the peace and friendship between the
                        peoples of the two countries. The agreement was signed by the captain of the
                        U.S. sloop of war Peacock Thomas ap Catesby Jones, who was appointed by the
                        U.S., and Guardians of Kauikeaouli, King of the Sandwich Islands: Elisabeta
                        Kaahumanu, the Queen Regent; Karaimoku, the Prime Minister; Boki, Governor
                        of Oahu and personal guardian of the King; Howapili, guardian of Nahienaena,
                        sister of the King; and Lidia Namahana, who was a dowager queen of
                        Kamehameha I. This was the first treaty that the Kingdom of Hawaii signed
                        with any foreign power. It was never ratified by Congress, although both
                        countries acted in accordance with its articles.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Friendship, Commerce, and Navigation and Extradition, <date
                            when="1849">1849</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 20, 1849, the U.S. and the Kingdom of Hawaii signed a Treaty of
                        Friendship, Commerce, and Navigation and Extradition. The treaty, negotiated
                        by U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/clayton-john-middleton">John M.
                            Clayton</ref> and the Hawaiian special Commissioner to the Government of
                        the United States <persName>James Jackson Jarves</persName>, was signed in
                        Washington, D.C.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Reciprocity, <date when="1875">1875</date>.</head>
                    <p>On January 30, 1875, United States Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/fish-hamilton">Hamilton Fish</ref> and
                        the Kingdom of Hawaii’s Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to
                        the United States <persName>Elisha H. Allen</persName> signed a Treaty of
                        Reciprocity. This treaty provided for duty-free import of Hawaiian
                        agricultural products into the United States. Conversely, the Kingdom of
                        Hawaii allowed U.S. agricultural products and manufactured goods to enter
                        Hawaiian ports duty-free. This treaty was originally intended to last for a
                        duration of seven years.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Reciprocity Convention, <date when="1884">1884</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 6, 1884, the United States and the Kingdom of Hawaii signed a
                        Reciprocity Convention, pertaining to commercial reciprocity, which was an
                        extension of the 1875 Treaty of Reciprocity.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="relevant-issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Whaling Industry.</head>
                    <p>By the 1820s, the U.S. whaling industry established itself in the Hawaiian
                        Islands, as there were greater numbers of whales to be found in the Pacific
                        than the Atlantic Ocean. By the 1860s, however, the whaling industry on the
                        whole was in decline, which meant that there were fewer American vessels
                        scouting the oceans for whales and less need for American whaling vessel
                        depots in Hawaii. The decline of the U.S. whaling industry in the Hawaiian
                        Islands coincided with the discovery of petroleum in Pennsylvania, and the
                        start of the first age of oil. Also, by the latter half of the nineteenth
                        century, whale bones were no longer used as widely in manufactured goods
                        (such as corsets) thanks to the invention of steel during the Second
                        Industrial Revolution (1870-1914).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Missionary Work.</head>
                    <p>During the 1820s, American missionaries began to descend on the Hawaiian
                        Islands. The earliest American missionaries to settle in the Hawaiian
                        Islands were Protestants from New England. They were followed by Roman
                        Catholic missionaries.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Sugar Trade.</head>
                    <p>The climate and soil of the Hawaiian Islands were ideal for producing sugar
                        cane; thus an entire industry was encouraged by American commercial trade in
                        the Hawaiian Islands. This was especially so after the demise of the whaling
                        industry in the 1860s; by the 1870s the sugar cane industry started to
                        supplant it as one of the more profitable commercial trades between the U.S.
                        and the Hawaiian Islands. Of note, from the late 1860s through the 1898 U.S.
                        annexation of Hawaii, there was a significant inflow of Japanese workers
                        into the Hawaiian Islands to work the sugar cane fields.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Edmund Janes Carpenter, <hi rend="italic">America in Hawaii: A History of
                            United States Influence in the Hawaiian Islands .</hi> (Boston: Small,
                        Maynard &amp; Company, 1899).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Richard Simpson Kuykendall, <hi rend="italic">The Hawaiian Kingdom, vol.
                            1: Foundation and Transformation.</hi>( Honolulu: University of Hawaii
                        Press, 1938, reprinted 1968). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Hunter Miller, ed. <hi rend="italic">Treaties and Other International Acts
                            of the United States of America</hi> (Washington: State Department,
                        1933), III, 249-260. </bibl>
                    <bibl>George H. Stauffer, “The Hawai’i-United States Treaty of 1826,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Hawaiian Journal of History</hi>, 17(1983), 40-63.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
