<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Hesse</title>
                <title type="short">Hesse*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States announced its independence from Great Britain in 1776,
                        <placeName xml:id="xq">Hesse</placeName> was a sovereign, independent state.
                    With the dissolution of the Holy Roman Empire in Central Europe in 1806, the
                    Landgraviate of Hesse-Darmstadt was elevated to the Grand Duchy of Hesse. The
                    first act of mutual recognition between the two states occurred in 1829 with the
                    accreditation of the first U.S. consul to Hesse, and relations between the two
                    countries expanded through 1871. During the Austro-Prussian War of 1866, Hesse
                    fought on the side of Austria, and in 1867 Hesse’s territories north of the Main
                    River joined the North German Confederation, whose foreign policy was made and
                    conducted out of Berlin. The entirety of the Grand Duchy of Hesse joined the
                    German Empire in 1871. From this point forward, foreign policy of the German
                    Empire was made in Berlin, with the German Kaiser (who was also the King of
                    Prussia) accrediting ambassadors of foreign nations. Relations with Imperial
                    Germany were severed when the U.S. declared war in 1917.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1829">1829</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first known act of mutual recognition between the Grand Duchy of Hesse
                        and the United States occurred on when the first U.S. Consul to Hesse
                        (Hesse-Darndstadt), <persName>Frederick Kahl</persName>, presented his
                        credentials in 1829. Kahl was appointed on May 14, 1829.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Grand Duchy of Hesse, <date when="1829-05-14">May 14, 1829</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. Consulate to open in the Grand Duchy of Hesse was on May 14,
                        1829, which closed on August 29, 1872. There was a U.S. Consulate in
                            <placeName xml:id="hessen-romberg">Hessen-Romberg</placeName>, which
                        opened on January 23, 1854 and closed on August 15, 1861.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Expansion of Relations, <date when="1868">1868</date>.</head>
                    <p>The relations between the United States and the Grand Duchy of Hesse
                        continued to expand through the 1860s. On August 1, 1868, specially
                        accredited U.S. Minister Plenipotentiary <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/bancroft-george">George Bancroft</ref>
                        signed a naturalization treaty with Hesse. At the time, Bancroft was also
                        accredited to Prussia and the North German Confederation and, after 1871, to
                        the German Empire. Yet, although Bancroft was recalled from his position in
                        Berlin in 1874 (at his own request), he was never officially recalled from
                        the court of Hesse. (See entry on <ref
                            target="/countries/issues/german-unification">German Unification</ref>.)
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Relations with Imperial Germany, <date when="1917"
                            >1917</date>.</head>
                    <p>On February 3, 1917, U.S. President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>
                        instructed the Secretary of State to notify the German Ambassador to the
                        United States that all diplomatic relations between the U.S. and the German
                        Empire were severed. As the foreign affairs of Imperial Germany were run out
                        of <placeName xml:id="berlin">Berlin</placeName> and decided upon by the
                        Kaiser, this constituted the severance of relations with Hesse, as part of
                        the German Empire. On April 6, 1917, Wilson declared war upon Imperial
                        Germany.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention for the Mutual Abolition of the Droit d’Aubaine and Taxes on
                        Emigration, <date when="1844">1844</date>.</head>
                    <p>On March 26, 1844 the U.S. and the Grand Duchy of Hesse signed the Convention
                        for the Mutual Abolition of the Droit d’Aubaine and Taxes on Emigration.
                        This convention was signed in Berlin by U.S. Minister to Prussia <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/wheaton-henry">Henry Wheaton</ref> and
                        the Grand Duke of Hesse’s Minister to Prussia <persName>Baron Schaeffer
                            Bernstein</persName> and served to remove “the restrictions which exist
                        in their territories upon the acquisition and transfer of property by their
                        respective citizens and subjects.” </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Agreement on Naturalization, <date when="1868">1868</date>.</head>
                    <p>When the northern part of Hesse joined the North German Confederation in
                        1867, it was subject to the laws and stipulations concerning immigration and
                        naturalization that were agreed upon by the United States and the North
                        German Confederation. To facilitate matters, the Grand Duchy of Hesse signed
                        a similar document concerning immigration and naturalization. The agreement
                        was signed in <placeName xml:id="darmstadt">Darmstadt</placeName> on August
                        1, 1868, by U.S. Minister to the North German Confederation George Bancroft
                        and the president of the council of state for the Grand Duchy of Hesse Dr.
                            <persName>Frederick Baron von Lindelof</persName>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Hesse Joins the German Empire, <date when="1871">1871</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Grand Duchy of Hesse was one of the founding states of the German Empire,
                        which was proclaimed on January 18, 1871.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>German Unification.</head>
                    <p>Hesse was one of the states involved in the process of German unification
                        during the mid-nineteenth century. See “<ref
                            target="/countries/issues/german-unification">Unification of German
                            States</ref>” for greater detail.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Charles I. Beavans, <hi rend="italic">Treaties and Other International
                            Agreements of the United States of America, 1776-1949</hi>, (Department
                        of State: Washington, DC, 1971), Volume 8.</bibl>
                    <bibl>William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi> (Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law</hi>
                        (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">Four Phases of American
                            Development</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, 1912).</bibl>
                    <bibl>James J. Sheehan, <hi rend="italic">German History 1770-1866</hi>,
                        (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1989).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
