<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Hungary</title>
                <title type="short">Hungary</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Evan Duncan, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The medieval Kingdom of Hungary was conquered by the Ottoman Turks in 1526 and
                    was liberated by the Austrian Empire in 1699. It had an uneasy relationship with
                    the Hapsburg monarchy. The <hi rend="italic">Ausgleich</hi> (Compromise) of 1867
                    granted Hungary considerable autonomy over its internal affairs and control over
                    its non-Magyar ethnic groups. The Emperor of <ref target="/countries/austria"
                        >Austria</ref> was also King of Hungary. Institutions were Imperial, Royal,
                    or Imperial and Royal (<hi rend="italic">Kaiserlich-und-Koeniglich</hi>). This
                    arrangement lasted until the breakup of the Austro-Hungarian Empire at the end
                    of World War I.</p>
                <p>As the Central Powers faced defeat, the Hungarian parliament declared
                    independence from Austria on October 17, 1918. An independent government was
                    formed November 1. Austria-Hungary concluded an armistice with the Allies on
                    November 3. A separate Military Convention between the Allies and Hungary,
                    signed on November 13, called for the withdrawal and demobilization of Hungarian
                    armed forces. A republic was proclaimed on November 16. Hungary was proclaimed a
                    kingdom on March 23, 1920, although the throne remained vacant.</p>
                <p>On September 10, 1919, the Treaty of St.-Germain recognized Hungary’s
                    independence from Austria. The Treaty of Trianon, signed on June 4, 1920,
                    defined Hungary’s postwar boundaries. It lost three-quarters of its prewar
                    territory and two-thirds of its prewar population to neighboring states.
                    However, the United States never ratified the treaties; thus, it was not until
                    1921 that the United States ended its state of war against the former
                    Austro-Hungarian Empire and recognized Hungary.</p>
                <p>During World War II Hungary fought on the side of Germany, although the country
                    fell under German military occupation after an unsuccessful attempt to switch
                    sides on October 15, 1944. During the Cold War, Hungarian foreign policy was
                    generally aligned with that of the Soviet Union, with the exception of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1953-1960/warsaw-treaty">short-lived period of
                        neutrality</ref> declared by <persName>Imre Nagy</persName> in November
                    1956. Since 1989, relations between the United States and Hungary have
                    strengthened significantly. <figure>
                        <graphic url="hungary.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Hungary</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Hungrian Independence, <date when="1921"
                        >1921</date>.</head>
                    <p>After the United States declared war on Germany, Austria-Hungary severed
                        diplomatic relations with the United States on April 8, 1917. The United
                        States declared war on Austria-Hungary on December 7. The tenth of President
                            <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>’s Fourteen Points called for free
                        opportunities for the “autonomous development” of the peoples of
                        Austria-Hungary.</p>
                    <p>The American Commission to Negotiate Peace and the U.S. Food Administration
                        sent missions to Hungary in 1919. The United States was represented on an
                        Inter-Allied Military Mission that oversaw Hungarian compliance with the
                        Armistice. On December 4, 1919, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/grant-smith-ulysses">Ulysses
                            Grant-Smith</ref> was appointed U.S. Commissioner to Hungary, with the
                        mission of reporting on political developments and promoting commerce.</p>
                    <p>At the time, the United States had not ratified the Treaty of St.-Germain,
                        which recognized Hungary’s independence, or the Treaty of Trianon which
                        defined Hungary’s postwar boundaries. Establishment of relations had to
                        await termination of the state of war, which took place under a Joint
                        Resolution of Congress on July 2, 1921. Hungary’s National Assembly accepted
                        the terms of the Joint Resolution on August 12 and authorized the Hungarian
                        Government to negotiate a treaty with the United States.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Consular Relations,<date when="1869">1869</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. consular post in the Kingdom of Hungary was established in
                        1869, when a Consular Agent was appointed in <placeName key="pesth"
                            >Pesth</placeName>. A Consul was appointed in 1874 (those appointed
                        after 1888 were accredited to <placeName key="budapest"
                        >Budapest</placeName>). The post became a Consulate General in 1904 and was
                        closed in 1917.</p>
                    <p>The only other consular post in the Kingdom of Hungary was at <placeName
                            key="fiume">Fiume</placeName>, the Kingdom’s only seaport. It was a
                        Consular Agency from 1865 to 1908 (<persName>Fiorello LaGuardia</persName>,
                        future Mayor of New York City, served there from 1904-06) and a Consulate
                        from 1908 to 1917. The postwar Consulate in Fiume, Italy is outside the
                        scope of this paper.</p>
                    <p>Hungary opened its first consular posts in the United States in 1922, with a
                        Consulate General in New York City and Consulates in Pittsburg, Chicago, and
                        Cleveland.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1921"
                        >1921</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States and Hungary signed a treaty establishing friendly relations
                        on August 29, 1921. It entered into force on December 17.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of American Legation in Budapest, <date when="1921"
                            >1921</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Legation was established in Budapest on December 26, 1921, with
                        Commissioner <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/grant-smith-ulysses"
                            >Ulysses Grant-Smith</ref> as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">pro
                            tempore</hi>. Grant-Smith presented his new credentials on January 24,
                        1922, and served until April 28.</p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/brentano-theodore">Theodore
                            Brentano</ref> was appointed as the first U.S. Minister to Hungary on
                        February 10, 1922. He presented his credentials May 16, 1922 and served
                        until May 6, 1927.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of American Legation in the United States, <date when="1922"
                            >1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>Count <persName>Laszlo Szechenyi</persName> presented his credentials as
                        Hungary’s first Minister to the United States on January 11, 1922. He served
                        until March 31, 1933.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Relations Interrupted, <date when="1941">1941</date>.</head>
                    <p>After Germany declared war on the United States, Hungary severed diplomatic
                        relations with the United States on December 11, 1941. A declaration of war
                        followed on December 13. U.S. President <persName>Franklin D.
                            Roosevelt</persName> believed that Hungary, along with Bulgaria and
                        Romania, had declared war under duress and against the will of their
                        peoples. Congress did not approve a resolution declaring that a state of war
                        existed with these countries until June 5, 1942. U.S. Minister <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/pell-herbert-claiborne">Herbert
                            Claiborne Pell</ref> left Budapest on January 16, 1942.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Relations Resumed, <date when="1945">1945</date>.</head>
                    <p>On January 20, 1945, a Hungarian Provisional National Government signed an
                        armistice agreement with the Allies in Moscow. An Allied Control Commission
                        was established to oversee compliance. The U.S military representative to
                        the Commission arrived in Hungary on February 18.</p>
                    <p>President Roosevelt also designated <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/schoenfeld-hans-frederick-arthur">H.
                            F. Arthur Schoenfeld</ref> as U.S. Representative in Hungary, with the
                        personal rank of Minister. Schoenfeld arrived in Budapest on May 11 and
                        established a U.S. Mission there.</p>
                    <p>On September 22, 1945, Schoenfeld delivered a note stating that the United
                        States was ready to establish diplomatic relations with Hungary if its
                        Provisional Government was ready to take measures that would make free
                        elections possible. The Provisional Government replied affirmatively on
                        September 25. Scheonfeld was appointed U.S. Minister to Hungary on December
                        15, 1945. He presented his credentials on January 26, 1946, and served until
                        June 1, 1947. After Schoenfeld presented his credentials, the U.S. Mission
                        became a Legation once more.</p>
                    <p>On November 2, 1945, the United States accepted the appointment of
                            <persName>Aladar de Szegedy-Maszak</persName> as Hungary’s Minister to
                        the United States. He presented his credentials January 18, 1946 and served
                        until July 11, 1947.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Revolution of 1956 and U.S.-Hungarian Relations, <date from="1956"
                            to="1957">1956-1957</date>.</head>
                    <p>Hungary revolted against Soviet domination on October 24, 1956. U.S. Minister
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/wailes-edward-thompson">Edward T.
                            Wailes</ref> arrived in Budapest on November 2, but did not present his
                        credentials before the Soviet Union began suppressing the Revolution on
                        November 4. The Department of State instructed Wailes to remain in Budapest
                        but to postpone presenting his credentials while events unfolded. On January
                        22, 1957, the Hungarian Government requested Wailes’ recall, claiming that
                        he had been conducting official activities without having presented his
                        credentials. Wailes left Budapest on February 27. From then until 1967, the
                        United States was represented in Hungary by Chargés d’Affaires.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1966"
                            >1966</date>.</head>
                    <p>On November 28, 1966, the United States raised its Legations in Bulgaria and
                        Hungary to Embassy status. These were the last U.S. diplomatic missions to
                        be upgraded. <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/tims-richard-womser"
                            >Richard W. Tims</ref> was serving as Chargé d’Affaires at the time.
                            <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hillenbrand-martin-joseph-anthony"
                            >Martin J. Hillenbrand</ref> was appointed as the first U.S. Ambassador
                        to Hungary on September 13, 1967. He presented his credentials on October
                        30, and served until February 15, 1969. <persName>Janos Nagy</persName>
                        presented his credentials as Hungary’s first Ambassador to the United States
                        on October 7, 1968. He served until June 9, 1971.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="treaties_agreements">
                    <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Treaty of Friendship, Commerce, and Consular Rights, <date when="1924"
                                >1924</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United States and Hungary signed a Treaty of Friendship, Commerce,
                            and Consular Rights in Washington, D.C. on June 24, 1924. It entered
                            into force on October 4.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_events">
                        <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                        <div type="timeline">
                            <head>The United States and Hungarian Independence, <date when="1849"
                                />1849</head>
                            <p>On April 13, 1849, the Hungarian Diet (legislature) proclaimed a
                                republic. The next day it elected <persName>Louis Kossuth</persName>
                                as its president. On June 18, Secretary of State <ref
                                    target="/departmenthistory/people/clayton-john-middleton">John
                                    M. Clayton</ref> appointed A. Dudley Mann as a special and
                                confidential agent to the Government of Hungary. Mann was authorized
                                to recognize the new government if Hungary appeared <quote>“able to
                                    maintain the independence she had declared.”</quote> He had
                                gotten no further than Vienna when Austrian and Russian armies
                                defeated the Hungarians.</p>
                            <p>The United States helped secure the release of Kossuth and those of
                                his followers who had fled to the Ottoman Empire and had been
                                imprisoned there. A Navy ship transported Kossuth to the United
                                States, where he received an enthusiastic welcome. Kossuth’s visit
                                lasted from December 5, 1851 to July 14, 1852, during which streets,
                                squares, and even towns and counties were named for him. Although
                                Secretary of State <ref
                                    target="/departmenthistory/people/webster-daniel">Daniel
                                    Webster</ref> waxed eloquent on the subject, Hungarian
                                independence received no official support.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="timeline">
                            <head>The United States and Hungarian Coronation Regalia, <date
                                    when="1978"/>1978</head>
                            <p>After the end of World War II, Hungarian soldiers guarding the
                                country’s coronation regalia transferred the Crown of St. Stephen to
                                U.S. military forces in Austria. The Crown was transferred to the
                                United States in 1953 and held at Fort Knox until 1978. Secretary of
                                State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/vance-cyrus-roberts"
                                    >Cyrus Vance</ref> returned it to Hungary on February 6,
                                1978.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="timeline">
                            <head>Hugarian Refugees and the United States, <date when="1949"
                                />1949</head>
                            <p>After the Revolution of 1956, the United States offered asylum to
                                over 32,000 Hungarian refugees. Cardinal <persName>Jozsef
                                    Mindszenty</persName>, who had been imprisoned by the Communist
                                government in 1949 and freed by the Revolution, found refuge in the
                                U.S. Legation from 1956 to 1971.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="appendix">
                            <head>Resources</head>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The United States and Hungary: Paths of
                                        Diplomacy 1848-2006</hi>. Department of State Publication
                                    11363 (March 2007).</bibl>
                                <bibl> Langer, William L. <hi rend="italic">An Encyclopedia of World
                                        History</hi>. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1968.</bibl>
                                <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                        target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-hungary/"
                                        >Hungary</ref>
                                </bibl>
                                <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                        target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/hungary/"
                                        >Hungary</ref>
                                </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
