<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Iceland</title>
                <title type="short">Iceland</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Emily Horne, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Following the April 9, 1940, German occupation of Denmark, Iceland took control
                    of its own foreign relations. In July and December of that year Icelandic
                    officials asked the United States to place Iceland under U.S. protection in
                    accordance with the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe">Monroe
                        Doctrine</ref> to forestall a feared German invasion of the island. The
                    United States was initially unenthusiastic about this proposal, but ultimately
                    concluded that Icelandic occupation was a matter of national defense and
                    occupied Iceland on July 7, 1941.<figure>
                        <graphic url="iceland.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Iceland</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Icelandic Independence, <date when="1944"
                        >1944</date>.</head>
                    <p>When German forces occupied <placeName>Denmark</placeName> in 1940, Iceland
                        assumed control over its own foreign affairs and gradually moved toward
                        complete independence from Denmark. Following a plebiscite, Iceland formally
                        became an independent republic on <date when="1944-06-17">June 17,
                            1944</date>. That same day, the United States recognized Iceland in
                        public statements of congratulation by President <persName>Franklin D.
                            Roosevelt</persName> and Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hull-cordell">Cordell Hull</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in
                            Iceland, <date when="1941">1941</date>.</head>
                        <p>Diplomatic relations and the American Legation at <placeName
                                key="reykjavik">Reykjavik</placeName> were established on September
                            30, 1941, when Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/macveagh-lincoln">Lincoln
                                MacVeagh</ref> presented credentials and elevated the American
                            Consulate to Legation status. Iceland had taken over full control of its
                            foreign relations on April 10, 1940, although the country had not yet
                            declared itself independent from Denmark, which was then under German
                            occupation.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1955"
                                >1955</date>.</head>
                        <p>The American Legation was elevated to Embassy status on November 3, 1955,
                            when <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/muccio-john-joseph">John J.
                                Muccio</ref> presented his credentials as Ambassador Extraordinary
                            and Plenipotentiary.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-iceland/">Iceland</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/iceland/">Iceland</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
