<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: India</title>
                <title type="short">India</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>In an unconventional sequence of events, the United States and India established
                    diplomatic relations prior to India’s formal independence from the British
                    Empire. The multistage independence process agreed to by the Indians and the
                    British allowed for the creation of an interim government with the authority to
                    conduct relations with other states before India attained full, sovereign
                    independence.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="india.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of India</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Indian Independence, <date when="1947"
                        >1947</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Union of India as an independent state on
                        August 15, 1947, when President <persName>Harry S. Truman</persName> sent a
                        congratulatory message to <persName>Lord Louis Mountbatten</persName>,
                        Governor General of the Dominion of India. It was on this date that, in
                        accordance with the British Parliament’s India Independence Act of July 18,
                        1947, the Union of India and Pakistan were created from the former “British
                        India” that had been a part of the British Empire.</p>
                    <p>The formal process that led to Indian independence began with a report that
                        the British government issued on May 16, 1946, which recommended the
                        formation of an interim government in India to devise a constitution as part
                        of a process by which India would achieve independence from Great Britain.
                        An Interim Government of India was formed on September 2, 1946, and this is
                        the government with which the United States established diplomatic relations
                        prior to formal Indian independence (see Diplomatic Relations below).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in India,
                            <date when="1946">1946</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations and the American Embassy at <placeName key="new-delhi"
                            >New Delhi</placeName> were established on November 1, 1946, when the
                        U.S. Department of State raised the American Mission at <placeName>New
                            Delhi</placeName> to an Embassy. The U.S. Department of State announced
                        on October 22, 1946, that the Governments of India and the United States had
                            <quote>“agreed to an exchange of ambassadors and to the raising of their
                            respective missions…to the rank of embassies.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <!--<bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-india/">India</ref></bibl>-->
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/india/">India</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back> </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
