<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Iraq</title>
                <title type="short">Iraq</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>American commercial interaction with the Ottoman Empire (which included the area
                    that later became modern Iraq) began in the late 1700s. In 1831, Chargé
                    d’Affaires <persName>David Porter</persName> became the first American diplomat
                    in the Ottoman Empire, at the capital city of Constantinople. With the
                    dissolution of the Ottoman Empire after World War I, the United States supported
                    Great Britain’s administration of Iraq as a mandate, but insisted that it be
                    groomed for independence, rather than remain a colony.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="iraq-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Iraq</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Iraqi Independence, <date when="1930"
                        >1930</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Iraq on January 9, 1930, when <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/dawes-charles-gates">Charles G.
                            Dawes</ref>, U.S. Ambassador to the United Kingdom, signed the
                        Anglo-American-Iraqi Convention in London. According to the preamble of the
                        convention, <quote>“the United States of America recognizes Iraq as an
                            independent State.”</quote> In this treaty, the United States also
                        acknowledged that “special relations” existed between the United Kingdom and
                        Iraq because the latter was a mandate under British protection according to
                        the Treaty of Versailles. In 1932 Iraq terminated its mandate status.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Consular Relations, <date when="1888">1888</date>.</head>
                    <p>
                        <persName>John Henry Haynes</persName> was appointed on August 10, 1888 as
                        the first American Consul for <placeName key="baghdad">Baghdad</placeName>,
                        which was in the part of the Ottoman Empire that later became modern Iraq.
                        He initially fulfilled his duties as Consul for Baghdad while residing in
                            <placeName>Constantinople, Turkey</placeName>, until he presented his
                        credentials to the Ottoman authorities in <placeName>Baghdad</placeName> on
                        January 8, 1889.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in Iraq,
                            <date when="1931">1931</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations and the American Legation in Iraq were established on
                        March 30, 1931, when <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/sloan-alexander-kilgore">Alexander K.
                            Sloan</ref> (then serving as Consul in Iraq) was appointed Chargé
                        d’Affaires of the American Legation at Baghdad.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Legation Raised to Embassy, <date when="1946">1946</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States upgraded its diplomatic representation in Iraq from a
                        Legation to an Embassy on December 28, 1946.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the Arab Union, <date when="1958">1958</date>.</head>
                    <p>On May 28, 1858, the United States recognized the Arab Union that formed
                        between Iraq and the Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan on May 19, 1958. U.S.
                        recognition of the new state was accorded in an exchange of notes between
                        the American Embassy at Baghdad and the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the
                        Arab Union. In announcing U.S. recognition, the Department of State noted
                        that the Arab Union’s constitution stipulated that <quote>“external affairs
                            will remain as they are at the present time”</quote> with the two
                        Kingdoms that had joined to form the new state. Consequently, formal
                        diplomatic relations were not established between the United States and the
                        Arab Union, and diplomatic relations continued uninterrupted between the
                        United States and Iraq, and the United States and Jordan.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Dissolution of the Arab Union, <date when="1958">1958</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following a <hi rend="italic">coup d’etat</hi> in Baghdad on July 14, 1958,
                        the Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan announced the dissolution of the Arab Union
                        and decreed that Jordan would function as a separate state,
                            <quote>“effective from the 1st of August 1958.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed by Iraq, <date when="1967"
                        >1967</date>.</head>
                    <p>Iraq severed diplomatic relations with the United States on June 7, 1967, in
                        the wake of the <ref target="/milestones/1961-1968/arab-israeli-war-1967"
                            >June 1967 Arab-Israeli War</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of U.S. Interest Section in Baghdad, <date when="1972"
                            >1972</date>.</head>
                    <p>A U.S. Interests Section was established in the Belgian Embassy in Baghdad on
                        October 1, 1972.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Resumption of Diplomatic Relations and Reestablishment of the American
                        Embassy in Iraq, <date when="1984">1984</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States resumed diplomatic relations with Iraq and elevated the
                        U.S. Interests Section in Baghdad to Embassy status on November 26, 1984,
                        when President <persName>Ronald Reagan</persName> and Deputy Prime Minister
                        and Foreign Minister <persName>Tariq Aziz</persName> concluded an agreement
                        to that effect.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Closing of the U.S. Embassy in Baghdad and the Severing of Diplomatic
                        Relations, <date when="1991">1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Embassy in Baghdad was closed January 12, 1991, following Iraq’s invasion
                        of <placeName>Kuwait</placeName>, the application of international sanctions
                        against Iraq, and the buildup of military forces in the region. The United
                        States and its allies began military operations against Iraq on January 16,
                        1991. Iraq severed diplomatic relations with the United States February 9,
                        1991, after which each nation maintained a modest Interests Section in the
                        other’s capital.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Invasion of Iraq and Establishment of Coalition Provisional Authority
                        (CPA), <date when="2003">2003</date>.</head>
                    <p>A coalition of countries led by U.S. and British forces invaded Iraq on March
                        20, 2003, and seized Baghdad on April 9. On May 12, 2003, the United States
                        established the Coalition Provisional Authority as the interim civil
                        authority in Iraq, under the leadership of <persName>L. Paul Bremer
                            III</persName>, a former U.S. diplomat. Bremer explained that his chief
                        goals were to manage the post-war reconstruction program and to define a
                        clear path for the resumption of Iraqi sovereignty, tasks that soon were
                        complicated by the outbreak of an insurgency and violent civil unrest.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Transfer of Sovereignty, <date when="2004">2004</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Coalition Provisional Authority transferred sovereignty to the new
                        Interim Iraqi Government led by Prime Minister <persName>Ayad Allawi
                        </persName>on June 28, 2004. After announcing the transfer of power to
                        Allawi’s Government, Coalition Administrator <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/bremer-l-paul">L. Paul Bremer</ref>
                        stated that the Coalition Provisional Authority ceased to exist; he left
                        Iraq later that day.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Embassy in Baghdad Reopens; Diplomatic Relations Reestablished, <date
                            when="2004">2004</date>.</head>
                    <p>Upon the transfer of sovereignty to the Iraqi Interim Government, diplomatic
                        relations were reestablished on June 28, 2004, when the United States
                        reopened its Embassy within Baghdad’s “Green Zone.” Ambassador <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/negroponte-john-dimitri">John
                            Negroponte</ref> presented his credentials to the Iraqi Interim
                        Government on June 29.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/6804.htm">Iraq</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/p/nea/ci/iz/">Iraq</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
