<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Ireland</title>
                <title type="short">Ireland</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, February 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Ireland gained independence from the <ref target="/countries/united-kingdom"
                        >United Kingdom</ref> on <date when="1921-12-06">December 6, 1921</date>,
                    when representatives of the two states signed the Anglo-Irish Treaty. This
                    agreement provided independence for 26 counties, constituted as the Irish Free
                    State, while six counties of northeast Ulster chose to remain a part of the
                    United Kingdom with limited self-government. Strong U.S.-Irish connections date
                    to the mid-19th century when a large number of Irish immigrants came to the
                    United States.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="ireland-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Ireland</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Ireland, <date when="1924-06-28">1924</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Irish Free State as a state with autonomous
                        control over its foreign relations on <date when="1924-06-28">June 28,
                            1924</date>, when U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hughes-charles-evans">Charles E.
                            Hughes</ref> informed the British Ambassador in Washington that the
                        President would be pleased to receive a duly accredited Minister
                        Plenipotentiary of the Irish Free State. Hughes was responding to a letter
                        the British Ambassador had sent on <date when="1924-06-24">June 24,
                            1924</date>, in which the ambassador requested U.S. approval of the
                        British government’s plan to have an Irish minister handle “matter as
                        Washington exclusively relating to the Irish Free State.”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1924-10-07"
                        >1924</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on <date when="1924-10-07">October 7,
                            1924</date>, when <persName>Timothy A. Smiddy</persName> presented his
                        credentials as Minister Plenipotentiary of the Irish Free State in
                        Washington.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Legation in Dublin, <date when="1927-07-27"
                            >1927</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation in Dublin was established on <date when="1927-07-27"
                            >July 27, 1927</date>, when <persName>Frederick A. Sterling</persName>
                        presented his credentials as American Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                        Plenipotentiary.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-ireland/">Ireland</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/ireland/">Ireland</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
