<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Italy</title>
                <title type="short">Italy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Louise Woodroofe, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p> The formation of the modern Italian state began in 1861 with the unification of
                    most of the peninsula under the House of Savoy (Piedmont-Sardinia) into the
                    Kingdom of Italy. Italy incorporated Venetia and the former Papal States
                    (including Rome) by 1871 following the Franco-Prussian War (1870-71). Prior to
                    Italian unification (also known as the Risorgimento), the United States had
                    diplomatic relations with the main entities of the Italian peninsula: the
                    Kingdom of Sardinia, the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies, and the Papal States. </p>
                <p> With the exception of the World War II years when Benito Mussolini’s government
                    declared war upon the United States (1941-43), the United States has had warm
                    relations with the Kingdom of Italy and, after 1946, its successor, the Republic
                    of Italy. Currently, the United States and Italy share strong bilateral
                    relations. Italy is a member of NATO and is a founding member of the European
                    Union. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="italy-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Italy</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Italian Independence, <date when="1861">1861</date>. </head>
                    <p> The United States officially recognized the Kingdom of Italy when it
                        accepted the credentials of <persName>Chevalier Joseph Bertinatti
                        </persName>as Minister Plenipotentiary of the Kingdom of Italy on April 11,
                        1861.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Consulate Generals.</head>
                    <p>Prior to the Risorgimento of 1861, the Italian peninsula was fragmented into
                        different kingdoms, city-states, duchies, etc. The U.S. established a
                        presence at virtually every seaport because trade, shipping, and seamen
                        protection were all major functions in protecting and enhancing American
                        interests. This explains why there were numerous U.S. Consulates General,
                        from the late eighteenth century through the mid-nineteenth century,
                        scattered throughout the region. Below is a list of U.S. Consulate Generals
                        that were located within what today would be the borders of Italy. </p>
                    <list>
                        <item> Leghorn (1794-1941)</item>
                        <item> Genoa (1797-1993)</item>
                        <item> Trieste (1797-1966)</item>
                        <item> Rome (1797-1965)</item>
                        <item> Venice (1797-1963)</item>
                        <item> Messina (1805-1934)</item>
                        <item> Palermo (1805-1994)</item>
                        <item> Florence (1823-current)</item>
                        <item> Ancona (1840-1907)</item>
                        <item> Ravenna (1844-1867)</item>
                        <item> Carrara (1852-1916)</item>
                        <item> Spezzia (1856-1876)</item>
                        <item> Otranto (1861-1867)</item>
                        <item> Taranto (1861-1872)</item>
                        <item> Civita Vecchia (1861-1907)</item>
                        <item> Porto D-Anzio (1862-?)</item>
                        <item> Capriano (1863-?)</item>
                        <item> Gallipoli (1864-1866)</item>
                        <item> Turin (1864-1967)</item>
                        <item> Ostia (1864-?)</item>
                        <item> Milan (1865-current)</item>
                        <item> Naples (1796-current)</item>
                        <item> Gioja (1868-?)</item>
                        <item> Castellamare (1869-1908)</item>
                        <item> Trapani (1869-1907)</item>
                        <item> Salerno (1871-?)</item>
                        <item> Pozzouli (1873-1884)</item>
                        <item> Girgenti (1875-1907)</item>
                        <item> Bari (1878-1953)</item>
                        <item> Rodi Garganico (1878-1907)</item>
                        <item> Verona (1880-?)</item>
                        <item> Milazzo (1880-1895)</item>
                        <item> Bologna (1881-1910)</item>
                        <item> Carini (1882-1907)</item>
                        <item> Catania (1883-1927)</item>
                        <item> San Remo (1883-1909)</item>
                        <item> Sorrento (1893-1908)</item>
                        <item> Reggio, Calabria (1895-1907)</item>
                        <item> Capri (1901-1914)</item>
                        <item> Aegean Sea Islands (1931-1938)</item>
                        <item> Brindisi (1864-1880)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The United States currently has Consulate Generals in Florence, Milan and
                        Naples.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1861">1861</date>.</head>
                    <p> The United States established diplomatic relations with the Kingdom of Italy
                        in 1861 when it accepted the credentials of Chevalier Joseph Bertinatti as
                        Minister Plenipotentiary of the Kingdom of Italy on April 11, 1861.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of American Legations in the Italian Peninsula, <date from="1831" to="1848">1831-48</date>.</head>
                    <p> Prior to the 1861 unification of Italy, the Italian peninsula was fragmented
                        into several kingdoms, duchies, and city-states. As such, since the early
                        nineteenth century, the United States maintained several legations which
                        served the larger Italian states. In 1831 the United States established a
                        legation to the Two Sicilies at Naples in 1831, while in 1840 the United
                        States established a legation to the Kingdom of Sardinia at Turin. Finally,
                        in 1848, the United States established a legation to the Papal States (later
                        the Pontifical States) in Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Legation of the Kingdom of Sardinia becomes the Legation of the Kingdom of
                        Italy, <date when="1861">1861</date>. </head>
                    <p> On April 11, 1861, following Italy’s unification, former Minister
                        Plenipotentiary of the Kingdom on Sardinia, Chevalier Joseph Bertinatti,
                        presented his credentials to the United States as Minister Plenipotentiary
                        of the Kingdom of Italy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Legation to the Kingdom of Italy moves to Florence and then Rome,
                        <date from="1865" to="1871">1865-71</date>.</head>
                    <p> During the period of Italian unification, George P. Marsh, as Minister
                        Plenipotentiary, oversaw the move of the U.S. Legation from Turin to
                        Florence in 1865 and from Florence to Rome in 1871.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1893">1893</date>. </head>
                    <p> The legation was elevated to an embassy when James J. Van Allen was
                        appointed ambassador on October 23, 1893, though he declined the
                        appointment. <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/macveagh-isaac-wayne">Wayne MacVeagh</ref> became the first official U.S. Ambassador to Italy
                        when he presented his credentials in Rome on March 11, 1894.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of the Italian Legation to the Italian Embassy, <date when="1893">1893</date>. </head>
                    <p> The Italian Legation to the United States became the Italian Embassy to the
                        United States when Rome elevated Minister Baron Saverio de Fava to the rank
                        of Ambassador on June 14, 1893.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed, <date when="1941">1941</date>.</head>
                    <p> Diplomatic relations were severed and the American Embassy in Rome was
                        closed on December 11, 1941, after Italy declared war on the United
                        States.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Re-established, <date when="1944">1944</date>.</head>
                    <p> Diplomatic relations were reestablished on October 16, 1944, when the Acting
                        Secretary of State announced the decision in a statement released to the
                        press.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy in Italy Re-opened, 1945.</head>
                    <p> Ambassador <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/kirk-alexander-comstock">Alexander C. Kirk </ref>re-opened the U.S. Embassy in Rome when he
                        presented his credentials on January 8, 1945.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/4033.htm">Italy</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/it/ ">Italy</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>