<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Kingdom of
                    Serbia/Yugoslavia</title>
                <title type="short">Kingdom of Serbia/Yugoslavia*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, February 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Note: Please click <ref target="/countries/serbia">here</ref>
                        for information on the Republic of Serbia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p> U.S. and Serbian officials first made overtures to establish diplomatic
                    relations in 1867, but it was not until 1881, three years after the country
                    gained its independence from the Ottoman Empire, that the United States
                    officially recognized the <placeName xml:id="qz">Kingdom of Serbia</placeName>. </p>
                <p> With the disintegration of the Habsburg Empire at the end of the Great War in
                    1918, many of the empire’s southern Slav minorities sought the protection of the
                    Serbian throne, and entered into union with Serbia as the Kingdom of Serbs,
                    Croats, and Slovenes in December 1918. The United States recognized the kingdom
                    in February 1919. As Serbia was the dominant partner in this state, the U.S.
                    Government has considered the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes and then
                    later, Yugoslavia, as the successor government to the original Government of
                    Serbia. In 1929 the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes adopted the name
                    Yugoslavia. In 1946, Yugoslavia became a socialist federation of six republics:
                    Croatia, Montenegro, Serbia, Slovenia, Bosnia and Herzegovina, and Macedonia. At
                    this time, it adopted the name Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (SFRY). </p>
                <p> The U.S. shared diplomatic relations with the Socialist Federal Republic of
                    Yugoslavia through 1992 when Slovenia, Croatia, Bosnia and Herzegovina, and
                    Macedonia all seceded. At the time, the Republics of Serbia and Montenegro
                    claimed to be the successor state to the SFRY. The United States Government,
                    however, adopted and subsequently maintained the position that the SFRY had
                    dissolved without any successor state, thus terminating relations between the
                    United States and the SFRY. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Serbian Independence, <date when="1881">1881</date>.</head>
                    <p> The United States recognized the Kingdom of Serbia as a sovereign nation on
                        October 14, 1881, with the signing of consular and commercial agreements
                        between the two nations. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of the Independence of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and
                        Slovenes, <date when="1919">1919</date>.</head>
                    <p> On February 7, 1919, the United States recognized the Kingdom of the Serbs,
                        Croats and Slovenes through a statement released to the press by the U.S.
                        Acting Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/polk-frank-lyon">Frank Polk</ref>. The
                        United States considered this new state as the successor state to the
                        Kingdom of Serbia. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in Serbia,
                            <date when="1882">1882</date>.</head>
                    <p> Diplomatic relations between the U.S. and Serbia were established on
                        November 10, 1882, when U.S. Consul General Eugene Schuyler presented his
                        credentials to the government of Serbia. At this time, the American Legation
                        in Belgrade was established, though Schuyler was resident at Athens. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Yugoslav Legation, <date when="1919">1919</date>.</head>
                    <p> On February 10, 1919, Acting Secretary of State Frank Polk wrote to the
                        Yugoslav Minister to the United States Slavko Grouvitch that the United
                        States Government recognized that the Serbian Legation will thereafter be
                        known as the Legation for the Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Legation Moved to London, <date when="1941">1941</date>.</head>
                    <p> The Government of Yugoslavia went into exile in England on April 14, 1941,
                        in anticipation of German occupation. U.S. Minister to Yugoslavia <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/lane-arthur-bliss">Arthur Bliss
                            Lane</ref> left Yugoslavia on May 17, 1941. <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/biddle-anthony-joseph-drexel-jr">Anthony J. Drexel Biddle Jr.</ref> presented his credentials as the
                        U.S. Minister Near the Government of Yugoslavia in England on October 3,
                        1941, and was resident in London. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1942">1942</date>.</head>
                    <p> The American Legation Belgrade was raised to the status of Embassy with the
                        appointment of Anthony J. Drexel Biddle Jr. as Ambassador Extraordinary and
                        Plenipotentiary on September 29, 1942. He presented his new credentials on
                        November 3, 1942. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy Moves to Egypt, <date when="1943">1943</date>.</head>
                    <p> On September 28, 1943, the Government of Yugoslavia was transferred to
                        Egypt. <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/macveagh-lincoln">Lincoln
                            MacVeagh</ref>, the U.S. Ambassador Near the Government of Yugoslavia
                        Established in Egypt, presented his credentials on December 9, 1943. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy Returns to London, <date when="1944">1944</date>.</head>
                    <p> The Government of Yugoslavia was transferred yet again to England in 1944.
                        On July 1, 1944, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/schoenfeld-rudolf-emil">Rudolf E.
                            Schoenfeld</ref> was designated U.S. Chargé d'Affaires ad interim near
                        the Government of Yugoslavia Established in England. On November 17, 1944,
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/patterson-richard-cunningham">Richard Cunningham Patterson</ref> presented his credentials as U.S.
                        Ambassador near the Government of Yugoslavia Established in England.
                        Patterson was resident in London.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy Returns to Belgrade, <date when="1945">1945</date>.</head>
                    <p> Near the end of the war, the Yugoslav Government returned to <placeName xml:id="belgrade">Belgrade</placeName>. On March 31, 1945, Embassy
                        Belgrade returned to Yugoslavia and resumed operations in Belgrade. Richard
                        Cunningham Patterson continued to serve as U.S. Ambassador to Yugoslavia and
                        was resident in Belgrade. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Relations, <date when="1992">1992</date>.</head>
                    <p> On May 21, 1992, the U.S. announced that it would not recognize the Federal
                        Republic of Yugoslavia (FRY) as a successor state of the Socialist Federal
                        Republic of Yugoslavia (SFRY). The FRY was composed of the Republics of
                        Serbia and Montenegro. U.S. Ambassador Warren Zimmerman was recalled from
                        Belgrade, but the mission continued with a staff under the authority of a
                        Chargé d'Affaires ad interim. The United States Government took the position
                        that the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia, the governing regime
                        since 1946, ceased to exist and that no state represented the sole
                        continuation of the SFRY. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Claims Convention, 1832. </head>
                    <p> This convention, also known as the Convention to Terminate the Reclamations
                        of the Government of the Untied States for the Depredations Inflicted upon
                        American Commerce by Murat During the Years 1809, 1810, 1811, and 1812,
                        1832, was signed on October 14, 1832 in Naples by U.S. Chargé d’Affaires
                        near the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies John Nelson Esq. and the Minister
                        Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs for the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies
                        Prince D. Antonio Maria Statella. The objective of this treaty was to allow
                        U.S. merchants to be <quote>“indemnified for losses inflicted upon them by
                            Murat, by the depredations, seizures, confiscations and destruction of
                            their Vessels [sic] and cargoes, during the years 1809, 1810, 1811, and
                            1812.”</quote> This treaty was deemed obsolete when the Two Sicilies was
                        consolidated into the Kingdom of Italy in 1861. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty on Commercial Relations, <date when="1881">1881</date>.</head>
                    <p> On October 14, 1881, U.S. Chargé d’Affaires and Consul-General at <placeName xml:id="bucharest">Bucharest</placeName>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/schuyler-eugene">Eugene
                            Schuyler</ref> and Serbian Minister of Foreign Affairs Ched. Mijatovitch
                        concluded a Treaty on Commercial Relations to facilitate and develop
                        commercial relations between the two countries.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention on Rights, Privileges, and Immunities of Consular Officers,
                            <date when="1881">1881</date>. </head>
                    <p> On October 14, 1881, U.S. Chargé d’Affaires and Consul-General at Bucharest
                        Eugene Schuyler and Serbian Minister of Foreign Affairs Ched. Mijatovitch
                        signed a Convention on Rights, Privileges, and Immunities of Consular
                        Officers. This agreement defined and regulated the rights, immunities, and
                        privileges of each state’s consular officers. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty on Extradition, <date when="1901">1901</date>.</head>
                    <p> On October 25, 1901, the United States and the Kingdom of Serbia signed a
                        Treaty on Extradition in Belgrade. The treaty promoted justice and confirmed
                        friendly relations between the two nations, and was negotiated by U.S.
                        Minister Charles S. Francis and Serbian Minister of Foreign Affairs, Michel
                        V. Vouïtch.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes, <date when="1918">1918</date>.</head>
                    <p> With the disintegration of the Habsburg Empire at the end of the Great War
                        in 1918, many of the empire’s southern Slav minorities sought the protection
                        of the Serbian throne, and entered into union with Serbia as the Kingdom of
                        Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes in December 1918. The United States recognized
                        the kingdom in February 1919. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia, <date when="1929">1929</date>. </head>
                    <p>In 1929 the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes adopted the name Kingdom
                        of Yugoslavia.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (SFRY),
                            <date when="1946">1946</date>.</head>
                    <p> In 1946, Yugoslavia became a socialist federation of six republics: Croatia,
                        Montenegro, Serbia, Slovenia, Bosnia and Herzegovina, and Macedonia. At this
                        time, it adopted the name Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia
                        (SFRY).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The Cold War.</head>
                    <p> Although the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (SFRY) was run by a
                        communist government, under its long-time president Josip Tito, Yugoslavia
                        balanced relations between East and West. For more information on
                        U.S.-Yugoslav foreign policy relations during the Cold War, please view the
                        chapter on “Foreign Relations” in the Library of Congress’s Country Study:
                            <ref target="http://memory.loc.gov/frd/cs/yutoc.html">Yugoslavia</ref>
                        (Former). </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>“The Commission to Negotiate Peace to the Acting Secretary of State,
                        February 6, 1919, 4 p.m.,” <ref rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the
                            United States 1919, Volume II</ref> (Washington, D.C.: Government
                        Printing Office). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Office of the Historian Website, “<ref rend="/departmenthistory/people/chiefsofmission/xi">Principal Officers
                            of the Department of State and U.S. Chiefs of Mission, 1778–2005,
                            Yugoslavia</ref>” </bibl>
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Study: <ref target="http://memory.loc.gov/frd/cs/yutoc.html">Yugoslavia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>U.S. Department of State Country Fact Sheets: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5388.htm">Serbia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref target="http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/collections/diplomacy/">Frontline
                            Diplomacy</ref>: The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the
                        Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training 1940-1990 </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>