<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Kosovo</title>
                <title type="short">Kosovo</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Derived from U.S. Department of State, Background Note, November 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="history">
                <head>Historical Overview</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Early History:</hi> The Ottomans ruled Kosovo for more than
                    four centuries, until Serbia acquired the territory during the First Balkan War
                    in 1912-13.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="kosovo-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Kosovo</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The 20th Century:</hi> First partitioned in 1913 between
                    Serbia and Montenegro, Kosovo was then incorporated into the Kingdom of the
                    Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes (later named Yugoslavia) after World War I. During
                    World War II, parts of Kosovo were absorbed into Italian-occupied Albania. After
                    the Italian capitulation, Nazi Germany assumed control over Kosovo until Tito’s
                    Yugoslav Partisans entered at the end of the war.</p>
                <p>After World War II, Kosovo became an autonomous province of Serbia in the
                    Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (S.F.R.Y.). The 1974 Yugoslav
                    Constitution gave Kosovo (along with Vojvodina) the status of a Socialist
                    Autonomous Province within Serbia. As such, it possessed nearly equal rights as
                    the six constituent Socialist Republics of the S.F.R.Y.</p>
                <p>In 1981, riots broke out and were violently suppressed after Kosovo Albanians
                    demonstrated to demand that Kosovo be granted full Republic status. In the late
                    1980s, Slobodan Milosevic propelled himself to power in Belgrade by exploiting
                    the fears of the Serbian minority in Kosovo. In 1989, he eliminated Kosovo’s
                    autonomy and imposed direct rule from Belgrade. Belgrade ordered the firing of
                    most ethnic Albanian state employees, whose jobs were then assumed by Serbs.</p>
                <p>In response, Kosovo Albanian leaders began a peaceful resistance movement in the
                    early 1990s, led by Ibrahim Rugova. They established a parallel government
                    funded mainly by the Albanian diaspora. When this movement failed to yield
                    results, an armed resistance emerged in 1997 in the form of the Kosovo
                    Liberation Army (KLA). The KLA’s main goal was to secure the independence of
                    Kosovo.</p>
                <p>In late 1998, Milosevic unleashed a brutal police and military campaign against
                    the KLA, which included widespread atrocities against civilians. Milosevic’s
                    failure to agree to the Rambouillet Accords triggered a NATO military campaign
                    to halt the violence in Kosovo. This campaign consisted primarily of aerial
                    bombing of the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (F.R.Y.), including Belgrade, and
                    continued from March through June 1999. After 78 days of bombing, Milosevic
                    capitulated. Shortly thereafter, the UN Security Council adopted Resolution 1244
                    (1999), which suspended Belgrade’s governance over Kosovo, and under which
                    Kosovo was placed under the administration of the United Nations Interim
                    Administration Mission in Kosovo (UNMIK), and which authorized a NATO
                    peacekeeping force. Resolution 1244 also envisioned a political process designed
                    to determine Kosovo’s future status.</p>
                <p>As ethnic Albanians returned to their homes, elements of the KLA conducted
                    reprisal killings and abductions of ethnic Serbs and Roma in Kosovo. Thousands
                    of ethnic Serbs, Roma, and other minorities fled from their homes during the
                    latter half of 1999, and many remain displaced.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The 21st Century:</hi> In November 2005, the Contact Group
                    (France, Germany, Italy, Russia, the United Kingdom, and the United States)
                    produced a set of “Guiding Principles” for the resolution of Kosovo’s future
                    status. Some key principles included: no return to the situation prior to 1999,
                    no changes in Kosovo’s borders, and no partition or union of Kosovo with a
                    neighboring state. The Contact Group later said that Kosovo’s future status had
                    to be acceptable to the people of Kosovo.</p>
                <p>Kosovo declared its independence from Serbia on February 17, 2008. In its
                    declaration of independence, Kosovo committed to fulfilling its obligations
                    under the Ahtisaari Plan, to embrace multi-ethnicity as a fundamental principle
                    of good governance, and to welcome a period of international supervision.</p>
                <p>The United States formally recognized Kosovo as a sovereign and independent state
                    on February 18. To date, Kosovo has been recognized by a robust majority of
                    European states, the United States, Japan, and Canada, and by other states from
                    the Americas, Africa, and Asia. Shortly after independence, a number of states
                    established an International Steering Group (ISG) for Kosovo that appointed
                    Dutch diplomat Pieter Feith as Kosovo’s first International Civilian
                    Representative (ICR).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreignrelations">
                <head>Foreign Relations</head>
                <p>In March 2008, Kosovo passed legislation to establish a foreign ministry. This
                    legislation went into effect on June 15, 2008. The Government of Kosovo
                    appointed Skender Hyseni as its first foreign minister.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition and Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Recognition and Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="2008"
                            >2008</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Kosovo’s independence and agreed to establish
                        diplomatic relations on February 18, 2008, when Secretary of State
                        Condoleezza Rice released a press statement announcing President George W.
                        Bush’s decisions.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
