<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Kuwait</title>
                <title type="short">Kuwait</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Under British protectorship since 1899, <placeName key="kw">Kuwait</placeName>
                    became fully independent in June 1961. Strategic cooperation between the United
                    States and Kuwait increased in 1987 with the implementation of a maritime
                    protection regime that ensured the freedom of navigation through the Gulf for 11
                    Kuwaiti tankers that were reflagged with U.S. markings. The U.S.-Kuwaiti
                    strategic partnership intensified dramatically again after Iraq’s August 2,
                    1990, invasion of Kuwait. <figure>
                        <graphic url="kuwait-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Kuwait</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Kuwaiti Independence, <date when="1961"
                        >1961</date>.</head>
                    <p>On June 19, 1961, Kuwait became fully independent following an exchange of
                        notes with the United Kingdom that terminated the Anglo-Kuwaiti Treaty of
                        1899 and therefore provided for Kuwaiti independence.</p>
                    <p>Despite the fact that Kuwait was technically still a British protectorate
                        prior to June 1961, the Department of State noted in July 1961 that the
                        United States had <quote>“for some time recognized Kuwait as a sovereign
                            state as evidenced by U.S. consular officers in Kuwait receiving
                            exequaturs from the Ruler of Kuwait, and by the conclusion in 1960 of an
                            agreement respecting visas directly with the Government of
                            Kuwait.”</quote> The United States opened its first consulate in Kuwait
                        on June 27, 1951, and concluded a bilateral agreement with Kuwait on
                        non-immigrant passport visas in an exchange of notes on December 11 and 27,
                        1960.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="consular_relations">
                    <head>Consular Presence</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>U.S. Consulate in Kuwait, <date when="1951">1951</date>, with
                            interruptions.</head>
                        <p>The United States opened its first consulate in Kuwait on June 27, 1951.
                            It opened to the public on October 15, with <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/duncan-enoch-sevier">Enoch
                                Duncan</ref> as U.S. Consul to Kuwait.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in
                            Kuwait, <date when="1961">1961</date>.</head>
                        <p>Diplomatic relations were established on September 22, 1961, by agreement
                            between the governments of both states. The American Embassy in Kuwait
                            was established on the same date when the American consul in Kuwait,
                                <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/mak-dayton-s">Dayton
                                Mak</ref>, was designated Chargé d’Affaires.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Evacuation of American Embassy Staff, <date when="1990"
                            >1990</date>.</head>
                        <p>American Ambassador <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/howell-w-nathaniel">W. Nathaniel
                                Howell</ref> and the Embassy staff left Kuwait on December 13, 1990,
                            in the wake of Iraq’s armed occupation of Kuwait that began on August 2,
                            1990.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>American Embassy Reopened, <date when="1991">1991.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>The American Embassy reopened on March 1, 1991, following the expulsion
                            of Iraqi armed forces from Kuwait by the military forces of the United
                            States and a multinational coalition.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="appendix">
                    <head>Resources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-kuwait/"
                                >Kuwait</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/kuwait/">Kuwait</ref>
                        </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
