<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Latvia</title>
                <title type="short">Latvia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, March 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The United States first established diplomatic relations with <placeName
                        key="latvia">Latvia</placeName> on July 28, 1922. The U.S. representative to
                    Latvia also was accredited to Estonia and Lithuania until 1930, when legations
                    were established in those two states. The Soviet invasion and annexation of
                    Latvia and the other Baltic States of Estonia and Lithuania in 1940 forced the
                    closure of the American legation, but Latvian representation in the United
                    States continued uninterrupted. The United States never recognized the forcible
                    incorporation of Latvia into the Soviet Union and views the present Government
                    of Latvia as a legal continuation of the interwar republic. Latvia and the
                    United States have signed treaties on investment, trade, intellectual property
                    protection, extradition, mutual legal assistance, and avoidance of double
                    taxation. Latvia has enjoyed most-favored-nation treatment with the United
                    States since December 1991.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="latvia-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Latvia</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States Recognition of Latvia, <date when="1922">1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Latvia on July 28, 1922, when the U.S.
                        Commissioner at <placeName key="riga">Riga</placeName>, <persName>Evan
                            Young</persName>, informed the Foreign Office of Latvia of the United
                        States’ decision. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hughes-charles-evans">Charles Evans
                            Hughes</ref> had instructed Young in a telegram dated July 25, 1922, to
                        advise the Foreign Offices of Estonia, Latvia, and Lithuania of this
                        decision on the 28th.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1922"
                        >1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on July 28, 1922, when U.S.
                        Commissioner at Riga, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/young-evan-erastus">Evan Young</ref>,
                        informed the Foreign Office of Latvia that the United States’ recognized its
                        independence and that he would continue as the American representative to
                        the three Baltic States, with the new rank of Minister.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Legation established at Riga, <date when="1922">1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Legation at Riga was established on November 13, 1922, when Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/coleman-frederick-william-backus"
                            >Frederick W.B. Coleman</ref> presented his credentials to the Latvian
                        Government. Coleman also was accredited to Estonia and Lithuania.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Legation at Riga Closed, <date when="1940">1940</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Legation at Riga was closed on September 5, 1940, after the USSR
                        occupied and annexed Latvia, as well as Estonia and Lithuania, in August
                        1940. Although the Soviet actions forced the closure of the American
                        Legation and ended the de facto independence of Latvia, the United States
                        never recognized the state’s forcible incorporation into the Soviet Union.
                        The U.S. Government permitted Latvian representatives accredited by the last
                        independent government to remain in the United States with diplomatic
                        status, and the U.S. position remained that diplomatic relations continued
                        uninterrupted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Recognition of Latvian Independence from the USSR, <date when="1991"
                            >1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. recognized the restoration of Latvia’s independence on September 2,
                        1991, in an announcement by President <persName>George H.W.
                        Bush</persName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Resumption of Normal Relations, <date when="1991">1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States and Latvia resumed normal diplomatic relations on September
                        5, 1991, when U.S. Deputy Assistant Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/kamman-curtis-w">Curtis Kamman</ref>
                        and the Latvian First Secretary in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs,
                            <persName>Martins Virsis</persName>, signed a memorandum of
                        understanding concerning diplomatic relations.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy at <placeName key="riga">Riga</placeName> Opened, <date
                            when="1991">1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Embassy at Riga was established on October 2, 1991, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/silins-ints-m">Ints M. Silins</ref> as
                        Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5378.htm">Latvia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/lg/">Latvia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
