<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Lebanon</title>
                <title type="short">Lebanon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Derived from U.S. Department of State, Background Note, November 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="history">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p> When the United States became independent, <placeName key="lb">Lebanon</placeName> was part of the Ottoman Empire and its foreign
                    relations were conducted through the Sultan’s government at Constantinople
                    (Istanbul). In 1922, after the collapse of the Ottoman Empire, the League of
                    Nations approved a French Mandate for Lebanon and Syria, which gave France
                    exclusive control over their foreign relations. The United States appointed
                    George Wadsworth as “Agent and Consul General” on October 9, 1942, to provide a
                    quasi-diplomatic presence in Beirut until the United States determined that
                    Lebanon achieved effective independence in 1944.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="lebanon-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Lebanon</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Lebanese Independence, <date when="1944">1944</date>.</head>
                    <p> The United States recognized Lebanon as an independent state on September 8,
                        1944, when the Lebanese Minister of Foreign Affairs informed the United
                        States that Lebanon fully recognized and would protect existing rights of
                        the United States and its nationals. This Lebanese assurance was in response
                        to a letter sent on September 7, 1944, by the American Diplomatic Agent and
                        Consul General in Lebanon that offered <quote>“full and unconditional
                            recognition”</quote> upon receipt of such written assurances. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in
                        Lebanon, <date when="1944">1944</date>.</head>
                    <p> The United States established diplomatic relations with Lebanon when <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/wadsworth-george">George
                        Wadsworth</ref> presented his credentials as Envoy Extraordinary and
                        Minister Plenipotentiary on November 16, 1944. Wadsworth had been serving as
                        Diplomatic Agent and Consul General to Syria and Lebanon while the United
                        States considered them to be “semi-independent” states. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Legation in <placeName key="beirut">Beirut</placeName> Raised to
                        Embassy, <date when="1952">1952.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p> The American Legation in Beirut was raised to embassy status on October 3,
                        1952, when <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/minor-harold-bronk">Harold
                            B. Minor</ref> was appointed Ambassador Extraordinary and
                        Plenipotentiary. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy Staff Withdrawn, <date when="1989">1989</date>.</head>
                    <p> The United States withdrew all personnel including Ambassador <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/mccarthy-john-thomas">John Thomas
                        McCarthy</ref> from the American Embassy in Beirut on September 6, 1989.
                        In a statement to the press, the Department of State explained that the step
                        was taken after supporters of a faction in the civil war had surrounded the
                        embassy, endangering the safety of embassy personnel and preventing the
                        embassy from functioning effectively. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy Reopened, <date when="1990">1990</date>.</head>
                    <p> The American Embassy in Beirut was reopened on November 29, 1990, when new
                        Ambassador <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/crocker-ryan-clark">Ryan
                            Crocker</ref> presented his credentials. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/35833.htm">Lebanon</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/p/nea/ci/le/index.htm">Lebanon</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>