<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Lew Chew
                    (Loochoo)</title>
                <title type="short">Lew Chew (Loochoo)*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>
                    <placeName xml:id="xr">Lew Chew</placeName> (sometimes referred to as Loochoo,
                    more commonly known as Ryukyu) is a series of islands in the Pacific Ocean off
                    of the Asian coast. Today it is known as Okinawa, and is one of the island
                    chains that constitute modern-day <placeName xml:id="jp">Japan</placeName>. In
                    the mid-nineteenth century, however, Lew Chew was an independent kingdom that
                    specialized in trade between Japan and mainland Asia.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>U.S. Commodore Matthew Perry</persName> signed a treaty with Lew Chew
                    on July 11, 1854. Other European powers followed with similar trade agreements,
                    which led to increased unease from Lew Chew’s northern neighbor, Japan. In late
                    1874, Japan started to more closely incorporate the Lew Chew islands into the
                    Meiji Empire. In 1875 Japan posted a military garrison in Lew Chew. The Japanese
                    Government annexed Lew Chew in 1879, abolished the Lew Chew monarchy, and made
                    it the southern frontier of the Japanese islands. By 1882 China recognized
                    Japan’s hold over the Lew Chew islands as de facto. .</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1854">1854</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first formal act of recognition between the United States and Lew Chew
                        occurred on July 11, 1854, when U.S. Commodore Matthew Perry signed a
                        treaty.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations.</head>
                    <p>The United States and the Kingdom of Lew Chew never established diplomatic
                        relations.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>1854 Compact.</head>
                    <p>This treaty allowed for courtesy and friendship to be shown to all U.S.
                        citizens who visited Lew Chew, as well as for hospitality provided to
                        shipwrecked U.S. vessels off of the Lew Chew coast. The compact also
                        stipulated that U.S. vessels could hire a Lew Chew pilot to guide them
                        safely past the reefs and not (or out of) the harbor for $5.00.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Potential Conflict of Interests with Japan.</head>
                    <p>One of the issues raised by the U.S. treaty with Lew Chew was that, as the
                        Government of Japan aggregated greater control over the islands, they began
                        to insist that all business by foreign governments pertaining to Lew Chew be
                        conducted through the Japanese Department of Foreign Affairs. The position
                        of the United States on these orders was that the independence of the
                        islands <quote>“was a disputed matter in which the United States could not
                            interfere unless its rights under treaty stipulations with any of the
                            powers concerned in the controversy be endangered.”</quote> This
                        question was negated when Japan directly took over the Lew Chew islands in
                        1879, making them a part of Japan.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law</hi>
                        (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Payson J. Treat, <hi rend="italic">Japan and the United States,
                            1853-1921</hi> (Stanford, Calif.: Stanford University Press,
                        1929).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
