<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Liberia</title>
                <title type="short">Liberia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The United States recognized the <placeName key="lr">Republic of
                        Liberia</placeName> on September 23, 1862, when the American Minister to
                    England <persName>Charles F. Adams</persName> was empowered to conclude a treaty
                    of commerce and navigation with the Republic of Liberia.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="liberia-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Liberia</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Liberia, <date when="1862">1862</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Republic of Liberia on September 23, 1862,
                        when the American Minister to England <persName>Charles F. Adams</persName>
                        was empowered to conclude a treaty of commerce and navigation with the
                        Republic of Liberia. The treaty was signed by Adams and the President of
                        Liberia on October 25, 1862.</p>
                    <p>The state that became Liberia originated in 1822 when the American
                        Colonization Society founded a settlement for freedmen and recaptured
                        slaves. In 1847 the settlement constituted itself as a republic and
                        subsequently was recognized by several European states.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and American Legation in Liberia,
                            <date when="1864">1864.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations and the American Legation at <placeName key="monrovia"
                            >Monrovia</placeName> were established on February 23, 1864, when
                        American Commissioner and Consul General <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hanson-abraham">Abraham Hanson</ref>
                        presented his credentials to the Liberian government.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1949">1949.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The American Legation at Monrovia was elevated to Embassy status on May 6,
                        1949, when Ambassador <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/dudley-edward-richard">Edward R.
                            Dudley</ref> presented his credentials to the Liberian government.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-liberia/">Liberia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/liberia/">Liberia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
