<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Libya</title>
                <title type="short">Libya</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and Written by Christopher Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="history">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Prior to its independence in 1951, the territory comprising present-day
                        <placeName key="ly">Libya</placeName> (Tripoli) had been a semi-independent
                    province of the Ottoman Empire from 1711 to 1835, an Italian colony from 1912
                    until 1947, and was under British and French occupation from 1943 to 1951. The
                    United States was recognized by Tripoli in 1796, but permanent diplomatic
                    relations were not established until modern Libya’s independence following World
                    War II. From 1980 until 2006, the U.S. did not have an open Embassy in Libya,
                    although relations were not formally severed.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="libya-flag.png"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Libya</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Tripolitan Recognition of the United States, <date from="1786-02"
                            to="1796-11-04">1786-1796</date>.</head>
                    <p>U.S. Minister to Great Britain <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john">John Adams</ref> entered
                        into treaty negotiations with <persName>Abdurrahman</persName>, the
                        Tripolitan diplomat stationed in London in February of 1786, but the
                        negotiations were inconclusive. Abdurrahman stated that without a treaty,
                        the Tripolitan government would regard the United States and Tripoli to be
                        at war with one another. The Tripolitan government formally recognized U.S.
                        independence by the signing of a peace treaty in Tripoli on November 4,
                        1796. The treaty was subsequently also signed by the Dey of Algiers, who
                        claimed authority over Tripolitan affairs, although this authority was
                        denied by Pasha <persName>Yusuf Qaramanli</persName>. The subsequent treaty
                        between the United States and Tripoli, signed on June 10, 1805, was
                        concluded without Algerian supervision.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Tripoli/Libya under Ottoman and Italian Control, <date when="1835"
                            to="1947">1835-1947</date>.</head>
                    <p>Tripolitan authority to conduct international relations ended when the
                        Ottoman Empire chose to reassert its formerly nominal suzerainty over its
                        Libyan provinces in 1835. The Ottoman Empire formally ceded Libya to Italy
                        under the Treaty of Ouchy on October 18, 1912. Libya formally remained an
                        Italian colony until 1947, when Italy relinquished its claims upon Libya,
                        which had been under joint Franco-British occupation since 1943.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Libyan Independence, <date when="1951"
                        >1951</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the United Kingdom of Libya on December 24,
                        1951, in a congratulatory message sent by President <persName>Harry
                            Truman</persName> to <persName>King Idris I</persName>. Libya declared
                        its independence on this date after the former Italian colony had been
                        administered jointly by France and Great Britain following World War II.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-relations">
                <head>Consular Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Consulate at Tripoli and Italian Libya, <date when="1799-04-05"
                            to="1949-07-01">1799-1949</date> (with interruptions).</head>
                    <p>
                        <persName>James Leander Cathcart</persName> arrived in Tripoli to assume his
                        duties as U.S. Consul on April 5, 1799. <persName>Yusuf
                        Qaramanli</persName>, Pasha of Tripoli, formally accepted Cathcart’s
                        credentials between that date and April 15, when he stated his acceptance of
                        Cathcart in a letter to U.S. President <persName>John Adams</persName>. The
                        Consulate closed on May 14, 1801 owing to the beginning of the Tripolitan
                        War. <persName>Tobias Lear</persName>, who conducted the 1805 peace
                        negotiations, appointed <persName>John Ridgely</persName> “U.S. agent” for
                        Tripoli, but it is unclear if this was a consular position, or if it meant
                        Ridgely was a signatory to the treaty. The Consulate had re-opened by 1807,
                        when <persName>George Davis</persName> was U.S. consul at Tripoli. Although
                        Tripoli ceased to be an independent state after 1835, the consulate remained
                        open until July 22, 1882, when it was closed by order of Congress. The
                        office re-opened on June 10, 1908, closed again on August 15, 1916, reopened
                        April 24, 1935, closed again March 15, 1937, then reestablished June 6,
                        1948. The office was raised to the rank of Consulate General July 1,
                        1949.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Other Consulates in Libya</head>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <item>Al-Baydā’ (Baida, Beida). Earliest extant date July 6, 1964; last
                                extant date June 20, 1996.</item>
                            <item>Benghazi (Banghāzī, Bengazi, Berenice). Earliest extant date July
                                31, 1950; last extant date September 26, 1966.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in Libya,
                            <date when="1951-12-24">1951</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations and the American Legation in Libya were established on
                        December 24, 1951, when the American Consulate General was elevated to a
                        Legation with <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/lynch-andrew-green">
                            <persName>Andrew Lynch</persName>
                        </ref> designated as Charge d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                        interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Legation in Libya was raised to Embassy status, <date when="1954-11-16"
                            >1954</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/gatch-john-newton-jr">
                            <persName>John N. Gatch, Jr.</persName>
                        </ref>, was serving as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>
                        when the Legation in Libya was raised to Embassy status, September 25, 1954.
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/tappin-john-lindsley">
                            <persName>John L. Tappin</persName>
                        </ref> was appointed Ambassador on the same day, and presented his
                        credentials on November 16, 1954.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Relations from <date from="1980-02-08" to="2004-02-08">1980 to
                        2004</date>.</head>
                    <p>U.S. Chargé d’Affaires <persName>William Eagleton, Jr.</persName> was
                        recalled February 8, 1980, and the U.S. Embassy at Tripoli closed May 2,
                        1980, and the Libyan People’s Bureau in Washington closed on May 6, 1981.
                        Relations were not formally severed during this time.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States Interests Section and Liaison Office Established, <date
                            when="2004-02-08">2004</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established an Interests Section at the Belgian Embassy in
                        Tripoli, February 8, 2004. It became the U.S. Liaison Office on June 28,
                        with <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/berry-gregory-l">
                            <persName>Gregory L. Berry</persName>
                        </ref> as the Principal Officer. Libyan diplomats reestablished a presence
                        in Washington on July 8, 2004, when they opened the Libyan Interests Section
                        as part of the United Arab Emirates Embassy, Libya’s protecting power.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of Liaison Office to Embassy Status and Resumption of Full
                        Diplomatic Relations, <date when="2006-05-31">2006</date>.</head>
                    <p>On May 31, 2006, the United States resumed full diplomatic relations with
                        Libya, and the Liaison Office in Tripoli became an Embassy, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/berry-gregory-l">
                            <persName>Gregory L. Berry</persName>
                        </ref> became Charge d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Suspension of U.S. Embassy Tripoli Operations, <date when="2011-02-25"
                            >2011</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>United States relations with Libya deteriorated sharply when Mu’ammar
                        al-Qadhafi tried to suppress an uprising against his regime in 2011. On
                        February 25, 2011, the United States suspended Embassy operations in
                        Tripoli. On March 16, the United States ordered the Libyan Government to
                        suspend its Embassy operations in Washington.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Resumption of U.S. Embassy Tripoli Operations, <date when="2011-09-22"
                            >2011</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States appointed a Special Representative to the Transitional
                        National Council in Benghazi in March 2011 and maintained a diplomatic
                        presence there from April 2011 to September 2012. The U.S. Government
                        officially recognized the Transitional National Council (TNC) as the
                        legitimate government of Libya on July 15, 2011. On September 22, 2011, the
                        U.S. Embassy in Tripoli resumed operations.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Assassination of the American Ambassador, <date when="2012-09-11"
                            >2012</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Ambassador to Libya, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/stevens-john-christopher">
                            <persName>J. Christopher Stevens</persName>
                        </ref> and three other American colleagues were killed on September 11,
                        2012, during an attack on the U.S. Mission in Benghazi. Following the death
                        of Ambassador Stevens, the American Embassy in Tripoli was headed by Chargé
                            <persName>Greg Hicks</persName>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/p/nea/ci/ly/index.htm">Libya</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/p/nea/ci/ba/index.htm">Libya</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Irwin, Ray W. <hi rend="italic">The Diplomatic Relations of the United
                            States with the Barbary Powers, 1776-1816</hi>. Chapel Hill: University
                        of North Carolina Press, 1931.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kitzen, Michael L. S. <hi rend="italic">Tripoli and the United States at
                            War: a History of American Relations with the Barbary States,
                            1785-1805</hi>. McFarland, 1993.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
