<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776:
                    Liechtenstein</title>
                <title type="short">Liechtenstein</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and Written by Aaron Marrs, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Although the United States has long maintained good relations with <placeName
                        key="li">Liechtenstein</placeName>, Liechtenstein yielded control of its
                    foreign affairs to Switzerland for much of the twentieth century. Therefore,
                    direct diplomatic connections between Liechtenstein and the United States are of
                    relatively recent origin. Liechtenstein began pursuing independent membership in
                    international organizations at the end of the twentieth century. The United
                    States first accredited its Ambassador to Switzerland to serve Liechtenstein in
                    1997.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="liechtenstein-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Liechtenstein</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Liechtenstein, <date when="1926">1926</date>.</head>
                    <p>Formerly a part of the Holy Roman Empire, Liechtenstein achieved sovereignty
                        in 1806, joined the German Confederation in 1815, and became independent
                        again in 1866. The United States executed its first treaty with
                        Liechtenstein in 1926, although Liechtenstein was represented in foreign
                        affairs at the time by <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>. Because
                        Switzerland and Liechtenstein allowed free passage between their two
                        countries, an exchange of notes between the Swiss and U.S. governments
                        extended rights of a U.S.-Swiss agreement to include citizens of
                        Liechtenstein as well.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="relations">
                <head>History of Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1997"
                        >1997</date>.</head>
                    <p>On February 10, 1997, U.S. Ambassador to Switzerland <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/kunin-madeleine-may">Madeleine M.
                            Kunin</ref> was the first U.S. Ambassador accredited to Liechtenstein,
                        resident at Bern.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/9403.htm">Liechtenstein</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/ls/index.htm">Liechtenstein</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
