<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Lithuania</title>
                <title type="short">Lithuania</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, March 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The United States first established diplomatic relations with <placeName key="lt">Lithuania</placeName> on July 28, 1922. The U.S. representative to
                    Lithuania was stationed at the Legation in Riga, Latvia until Legation
                    <placeName key="kovno">Kovno</placeName> was established May 31, 1930. The
                    Soviet invasion and annexation of Lithuania and the other Baltic States of
                    Estonia and Latvia in 1940 forced the closure of the American legation, but
                    Lithuanian representation in the United States continued uninterrupted. The
                    United States never recognized the forcible incorporation of Lithuania into the
                    Soviet Union and views the present Government of Lithuania as a legal
                    continuation of the interwar republic.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="lithuania-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Lithuania</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States Recognition of Lithuania, <date when="1922">1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Lithuania on July 28, 1922, when the U.S.
                        Commissioner at Riga, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/young-evan-erastus">Evan Young</ref>,
                        informed the Foreign Office of Lithuania of the United States’ decision.
                        Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hughes-charles-evans">Charles Evans
                            Hughes</ref> had instructed Young in a telegram dated July 25, 1922, to
                        advise the Foreign Offices of Estonia, Latvia, and Lithuania of this
                        decision on the 28th. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1922">1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on July 28, 1922, when U.S.
                        Commissioner at Riga, Evan Young, informed the Foreign Office of Lithuania
                        that the United States’ recognized its independence and that he would
                        continue as the American representative to the three Baltic States, with the
                        new rank of Minister. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Legation established at <placeName key="kovno">Kovno</placeName>
                        (later Kaunas), <date when="1922">1922</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Legation at Kovno was established on May 31, 1930, with
                        <persName>Hugh S. Fullerton</persName> as Charge d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>. Previous U.S. diplomatic representatives
                        to Lithuania also had been accredited to Estonia and Latvia, and had resided
                        in Riga. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Legation at <placeName key="kovno">Kaunas</placeName> Closed, <date when="1940">1940</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Legation at Kaunas was closed on September 5, 1940, after the USSR
                        occupied and annexed Lithuania, as well as Estonia and Latvia, in August
                        1940. Although the Soviet actions forced the closure of the American
                        Legation and ended the de facto independence of Lithuania, the United States
                        never recognized the state’s forcible incorporation into the Soviet Union.
                        The U.S. Government permitted Lithuanian representatives accredited by the
                        last independent government to remain in the United States with diplomatic
                        status, and the U.S. position remained that diplomatic relations continued
                        uninterrupted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Recognition of Lithuanian Independence from the USSR, <date when="1991">1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. recognized the restoration of Lithuania’s independence on September
                        2, 1991, in an announcement by President <persName>George H.W.
                            Bush</persName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Resumption of Normal Relations, <date when="1991">1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States and Lithuania resumed normal diplomatic relations on
                        September 6, 1991, when U.S. Deputy Assistant Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/kamman-curtis-w">Curtis Kamman</ref>
                        and the Lithuanian First Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs,
                        <persName>Valdemaras Katkus</persName>, signed a memorandum of
                        understanding concerning diplomatic relations.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy at <placeName>Vilnius</placeName> Opened, <date when="1991">1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Embassy at <placeName key="vilnius">Vilnius</placeName> was
                        established October 2, 1991, with <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/johnson-darryl-norman">Darryl N.
                            Johnson</ref> as Chargé d'Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5379.htm">Lithuania</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/lh/">Lithuania</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>