<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Madagascar</title>
                <title type="short">Madagascar</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Relations between <placeName key="mg">Madagascar</placeName> (formerly the
                    Malagasy Republic) and the United States date to the middle 1800s. John P.
                    Finkelmeier was appointed Commercial Agent in Tamatave on February 13, 1866. The
                    two countries concluded a commercial convention in 1867 and a treaty of peace,
                    friendship, and commerce in 1881. Finkelmeier was appointed Consul on June 17,
                    1874. In 1890, France assumed sovereignty over Madagascar as a colony. The U.S.
                    consulate moved from Tamatave to Tananarivo on or around July 8, 1916.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="madagascar-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Madagascar</head>
                </figure>
                <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                    <head>Recognition</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>U.S. Recognition of Malagasy Independence, <date when="1960"
                                >1960</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United States recognized the Malagasy Republic on June 25, 1960, when
                            President <persName>Dwight D. Eisenhower</persName> sent a letter to
                            that effect to President <persName>Philibert Tsiranana</persName>. The
                            area that became the Malagasy Republic had been previously under French
                            sovereignty.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Elevation of U.S. Consulate to Embassy and Establishment of Diplomatic
                            Relations, <date when="1960">1960</date>.</head>
                        <p>With the establishment of the independent Malagasy Republic, the American
                            Consulate at <placeName key="antananarivo">Tananarive (now
                                Antananarivo)</placeName> was elevated to Embassy status on June 25,
                            1960 with former Consul <persName>J. Roland Jacobs</persName> as Charge
                            d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>First U.S. Ambassador to the Malagasy Republic Appointed, <date
                                when="1960">1960</date>.</head>
                        <p>
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/bartlett-frederic-pearson"
                                >Frederic P. Bartlett </ref>was appointed Ambassador to the Malagasy
                            Republic on August 27, 1960.</p>
                    </div>

                </div>
                <div type="appendix">
                    <head>Resources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5460.htm">Madagascar</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                target="http://www.state.gov/p/af/ci/ma">Madagascar</ref>
                        </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
