<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776:
                    Mecklenburg-Strelitz</title>
                <title type="short">Mecklenburg-Strelitz*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States announced its independence from Great Britain in 1776,
                        <placeName xml:id="xz">Mecklenburg-Strelitz</placeName> was a sovereign,
                    independent duchy. Although it joined the Confederation of the Rhine in 1808, it
                    later joined the states allied against Napoleon. Following the Congress of
                    Vienna in 1815, the duchy was raised to a grand duchy, and the Grand Duchy of
                    Mecklenburg-Strelitz joined the German Confederation. Although it was a separate
                    and independently sovereign state from its neighbor, Mecklenburg-Schwerin, both
                    Mecklenburgs shared the same diet and constitution.</p>
                <p>The United States and Mecklenburg-Strelitz established mutual recognition in
                    1853. In the 1866 Austro-Prussian War, Mecklenburg-Strelitz sided with Prussia
                    and subsequently joined the North German Confederation. In 1871,
                    Mecklenburg-Strelitz became part of the German Empire. From this point forward,
                    foreign policy of the German Empire was made in Berlin, with the German Kaiser
                    (who was also the King of Prussia) accrediting ambassadors of foreign nations.
                    Relations with Imperial Germany were severed when the U.S. declared war in
                    1917.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1853">1853</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first known act of mutual recognition between the United States and the
                        Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Strelitz occurred on December 2, 1853, when the
                        Government of Mecklenburg-Strelitz signed the Declaration of Accession to
                        the Convention for the Extradition of Criminals, Fugitive from Justice, of
                        June 16, 1852 Between the United States and Prussia and Other States of the
                        Germanic Confederation to provide for the “reciprocal extradition of
                        fugitive criminals, in special cases.” </p>
                    <p>U.S. archival materials suggest that the date of mutual recognition may have
                        been as early as May 13, 1834, when U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/mclane-louis">Louis McLane</ref>
                        granted an exequatur to <persName>Leon Herckenrath</persName> as Consul of
                        the Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg at Charleston. Unfortunately, this
                        correspondence and others in the Department of State archives does not
                        designate which Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg Herckenrath represented.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations.</head>
                    <p>The United States and the Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Strelitz never
                        established diplomatic relations.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Declaration of Accession to the Convention for the Extradition of
                        Criminals, Fugitive from Justice, of June 16, 1852, between the United
                        States and Prussia and Other States of the Germanic Confederation, <date
                            when="1853">1853</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 2, 1853, the Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Sterlitz signed the
                        Declaration of Accession to the Convention for the Extradition of Criminals,
                        Fugitive from Justice, of June 16, 1852 Between the United States and
                        Prussia and Other States of the Germanic Confederation to provide for the
                            <quote>“reciprocal extradition of fugitive criminals, in special cases.”
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mecklenburg-Sterlitz Joins the North German Confederation, <date
                            when="1867">1867</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following the Austro-Prussian War of 1866, the Grand Duchy of
                        Mecklenburg-Sterlitz joined the North German Confederation in 1867 when it
                        was created as a federal state.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mecklenburg-Sterlitz Joins the German Empire, <date when="1871"
                            >1871</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Sterlitz joined the German Empire, which was
                        proclaimed on January 18, 1871.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>German Unification.</head>
                    <p>The Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Sterlitz was one of the states involved in the
                        process of German unification during the mid-nineteenth century. (See “<ref
                            target="/countries/issues/german-unification">Unification of German
                            States</ref>” for greater detail.)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi> (Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law</hi>
                        (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">Four Phases of American
                            Development</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, 1912).</bibl>
                    <bibl>James J. Sheehan, <hi rend="italic">German History 1770-1866,</hi>
                        (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1989).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
