<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Mexico</title>
                <title type="short">Mexico</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, March 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Diplomatic relations between the United States and <placeName key="mx"
                        >Mexico</placeName> have been intimate and often contentious. At the outset,
                    the issue of granting recognition to an independent Mexico divided American
                    leaders such as <persName>Henry Clay</persName> and <persName>John Quincy
                        Adams</persName>. After finally recognizing Mexico in 1822, the U.S. push
                    for territorial expansion led to a war between the two countries (1846-48).
                    Political instability in Mexico followed and produced strains in U.S.-Mexican
                    relations. Diplomatic relations have not been severed since 1917.<figure>
                        <graphic url="mexico-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Mexico</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States Recognition of Mexican Independence, <date when="1822"
                            >1822</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Mexico on December 12, 1822, when President
                            <persName>James Monroe</persName> received <persName>José Manuel
                            Zozaya</persName> as Mexican Minister to the United States. Earlier
                        Mexican attempts to garner U.S. recognition had failed, largely due to the
                        desire of American presidents to remain formally neutral during hostilities
                        between Spanish forces and independence fighters in the American republics.
                        Previously, Mexico was under Spanish sovereignty. This changed when Napoleon
                        Bonaparte led the French invasion of Spain in 1808, which provided Latin
                        Americans an opening to fight for independence from Spanish colonial
                        rule.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1822"
                        >1822</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on December 12, 1822, when President
                        James Monroe received José Manuel Zozaya as Mexican Minister to the United
                        States.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Legation in <placeName key="mexico-city"
                            >Mexico City</placeName>, <date when="1825">1825</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation in Mexico was established on June 1, 1825, when <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/poinsett-joel-roberts">Joel Robert
                            Poinsett</ref> presented his credentials as Envoy Extraordinary and
                        Minister Plenipotentiary to President <persName>Guadalupe
                            Victoria</persName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed by Mexico, <date when="1845"
                        >1845</date>.</head>
                    <p>In 1836 settlers in <placeName>Texas</placeName> declared themselves
                        independent from Mexico. The United States recognized the Republic of Texas
                        on March 7, 1837. On August 23, 1843, the Mexican foreign minister informed
                        U.S. Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Mexico, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/thompson-waddy">Waddy Thompson</ref>,
                        that U.S. annexation of Texas would be grounds for war. On March 1, 1845,
                        U.S. President <persName>John Tyler</persName> signed a congressional joint
                        resolution favoring the annexation of Texas. On March 4, 1845, U.S.
                        President <persName>James Knox Polk</persName> noted his approval of the
                        “reunion” of the Republic of Texas with the United States in his inaugural
                        address. In response, the Mexican Minister of Foreign Affairs informed U.S.
                        Minister to Mexico, <persName>Wilson Shannon</persName>, on March 28, 1845,
                        that Mexico was severing diplomatic relations with the United States. In
                        December 1845 Texas was admitted to the union as the twenty-eighth state. In
                        April 1846, Mexican troops attacked what they perceived to be invading U.S.
                        forces that had occupied territory claimed by both Mexico and the United
                        States, and on May 13, the<ref
                            target="/milestones/1830-1860/texas-annexation">U.S. Congress declared
                            war against Mexico</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Reestablished, <date when="1848">1848</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Treaty of <placeName key="guadalupe-hidalgo"
                            >Guadalupe-Hidalgo</placeName>, signed in Mexico City on February 2,
                        1848, and ratified by the Senate on March 10, 1848, ended the war.
                        Diplomatic relations were reestablished on December 4, 1848, when U.S.
                        President James K. Polk accepted <persName>Luis de la Rosa</persName>’s
                        credentials as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to the
                        United States.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed by the United States, <date when="1858"
                            >1858</date>.</head>
                    <p>Citing mistreatment of U.S. citizens and their property by the Mexican
                        Government, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Mexico <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/forsyth-john">John Forsyth</ref>
                        “suspended” relations, on June 21, 1858, between the legation and the
                        conservative government of <persName>Miguel Miramón y Tarelo</persName>,
                        which had displaced the liberal government of <persName>Benito
                            Juárez</persName>, pending instructions from President Buchanan.
                        Buchanan assented and recalled Forsyth on July 15, 1858.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Reestablished, <date when="1859">1859</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were reestablished on April 6, 1859, when Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Mexico, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/mclane-robert-milligan">Robert M.
                            McLane</ref>, presented his credentials to President Benito Juárez.
                        McLane also recognized Juarez’s government as the sole legitimate government
                        of Mexico (despite its placement outside the national capital, which was
                        occupied by the rival presidential claimant, Miguel Miramón y Tarelo.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1899"
                            >1899</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Legation in Mexico was raised to Embassy status on January 3, 1899, when
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/clayton-powell">Powell
                            Clayton</ref> presented his credentials as Ambassador Extraordinary and
                        Plenipotentiary to President Porfirio Díaz.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed by Mexico, <date when="1914"
                        >1914</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following the Tampico Incident of April 9, 1914, when Mexican military forces
                        arrested two U.S. naval officers and seven crew members and marched them
                        through the streets, U.S. President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>
                        ordered the bombardment and occupation of <placeName key="veracruz"
                            >Veracruz</placeName> by the U.S. Marines. In reaction to the U.S.
                        occupation of Veracruz, Mexican officials severed diplomatic relations with
                        the United States on April 22, when they handed Chargé d’Affaires <hi
                            rend="italic">ad interim</hi> O’Shaughnessy his passport and requested
                        his departure from Mexico (they provided him with a special train to
                        Veracruz, still held by U.S. forces).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Reestablished, <date when="1917">1917</date>.</head>
                    <p>President Huerta resigned on July 15, 1914. The United States recognized the
                        government of General <persName>Venustiano Carranza</persName> as the de
                        facto government of Mexico on October 19, 1915, in a letter from the
                        Department of State to the Carranza government. On the same day, Secretary
                        of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Robert
                            Lansing</ref> invited Carranza to dispatch a diplomatic representative
                        for formal reception in Washington. Diplomatic relations were reestablished
                        on March 3, 1917, when U.S. Ambassador <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/fletcher-henry-prather">Henry P.
                            Fletcher</ref> presented his credentials to President Carranza.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-mexico/">Mexico</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/mexico/">Mexico</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
