<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Monaco</title>
                <title type="short">Monaco</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, March 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States announced its independence from Great Britain in 1776, the
                        <placeName key="mc">Principality of Monaco</placeName> was a sovereign,
                    independent country under the military protection of the King of France,
                        <persName>Louis XVI</persName>. Although Monaco was directly annexed to the
                    First French Republic in 1793 during the French Revolution, it regained its
                    independence and sovereignty in 1814, both of which were reaffirmed by the 1815
                    Treaty of Vienna. From 1815-1861 Monaco had the protectorship of the Kingdom of
                    Piedmont-Sardinia, and since 1861 it has been under the military safeguard of
                    France.</p>
                <p>Monaco and the United States exchanged their first consular agents in the years
                    following the U.S. Civil War. Since then, the two countries have had overlapping
                    ties, strengthened early-on by <persName>Prince Albert I</persName> of Monaco
                    who travelled the United States three times between 1868 and 1921. During World
                    War I, the principality hosted American soldiers. The marriage of Philadelphia
                    native <persName>Grace Kelly</persName> to Monaco’s <persName>Prince Rainier
                        III</persName> in 1956 further cemented the bond between Monaco and the
                    United States.</p>
                <p>Monaco joined the United Nations in 1993 and the Council of Europe in October
                    2004. In 2005 France and Monaco renegotiated the 1918 Franco-Monégasque Treaty.
                    Under the new provisions, which reaffirmed the independence and sovereignty of
                    Monaco, full direct diplomatic relations between Monaco and other countries has
                    occurred and Monaco began to receive foreign Ambassadors. <figure>
                        <graphic url="monaco-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Monaco</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>First Official State-to-State Interaction, <date when="1865"
                        >1865</date>.</head>
                    <p>It was in the years following the U.S. Civil War that the United States and
                        Monaco, both established states, began commercial relations. Although the
                        Prince of Monaco appointed <persName>Louis Borg</persName> to serve as his
                        consul to the United States in New York on May 19, 1865, nearly another year
                        passed before Borg was able to present his official credentials to the
                        United States Government. Borg, already serving in New York as the
                        Chancellor of the French Consulate, had to obtain special authority from the
                        Emperor of the French <persName>Napoleon III</persName> to also hold the
                        post of Monégasque consul. This dispensation was granted, and in May 1866
                        Borg was fully accredited by the United States as consul for the
                        Principality of Monaco.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_relations">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of U.S. Consul in Monaco, <date when="1874"
                        >1874</date>.</head>
                    <p>The late-1860s was an era of increased tourism for Monaco, due to the
                        construction of railways to provide greater access to the principality, as
                        well as the establishment of the casino in <placeName key="monte-carlo"
                            >Monte Carlo</placeName>. Consequently, the United States appointed its
                        first consular representative to Monaco, <persName>Emile de Loth</persName>,
                        on January 30, 1874, as Consular Agent. De Loth was accredited by the Prince
                        of Monaco on February 22, 1874. This post was ordered closed on February 16,
                        1906, and moved to Nice.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Full Diplomatic Relations, <date when="2006">December
                                2006.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>The United States and Monaco established full diplomatic relations on
                            December 8, 2006, when the first Monégasque ambassador to the United
                            States, <persName>Gilles Noghès</persName>, presented his letters of
                            credence to President <persName>George W. Bush</persName>. U.S.
                            Ambassador to Monaco <persName>Craig Stapleton</persName> presented his
                            credentials to <persName>Prince Albert II</persName> on December 13,
                            2006. Stapleton was resident in Paris.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="treaties_agreements">
                    <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Treaty of Extradition, <date when="1939">1939.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>On February 15, 1939, a treaty of extradition was signed between the
                            United States and the Principality of Monaco. This treaty was ratified
                            on August 30, 1939.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Agreement on Passport Visas, <date when="1952">1952.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>An agreement on passport visas for United States and Monégasque citizens
                            entered into force on March 31, 1952.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Tax Information Exchange Agreement, <date when="2009">2009.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>On September 8, 2009, the United States and the Principality of Monaco
                            signed a Tax Information Exchange Agreement. The agreement provides for
                            the exchange of information relating to tax matters, and was signed in
                            Washington, D.C., by the Honorable Neal S. Wolin, Deputy Secretary, U.S.
                            Department of The Treasury, and H.E. Franck Biancheri, Government
                            Councilor for External Relations and for International Economic and
                            Financial Affairs for the Principality of Monaco. The agreement entered
                            into force on March 11, 2010. (View the <ref
                                target="http://www.state.gov/documents/organization/140168.pdf">text
                                of the agreement</ref>.) </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_event">
                        <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                        <div type="timeline">
                            <head>Reception of Monégasque Prince by U.S. President, <date
                                    when="1913">1913.</date>
                            </head>
                            <p>On October 20, 1913, <persName>Prince Albert I</persName> of Monaco
                                was received at the White House by U.S. President <persName>Woodrow
                                    Wilson</persName>. This was Prince Albert’s second trip to the
                                United States, one that took him through the Midwest and Western
                                states, where he met with <persName>Col. William Frederick
                                    Cody</persName>, commonly known as “Buffalo Bill.”</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="timeline">
                            <head>Franco-Monégasque Treaty Signed, <date when="1918">1918.</date>
                            </head>
                            <p>The Franco-Monégasque Treaty, later confirmed by the Treaty of
                                Versailles (Article 436), stated that France would defend the
                                independence and sovereignty of Monaco. In return, Monaco was not to
                                conduct a foreign policy at odds with that of the French
                                Republic.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="timeline">
                            <head>Marriage of Grace Kelly to Prince Rainier III, <date when="1956"
                                    >1956.</date>
                            </head>
                            <p>American actress and Philadelphia native Grace Kelly married Monaco’s
                                Prince Rainier III on April 18, 1956, an act that brought the two
                                states closer together.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="appendix">
                        <head>Resources</head>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                    target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/3397.htm">Monaco</ref>
                            </bibl>
                            <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                    target="http://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/mn">Monaco</ref>
                            </bibl>
                            <bibl>Grinda, Georges. <hi rend="italic">The Principality of Monaco:
                                    State, International Status, Institutions</hi>. The Hague:
                                T.M.C. Asser Press, 2006.</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
