<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Mongolia</title>
                <title type="short">Mongolia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Evan Dawley, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p> For roughly 200 years prior to 1911, what is today the nation of <placeName key="mn">Mongolia</placeName> was contained within the territorial borders
                    of the Empire of <placeName>China</placeName>. After the collapse of that
                    empire, a group of Mongolia nationalists established a new republic in 1924,
                    with the assistance of the Soviet Union. Mongolians affirmed their independence
                    in a plebiscite in October 1945, but because Mongolia remained close to the
                    <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName>, relations between Mongolia and the
                    United States were slow to develop.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="mongolia-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Mongolia</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Mongolia, <date when="1987">1987</date>.</head>
                    <p> The United States recognized the People’s Republic of Mongolia on January
                        27, 1987, when the two nations established formal diplomatic relations in a
                        joint communiqué. Prior to this, the United States had on several occasions
                        during the Kennedy, Johnson, Nixon, and Carter Administrations entertained
                        the possibility of recognition, both through internal discussions and
                        informal discussions with Mongolian representatives, without success.
                        Although the United States had not blocked Mongolia’s 1961 entrance into the
                        UN (the United States abstained), and had signed several multilateral
                        treaties to which Mongolia was also a party, these acts had not constituted
                        recognition.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1987">1987</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established diplomatic relations with Mongolia on January
                        27, 1987, when the United States and Mongolia issued a joint communiqué to
                        that effect. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Embassy in Mongolia, <date when="1988">1988</date>.</head>
                    <p> The American Embassy at <placeName key="ulaanbaatar">Ulaanbaatar</placeName>
                        was opened on April 17, 1988, with <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/mann-steven-robert">Steven Mann</ref>
                        as Chargé d'Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2779.htm">Mongolia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/p/eap/ci/mg/index.htm">Mongolia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>