<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Montenegro</title>
                <title type="short">Montenegro</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Nathaniel Smith, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The Great Powers of Europe recognized an independent and sovereign Principality
                    of <placeName key="me">Montenegro</placeName> at the Congress of Berlin in 1878.
                    Diplomatic relations between the United States and Montenegro began at the
                    opening of the twentieth century on October 30, 1905. Following World War I, the
                    Kingdom of Montenegro was subsumed into the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and
                    Slovenes, and President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> decided to withdraw
                    recognition of independent Montenegro in 1920.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="montenegro-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Montenegro</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Following the dissolution of the <placeName>Federation of Yugoslavia</placeName>
                    in 1989, Montenegrin independence returned when the Republic of Montenegro
                    declared independence from the State Union of Serbia and Montenegro on June 3,
                    2006. The United States recognized the Republic of Montenegro on June 13, 2006,
                    and established relations with it on August 15, 2006.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States Recognition of Montenegro, <date when="1905"
                        >1905</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Republic of Montenegro on March 3, 1905,
                        when President <persName>Theodore Roosevelt</persName> approved the
                        Diplomatic and Consular Act, which assigned the U.S. Mission to
                            <placeName>Greece</placeName> responsibility for American representation
                        in Montenegro.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Recognition of Independent Montenegro Withdrawn by the United States,
                            <date from="1920" to="1921">1920-21</date>.</head>
                    <p>President Woodrow Wilson made the decision to withdraw recognition of
                        independent Montenegro on December 30, 1920, and on January 21, 1921, Acting
                        Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/davis-norman-hezekiah">Norman H.
                            Davis</ref> informed Montenegro’s Honorary Consul-General,
                            <persName>William F. Dix</persName>, that <quote>“in view of the present
                            status of Montenegro, this Government no longer considers it necessary
                            to accord recognition to her diplomatic and consular officers.”</quote>
                        The United States followed the lead of European powers in withdrawing
                        recognition. Montenegro had sided with the Allied Powers in World War I, but
                        was occupied by Austria-Hungary for a period and <persName>King
                            Nikola</persName> was forced into exile. With the departure of
                        Austria-Hungary’s forces in 1918, French, Italian, and Serbian troops
                        arrived to occupy Montenegro. Serbian leaders quickly convoked a “National
                        Assembly” that voted to depose King Nikola and merge Montenegro into the
                        Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes. One of President Wilson’s Fourteen
                        Points called for the evacuation of Montenegro and other Balkan states, as
                        well as international guarantees for their independence. The <ref
                            target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">1919 Paris Peace
                            Conference</ref> failed to reach a decision on Montenegro, however, and
                        the Allies remained unwilling to intervene against the de facto occupation
                        by Serbian forces.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>United States Recognition of Montenegro, <date when="2006"
                        >2006</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Republic of Montenegro on June 13, 2006,
                        when Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/rice-condoleezza">Condoleezza
                            Rice</ref> released a public statement to that effect. From World War I
                        until 2006, Montenegro had been a constituent part of various incarnations
                        of the state of Yugoslavia. Following the dissolution of the Federation of
                        Yugoslavia in 1989, Montenegro had been part of Yugoslavia’s successor state
                        (named the State Union of Serbia &amp; Montenegro in 2003) until declaring
                        independence on June 3, 2006.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Established, <date when="1905">1905.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on October 30, 1905, when <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/jackson-john-brinkerhoff">John B.
                            Jackson</ref>, U.S. Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary,
                        presented his credentials to <persName>Prince Nikola</persName>. Jackson and
                        his successors resided in Athens, Greece and made annual visits to
                            <placeName key="cetinje">Cetinje</placeName>, the Montenegrin
                        capitol.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Ended, <date from="1920" to="1921"
                        >1920-21</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations ended on December 30, 1920, when President Woodrow
                        Wilson withdrew recognition of Montenegro as an independent state (see
                        Recognitions above).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Re-establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="2006"
                        >2006</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on August 15, 2006, with an exchange of
                        letters between President <persName>George W. Bush</persName> and
                        Montenegrin President <persName>Filip Vujanovic</persName>. The United
                        States had recognized the independence of the Republic of Montenegro on June
                        13, 2006.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Embassy in Podgorica, <date when="2006"
                            >2006</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Embasy in <placeName key="podgorica">Podgorica</placeName> was
                        established on October 5, 2006, when the U.S. Consulate became an embassy,
                        with <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/ferrill-arlene">Arlene
                            Ferrill</ref> as Charge d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                        interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-montenegro/"
                            >Montenegro</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/montenegro/"
                            >Montenegro</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
