<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Nassau</title>
                <title type="short">Nassau*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States announced its independence from Great Britain in 1776,
                        <placeName xml:id="qm">Nassau</placeName> was a sovereign, independent
                    state. With the 1806 dissolution of the Holy Roman Empire, Nassau was enlarged
                    and elevated to duchy status. In 1815 the Duchy of Nassau became part of the
                    German Confederation. The first act of mutual recognition between the Duchy of
                    Nassau and the United States occurred in 1846 when the two states signed a
                    convention to abolish emigration taxes. During the Austro-Prussian War of 1866,
                    the Duchy of Nassau fought on the side of Austria. On the losing side, the Duchy
                    of Nassau was annexed to Prussia on October 3, 1866, and ceased to be an
                    independent, sovereign state.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1846">1846</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first known act of mutual recognition between the United States and the
                        Duchy of Nassau was on May 27, 1846 with the signing of a Convention for the
                        Mutual Abolition of the <hi rend="italic">Droit d’Aubaine</hi> and Taxes on
                        Emigration. This convention was concluded in Berlin between U.S. Minister to
                        Prussia <persName>Henry Wheaton</persName> and Nassau’s Minister to Prussia
                        Col. and Chamberlain <persName>Otto Wilhelm Carl von Roeder</persName>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The first U.S. Consul appointed to the Duchy of Nassau was John B. Muller
                        Melchiors on <date when="1853-11-01">November 1, 1853</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. Consul appointed to the Duchy of Nassau was <persName>John B.
                            Muller Melchiors</persName> on November 1, 1853.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations.</head>
                    <p> The United States and the Duchy of Nassau never established diplomatic
                        relations.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention Abolishing Droit d’Aubaine and Emigration Taxes, <date when="1846">1846</date>.</head>
                    <p> On May 27, 1846, U.S. Minister to Prussia <persName>Henry Wheaton</persName>
                        and Nassau’s Minister to Prussia Col. and Chamberlain <persName>Otto Wilhelm
                            Carl von Roeder</persName> signed the Convention for the Mutual
                        Abolition of the <hi rend="italic">Droit d’Aubaine</hi> and Taxes on
                        Emigration.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The Austro-Prussian War of <date when="1866">1866</date>. </head>
                    <p> In 1866 Prussia and her allies launched a war against Austria and her allied
                        German states. The war, also commonly referred to as the Seven Weeks’ War
                        for the rapidity with which the Prussians triumphed, enabled the Kingdom of
                        Prussia to absorb some of the smaller states that had sided with Austria –
                        in this case, the Duchy of Nassau.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>German Unification.</head>
                    <p>Nassau participated in German unification during the mid-nineteenth century.
                        (See “<ref target="/countries/issues/german-unification">Unification of German
                            States</ref>” for greater detail.)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi> (Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law</hi>
                        (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">Four Phases of American
                            Development</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, 1912).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Elmer Plischke, <hi rend="italic">U.S. Department of State: A Reference
                            Book</hi> (Greenport, CT: Westwood Press, 1999).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>