<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: The
                    Netherlands</title>
                <title type="short">The Netherlands</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Derived from U.S. Department of State, Background Note, November 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="history">
                <head>Historical Overview</head>
                <p>In 1779, while still fighting for independence from Great Britain, the
                    Continental Congress of the United States commissioned <persName>Henry
                        Laurens</persName> as Minister to the Netherlands in order to negotiate a
                    treaty and a loan. The British Navy captured Laurens en route to Europe while
                    carrying a draft of a proposal for a treaty between the newly independent United
                    States of America and the Republic of the Netherlands. Britain subsequently
                    declared war on the Netherlands in 1780.</p>
                <p>The Netherlands, though a republic at the time the two countries established
                    relations, is now a constitutional monarchy, a long-time ally of the United
                    States, and a member of <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/nato">NATO</ref>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="netherlands-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of The Netherlands</head>
                </figure>
                <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                    <head>Recognition</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Dutch Recognition of U.S. Independence, <date when="1782"
                            >1782</date>.</head>
                        <p>The Republic of the Netherlands became the second nation to officially
                            recognize the United States of America when The Hague accepted the
                            credentials of Minister <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john">John Adams</ref> on
                            April 19, 1782.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                    <head>Consular Presence</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Consular Relations, <date when="1789"
                            >1798</date>.</head>
                        <p>The Netherlands acknowledged Sylvanus Bourne as Consul General in
                            Amsterdam on January 2, 1798. The Netherlands also acknowledged
                                <persName>Jan Beeldermaker</persName> as Consul of the United States
                            of America in <placeName>Rotterdam</placeName> also on January 2,
                            1798.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Closure of Consulate in Rotterdam, <date when="1986"
                            >1986</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United States closed its consulate at Rotterdam in 1986.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Other Consulates.</head>
                        <p>From 1821 until after the U.S. Civil War, the United States also had
                            consular representatives in <placeName>Dordrecht</placeName>,
                                <placeName>Harlingen</placeName>, <placeName>Den Helder</placeName>
                            and <placeName>Zierikzee</placeName>.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in The
                            Hague, <date when="1782">1782</date>.</head>
                        <p>Diplomatic relations and the American Legation in <placeName>The
                                Hague</placeName> were established on April 19, 1782, when U.S.
                            Minister <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john">John
                                Adams</ref> presented his credentials.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of the Dutch Legation to the United States, <date
                                when="1783">1783</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United States received <persName>Peter John Van Berckel</persName> of
                            the Netherlands as Minister Plenipotentiary in October 1783.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Closure of American Legation in The Hague, <date when="1801"
                                >1801</date>.</head>
                        <p>The U.S. closed its legation at The Hague in May 1801, so that, as
                            Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/madison-james"
                                >James Madison</ref> explained, the U.S. Government could reduce
                            expenditures. In reality, it was clear that, as an ally of France, Dutch
                            foreign policy was increasingly run by Napoleon. On September 2, 1801,
                            U.S. Minister <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/murray-william-vans">William Vans
                                Murray</ref> departed the Batavian Republic, the last U.S. diplomat
                            accredited to the Netherlands until 1814. During this time, American
                            interests were overseen by <persName>Sylvanus Bourne</persName>, U.S.
                            Consul in Amsterdam. Additionally, from time to time the U.S. minister
                            in Paris would journey to the Batavian Republic/Kingdom of Holland in
                            order to see to American interests. In 1802 the Dutch Minister to the
                            United States <persName>R. G. van Polanen</persName> presented his
                            letters of recall. For more details on the regime changes within the
                            Netherlands between 1795 and 1814, please see “Key Diplomatic Events”
                            below.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Netherlands Under French Control, <date from="1810" to="1814"
                                >1810-1814</date>.</head>
                        <p>Starting with the 1810 abdication of <persName>Louis Bonaparte</persName>
                            from the throne of the Kingdom of Holland, the Netherlands was annexed
                            to the French Empire.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Re-Opening of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1814"
                            >1814</date>.</head>
                        <p>Dutch independence and full sovereignty were regained in 1814 with the
                            defeat of Napoleon. On September 24, 1814, Dutch Minister to the U.S.
                                <persName>François Daniel Changuion</persName> presented his
                            credentials to U.S. President <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/madison-james">James
                            Madison</ref>. On December 19, 1814, the U.S. accredited <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/eustis-william">William
                                Eustis</ref> to the Kingdom of the Netherlands, who presented his
                            credentials on July 20, 1815.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>U.S. Legation moved to London, <date when="1940">1940</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United States closed its legation to The Hague on July 15, 1940,
                            after the German invasion of the Netherlands and reopened the legation
                            in London near the Dutch government-in-exile on August 15, 1940.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1942"
                                >1942</date>.</head>
                        <p>The U.S. legation to the Kingdom of the Netherlands was elevated to the
                            status of an embassy when Minister <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/biddle-anthony-joseph-drexel-jr"
                                >Anthony J. Drexel Biddle Jr.</ref> presented his new credentials as
                            Ambassador to the government in exile in London on May 8, 1942.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>U.S. Embassy Returned to The Hague, <date when="1945"
                            >1945</date>.</head>
                        <p>Ambassador <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hornbeck-stanley-kuhl"
                                >Stanley Hornbeck</ref> oversaw the return of the US Embassy to the
                            Netherlands from London to The Hague on August 17, 1945.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties_agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Amity and Commerce, <date when="1782">1782</date>.</head>
                    <p>On October 8, 1782, the Netherlands and the United States signed a Treaty of
                        Amity and Commerce in The Hague.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention on Recaptured Vessels, <date when="1782">1782</date>.</head>
                    <p>On October 8, 1782, the Netherlands and the United States signed a convention
                        governing recaptured vessels in The Hague.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Commerce and Navigation, <date when="1839">1839</date>.</head>
                    <p>On January 19, 1839, the United States and the Kingdom of the Netherlands
                        signed a Treaty of Commerce and Navigation negotiated by U.S. Secretary of
                        State John Forsyth and the Dutch Chargé d’Affaires near the United States,
                        Evert Marius Adrian Martini.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention on Commerce, <date when="1852">1852</date>.</head>
                    <p>On August 26, 1852, the United States and the Kingdom of the Netherlands
                        signed a Convention on Commerce, designed to supplement the 1839 Treaty of
                        Commerce and Navigation.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention on Consuls, <date when="1855">1855</date>.</head>
                    <p>A convention regulating the rights, duties, and privileges of U.S. and Dutch
                        consuls in the Netherlands and the United States respectively was signed at
                        The Hague on January 22, 1855.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention on Rights, Privileges, and Immunities of Consular Officers,
                            <date when="1878">1839</date>.</head>
                    <p>On May 23, 1878, a Convention on the Rights, Privileges, and Immunities of
                        Consular Officers was signed in Washington, D.C., by the U.S. Secretary of
                        State William M. Evarts and the Dutch Minister Resident in the United States
                        Rudolph Alexander August Eduard von Pestel.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_event">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the Batavian Republic, <date when="1795"
                        >1795</date>.</head>
                    <p>In January 1795 the United Provinces of the Netherlands was overthrown and
                        replaced with a new regime, known as the Batavian Republic, to which a young
                        John Quincy Adams was assigned as U.S. minister. Adams believed the new
                        republic to be an agent of French power.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the Kingdom of Holland, <date when="1806"
                        >1806</date>.</head>
                    <p>In 1806 the Batavian Republic became the Kingdom of Holland, and Napoleon
                        Bonaparte’s brother, Louis Bonaparte, was installed as king. At the height
                        of Napoleon’s domination of the European continent, in 1810 Holland was
                        annexed to the French Empire.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, <date when="1814"
                            >1814</date>.</head>
                    <p>With the defeat of the French in 1814, the Dutch regained independence and
                        full sovereignty, and in 1814 the Kingdom of the Netherlands was
                        proclaimed.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-the-netherlands/">The
                            Netherlands</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/netherlands/">The
                            Netherlands</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Hoekstra, Peter. <hi rend="italic">Thirty-Seven Years of Holland-American
                            Relation, 1803-1840</hi>, (Paterson, N.J.: Eerdmans-Sevensma Co.,
                        1917).</bibl>
                    <bibl>van Minnen, Cornelis A. <hi rend="italic">American Diplomats in the
                            Netherlands, 1815-50</hi>, (New York; St. Martin’s Press, 1993).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Westermann, Johannes Cornelis. <hi rend="italic">The Netherlands and the
                            United States: Their Relations in the Beginning of the Nineteenth
                            Century, </hi>(The Hague: Martinus Nyhoff, 1935).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
