<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: New Zealand</title>
                <title type="short">New Zealand</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Kathleen Rasmussen, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>On September 26, 1907, the constitutional status of the colony of <placeName
                        key="nz">New Zealand</placeName> was elevated to that of a self-governing
                    Dominion in the British Empire. While the new nation was sovereign when it came
                    to its domestic affairs, the United Kingdom maintained control over its
                    relations with the wider world. Over the next four decades, New Zealand
                    gradually gained control over its external policy. The Balfour Declaration of
                    1926, issued at the end of the Imperial Conference held in London that year,
                    recognized that the United Kingdom and the Dominions were <quote>“autonomous
                        Communities within the British Empire, equal in status, in no way
                        subordinate one to another in any aspect of their domestic or external
                        affairs.”</quote> In December 1931, the United Kingdom codified this
                    relationship in the Statute of Westminster, which specified, however, that its
                    provisions would not come into effect until formally adopted by the government
                    of New Zealand. On November 25, 1947, New Zealand’s Statute of Westminster
                    Adoption Act 1947 became law.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="new-zealand-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of New Zealand</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of New Zealand’s Independence, <date when="1942"
                            >1942</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized New Zealand as an independent state with
                        autonomous control over its foreign relations on February 16, 1942, when New
                        Zealand’s Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary <persName>Walter
                            Nash</persName> presented his credentials to President
                            <persName>Franklin Roosevelt</persName>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the New Zealand Legation in the
                        United States, <date when="1942">1942</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations and the New Zealand Legation in Washington were
                        established on February 16, 1942, when Walter Nash presented his credentials
                        as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to President Franklin
                        Roosevelt.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Legation in New Zealand, <date when="1942"
                            >1942</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established its legation in <placeName key="wellington"
                            >Wellington</placeName> on April 1, 1942, under the charge of <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hurley-patrick-jay">Patrick
                            Hurley</ref>. On April 24, Hurley presented his credentials as Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to the Government of New
                        Zealand.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of New Zealand Legation in the United States to Embassy Status,
                            <date when="1948">1948</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 1, 1948, Sir Carl Berendsen, who had been serving as Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary since July 12, 1944, presented
                        his credentials as Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary to President
                            <persName>Harry S. Truman</persName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of American Legation in New Zealand to Embassy Status, <date
                            when="1948">1948</date>.</head>
                    <p>On November 1, 1948, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/scotten-robert-mcgregor">Robert
                            Scotten</ref>, whose credentials as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                        Plenipotentiary had been accepted on April 7, 1948, was appointed Ambassador
                        Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary. On December 22, 1948, Scotten presented
                        his credentials as Ambassador to the Government of New Zealand.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-new-zealand/">New
                            Zealand</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/new-zealand/">New
                            Zealand</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
