<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: North German
                    Union</title>
                <title type="short">North German Union*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The <placeName xml:id="qn">North German Union (Confederation)</placeName> was the
                    product of the 1866 Austro-Prussian War. It was a federal state that comprised
                    21 German states in addition to the Kingdom of Prussia. The German states that
                    did not join the North German Confederation were Wurttemberg, Baden, Bavaria,
                    Austria, and Southern Hesse. The United States recognized the North German
                    Confederation (referred to by the U.S. Government at the time as the North
                    German Union) in 1867, and established diplomatic relations. When the German
                    Empire was created in 1871, it made the North German Confederation obsolete.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of the North German Confederation, <date when="1867">1867</date>.</head>
                    <p> Following the establishment of the North German Confederation on July 1,
                        1867, on November 20, 1867, the U.S. Minister to Prussia, <persName>George
                            Bancroft</persName>, informed Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William H.
                            Seward</ref> that he had attended the opening of the North German
                        Parliament. He requested, however, that the Secretary formally notify him of
                        the intentions of the U.S. Government concerning the question of the
                        recognition of the North German Confederation. On December 9, 1867,
                        Secretary Seward approved of Bancroft’s decision to attend the opening of
                        the North German Parliament since he was the officially-accredited U.S.
                        Minister to the Prussian <persName>King Wilhelm I</persName>, who was also
                        the hereditary President of the North German Confederation. Furthermore,
                        Seward informed Bancroft that he would disseminate a description of the
                        Confederation’s flag so that its ships would be welcomed in American waters.
                        This exchange between Seward and Bancroft implicitly signified a formal
                        recognition of the North German Confederation by the United States. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1868">1868</date>.</head>
                    <p> The U.S. sent <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/bancroft-george">George
                            Bancroft</ref> to serve as Minister of the North German Confederation,
                        in addition to Bancroft’s 1867 commission as U.S. Minister to Prussia. On
                        February 22, 1868, Bancroft concluded the Naturalization Convention with the
                        North German Union to <quote>“regulate the citizenship of those persons who
                            emigrate from the North German Confederation to the United States of
                            America, and from the United States of America to the territory of the
                            North German Confederation.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Diplomatic Relations with the North German Union, <date when="1871">1871</date>.</head>
                    <p> When the North German Union was abolished by the creation of the German
                        Empire in 1871, the United States recognized the legitimacy of and
                        established diplomatic relations with the German Empire. At this point the
                        North German Union was defunct. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>German Unification.</head>
                    <p>The North German Confederation was part of the general process of German
                        unification of the mid-nineteenth century. (See “<ref target="/countries/issues/german-unification">Unification of German
                            States</ref>” for greater detail.)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi> (Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law</hi>
                        (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">Four Phases of American
                            Development</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, 1912).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Elmer Plischke, <hi rend="italic">U.S. Department of State: A Reference
                            Book</hi> (Greenport, CT: Westwood Press, 1999).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>