<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Oldenburg</title>
                <title type="short">Oldenburg*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>
                    <placeName xml:id="qo">Oldenburg</placeName> attained its independence from
                    Denmark in 1773 and in 1777 was elevated to the status of duchy. Thus, when the
                    United States announced its independence from Great Britain in 1776, Oldenburg
                    was a sovereign, independent state. Annexed by France in 1810, the Duchy of
                    Oldenburg was restored and elevated to the status of Grand Duchy following the
                    1815 Congress of Vienna. The United States and the Grand Duchy of Oldenburg
                    mutually recognized each other in 1829.</p>
                <p>During the 1866 Austro-Prussian War, Oldenburg sided with Prussia. In 1867
                    Oldenburg was incorporated into the North German Confederation, after which
                    point foreign policy for the new confederation was conducted out of <placeName
                        xml:id="berlin">Berlin</placeName>. Oldenburg, like the other North German
                    Confederation members, joined the German Empire in 1871. From this point
                    forward, foreign policy of the German Empire was made in Berlin, with the German
                    Kaiser (who was also the King of Prussia) accrediting ambassadors of foreign
                    nations. Relations with Imperial Germany were severed when the U.S. declared war
                    in 1917.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1847">1847</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first known act of mutual recognition between the United States and the
                        Grand Duchy of Oldenburg was on December 2, 1829, when U.S. Secretary of
                        State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/van-buren-martin">Martin Van
                            Buren</ref> issued an exequatur to <persName>Frederick A. Mensch
                            Esq.</persName> as Consul for the Grade Duke of Oldenburg at New
                        York.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations.</head>
                    <p>The United States and the Grand Duchy of Oldenburg never established
                        diplomatic relations.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Declaration of Accession to the Treaty of Commerce and Navigation with
                        Hanover, <date when="1847">1847</date>.</head>
                    <p>On March 10, 1847, the United States and the Grand Duchy of Oldenburg signed
                        the Declaration of Accession to the Treaty of Commerce and Navigation with
                            <placeName xml:id="xx">Hanover</placeName>, to regulate trade, commerce,
                        and navigation between the U.S. and Oldenburg. The declaration was signed by
                        U.S. Special Agent <persName>A.D. Mann</persName> and Oldenburg’s head of
                        Foreign Affairs, <persName>Baron W.E. de Beaulieu Marconnay</persName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Declaration of Accession to the Convention for the Extradition of
                        Criminals, Fugitive from Justice, of June 16, 1852, between the United
                        States and Prussia and Other States of the Germanic Confederation,
                        1853.</head>
                    <p>On December 30, 1853, the Grand Duchy of Oldenburg signed the Declaration of
                        Accession to the Convention for the Extradition of Criminals, Fugitives from
                        Justice, of June 16, 1852 Between the United States and Prussia and Other
                        States of the Germanic Confederation, to establish reciprocal extradition of
                        fugitive criminals in special cases.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Oldenburg Joins the North German Union, 1867.</head>
                    <p>Following the Austro-Prussian War of 1866, the Duchy of Oldeburg joined the
                            <placeName xml:id="qn">North German Union</placeName> in 1867.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Oldenburg Joins the German Empire, 1871.</head>
                    <p>The Duchy of Oldenburg joined the German Empire, which was proclaimed on
                        January 18, 1871.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>German Unification.</head>
                    <p>The Duchy of Oldenburg was one of the states involved in the process of
                        German unification during the mid-nineteenth century. (See “<ref
                            target="/countries/issues/german-unification">Unification of German
                            States</ref>” for greater detail.)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi> (Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law</hi>
                        (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">Four Phases of American
                            Development</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, 1912).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Elmer Plischke, <hi rend="italic">U.S. Department of State: A Reference
                            Book</hi> (Greenport, CT: Westwood Press, 1999).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
