<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Orange Free
                    State</title>
                <title type="short">Orange Free State*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The <placeName xml:id="xt">Orange Free State</placeName> was a Boer republic in
                    southern Africa. The Boers, of Dutch ancestry, had settled the area earlier in
                    the nineteenth century. The 1854 Bloemfontein Convention recognized the
                    independence of the Orange Free State, which was located between the Orange and
                    the Vaal Rivers. The Orange Free State was a republic modeled upon the U.S.
                    constitution, but restricted franchise to white males.</p>
                <p>In 1867 diamonds were discovered in the Orange Free State and by 1870 there were
                    sufficient reserves of diamonds to stimulate a “rush” of several thousand
                    fortune hunters. Other important Orange Free State exports that gained a wider
                    world market during the 1860s were ostrich feathers and ivory, obtained by
                    hunting the region’s elephants. The expanding commercial trade prompted the
                    United States to complete its first international agreement with the Orange Free
                    State, the Convention of Friendship and Commerce and Extradition of 1871, and
                    also recognize the young republic.</p>
                <p>Full diplomatic relations between the United States and the Orange Free State
                    were never established. In 1899, the Orange Free State declared war upon the
                    British and fought alongside its sister Boer republic, the South African
                    Republic, during the Boer War (1899-1902). The British occupied the capital of
                    Bloemfontein in 1900. The 1902 Peace of Vereeniging, which ended the Boer War,
                    annexed the Orange Free State to the British Empire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1871">1871</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first known act of recognition between the United States and the Republic
                        of the Orange Free State occurred in 1871 when plenipotentiaries for the two
                        states signed a Convention of Friendship and Commerce and Extradition on
                        December 22, 1871.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Bloemfontein, <date when="1891-12-16">December 16, 1891</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. Consul assigned to the Orange Free State was <persName>Ernst
                            Richard Landgraf</persName>, who was appointed as U.S. Consular Agent to
                        Bloemfontein on December 16, 1891. U.S. consular agents remained posted at
                        Bloemfontein after its incorporation into the British Empire until the post
                        was closed by agency order on November 30, 1928.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations.</head>
                    <p>The United States and the Orange Free State never established diplomatic
                        relations.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention of Friendship and Commerce and Extradition, <date when="1871"
                            >1871</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 22, 1871, the United States signed a Convention of Friendship and
                        Commerce and Extradition with the Orange Free State in Bloemfonten, Orange
                        Free State. The convention was negotiated and signed by U.S. Special Agent
                            <persName>Willard W. Edgcomb</persName>, who served at the time as
                        American Consul at the <placeName xml:id="capeofgoodhope">Cape of Good
                            Hope</placeName>, and the government secretary of the Orange Free State,
                            <persName>Friedrich Kaufman Höhne</persName>. This convention was
                        denounced on January 4, 1895 by the Government of Orange Free State.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Extradition Treaty, <date when="1896">1896</date>.</head>
                    <p>On October 28, 1896, U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/olney-richard">Richard Olney</ref> and
                        the Consul General of the Orange Free State in the United States
                            <persName>Charles D. Pierce</persName> signed an Extradition Treaty in
                        Washington, D.C.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Colonization.</head>
                    <p>The Orange Free State ceased to exist as an independent, sovereign state in
                        1902 as a result of the process of colonization that carved up much of the
                        African continent into areas of European empire. There were several states
                        like the Orange Free State, with which the United States had treaties or
                        sometimes even diplomatic relations, that were incorporated into another
                        state’s overseas empire.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi> (Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
