<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Pakistan</title>
                <title type="short">Pakistan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The United States and <placeName key="pk">Pakistan</placeName> have generally
                    enjoyed a close relationship since Pakistan’s independence in 1947. Pakistan has
                    historically been a supporter of U.S. foreign policy, specifically during the
                    United States’ opening to China and following the Soviet invasion of
                    Afghanistan. For its part, the United States has striven to lessen tensions
                    between Pakistan and India. Although relations between the United States and
                    Pakistan remain somewhat unsettled over regional disputes and Pakistan’s nuclear
                    weapons program, the United States has provided Pakistan with economic aid
                    through loans and debt relief and is a major supplier of military equipment to
                    Pakistan.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="pakistan-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Pakistan</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Pakistani Independence, <date when="1947"
                        >1947</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Dominion of Pakistan as an independent state
                        on August 15, 1947, when President <persName>Harry S. Truman</persName> sent
                        a congratulatory message to <persName>Mohammed Ali Jinnah</persName>,
                        Governor General of the Dominion of Pakistan, to congratulate Pakistan on
                        its <quote>“emergence among the family of nations.”</quote> The area that
                        became Pakistan had formerly been part of British India within the British
                        Empire.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in
                        Pakistan, <date when="1947">1947</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on August 15, 1947, when the U.S.
                        Department of State established the American Embassy at <placeName
                            key="karachi">Karachi</placeName> with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/lewis-charles-william">Charles W.
                            Lewis, Jr.</ref>, as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                        interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-pakistan/"
                            >Pakistan</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/pakistan/">Pakistan</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Country Study: <ref
                            target="http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/pktoc.html">Pakistan</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
