<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Panama</title>
                <title type="short">Panama</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The area that became <placeName key="pa">Panama</placeName> was part of Colombia
                    until the Panamanians revolted, with U.S. support, in 1903. In 1904, the United
                    States and Panama signed a treaty that allowed the United States to build and
                    operate <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/panama-canal">a canal that traversed
                        Panama</ref>. The treaty also gave the United States the right to govern a
                    ten-mile wide Canal Zone that encompassed the waterway, which was completed in
                    1914. In 1979, the United States transferred control of the Canal Zone to
                    Panama, and in 1999 transferred control and responsibility for the Canal to
                    Panama.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="panama-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Panama</head>
                </figure>
                <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                    <head>Recognition</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>United States Recognition of Panama, <date when="1903"
                            >1903</date>.</head>
                        <p>The United States recognized Panama on November 6, 1903, after Panama
                            declared its independence from Colombia. On November 3, 1903,
                            Panamanians had revolted against the Colombian government, declared an
                            independent Republic of Panama, and established a provisional government
                            junta. On November 6, Secretary of State <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/hay-john-milton">John Hay</ref>
                            instructed U.S. Vice-Consul-General at <placeName key="panama-city"
                                >Panama City</placeName> Felix Ehrman to “enter into relations” with
                            the Government of the Republic of Panama when it appeared to meet
                            conditions of a de facto government having the support of its own
                            people. On the same day, Hay sent Colombian Charge d’Affaires
                                <persName>Tomas Herran</persName> a copy of a cable dated November 6
                            in which Hay explained to the U.S. minister at Bogota, Colombia, that
                            the people of Panama had created an independent republican government
                                <quote>“with which the…United States…has entered into
                                relations.”</quote>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                    <head>Consular Presence</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Consular Relations, <date when="1823"
                            >1823</date>.</head>
                        <p>Consular relations in the part of Colombia that later became Panama were
                            established in 1823 with the appointment of <persName>David
                                Craig</persName> as Consular Commercial Agent at Panama.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1903"
                            >1903</date>.</head>
                        <p>Diplomatic relations were established on November 13, 1903, when
                            President Theodore Roosevelt accepted the credentials of
                                <persName>Philippe Bunau-Varilla</persName> as Panama’s Minister to
                            the United States.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of U.S. Diplomatic Mission, <date when="1903"
                                >1903</date>.</head>
                        <p>The U.S. diplomatic mission in Panama was established on December 25,
                            1903, when <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/buchanan-william-insco">William
                                Buchanan</ref> presented his credentials as Envoy Extraordinary and
                            Minister Plenipotentiary on special mission to Panamanian
                            authorities.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Diplomatic Relations Interrupted, <date when="1931"
                            >1931</date>.</head>
                        <p>On January 2, 1931, a coup d’état was carried out against the Panamanian
                            government and forced the resignation of President <persName>Florencio
                                Arosemena</persName>. Secretary of State <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/stimson-henry-lewis">Henry
                                Stimson</ref> on January 5 instructed Minister at Panama
                                <persName>Roy Davis</persName> not to reply at that time to a
                            representative of the new government who had written seeking continuity
                            in relations with the United States. Stimson informed Davis that he
                            would not receive instructions concerning recognition of the new
                            government until the Department of State was satisfied it could survive
                            and maintain control of the country.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Diplomatic Relations Resumed, <date when="1931">1931</date>.</head>
                        <p>Secretary Stimson wrote to Minister Davis on January 15, 1931, that the
                            Department was satisfied with the legitimacy and viability of the new
                            Panamanian government. Accordingly, Stimson instructed Davis to attend
                            the inauguration of President Ricardo Alfaro <quote>“and carry on normal
                                diplomatic relations thereafter with his government.”</quote> Davis
                            attended the inauguration on January 16, 1931.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Legation Raised to Embassy, <date when="1939">1939</date>.</head>
                        <p>The Legation in Panama was raised to Embassy status on July 14, 1939,
                            when Ambassador<ref target="/departmenthistory/people/dawson-william"
                                >William Dawson</ref> presented his credentials to Panamanian
                            authorities.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Diplomatic Relations Interrupted, <date when="1949"
                            >1949</date>.</head>
                        <p>The Panamanian National Police on November 24, 1949, forced the
                            resignation of President Chanis who was succeeded by <persName>Arnulfo
                                Aria</persName>. On November 25, U.S. Assistant Secretary of State
                                <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/miller-edward-godfrey">Edward
                                Miller</ref> announced that, in view of the circumstances
                            surrounding the change of government, <quote>“diplomatic relations
                                between the United States and the Arias regime in Panama do not
                                exist.”</quote>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Diplomatic Relations Resumed, <date when="1949">1949</date>.</head>
                        <p>Secretary of State <persName>Dean Acheson</persName> announced on
                            December 14, 1949, that <quote>“the United States today is renewing
                                diplomatic relations with Panama,”</quote> and U.S. Ambassador <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/davis-monnett-bain">Monnett
                                Davis</ref> delivered a formal notification to the Government of
                            Panama. Acheson explained that this decision was made after consultation
                            with other American Republics and upon receipt of assurances that the
                            new government would fulfill its international obligations.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed by Panama, <date when="1964"
                            >1964</date>.</head>
                        <p>Panamanian President <persName>Roberto Chiari</persName> broke off
                            diplomatic relations with the United States on January 10, 1964. Chiari
                            accused the United States of “unprovoked aggression” during clashes
                            between Panamanians and U.S. troops in the Canal Zone that followed
                            violence sparked by a flag-raising incident between Panamanian and
                            American students.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Diplomatic Relations Reestablished, <date when="1964"
                            >1964</date>.</head>
                        <p>Panama wanted to renegotiate the 1903 Bunau-Varilla Treaty before
                            resuming diplomatic relations, while the United States promised to
                            discuss all issues after relations were restored. On April 3, 1964, the
                            two states signed a Joint Declaration in which they agreed to
                            reestablish diplomatic relations and to immediately designate
                                <quote>“Special Ambassadors with sufficient powers to seek the
                                prompt elimination of the causes of conflict between the two
                                countries, without limitations or preconditions of any
                                kind.”</quote>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Diplomatic Relations Interrupted, <date when="1968"
                            >1968</date>.</head>
                        <p>On October 11, 1968, President Arias was deposed in a National Guard coup
                            and a “Provisional Junta of Government” was established on October 13.
                            On October 15, the Department of State spokesman announced that
                            diplomatic relations were suspended as a result of events in Panama.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Diplomatic Relations Resumed, <date when="1968">1968</date>.</head>
                        <p>On November 13, 1968, the Embassy at <placeName key="panama-city">Panama
                                City</placeName> informed the Panamanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs
                            that the United States was resuming diplomatic relations. The Department
                            of State announced that the decision was made after consulting with OAS
                            member states and receiving assurances from the new Panamanian
                            government as to its future conduct.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>U.S. Ambassador Recalled, <date when="1989">1989</date>.</head>
                        <p>On May 11, 1989, President <persName>George Bush</persName> recalled
                            Ambassador <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/davis-arthur-h--jr"
                                >Arthur Davis</ref> and reduced the Embassy staff to essential
                            personnel only. Bush explained that he was acting because the people of
                            Panama had <quote>“voted to replace the dictatorship of General Manuel
                                Noreiga,”</quote> but Noreiga refused to give up power. On December
                            20, Bush announced the beginning of U.S. military operations against
                            Noriega’s regime and the return of the U.S. Ambassador to inaugurate
                            relations with a new Panamanian government. U.S. forces eventually
                            captured Noriega and took him to stand trial in the United States on
                            narcotics charges.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <!--<bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-panama/">Panama</ref></bibl>-->
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/panama">Panama</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Country Study: <ref
                            target="http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/patoc.html">Panama</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
