<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Papal States</title>
                <title type="short">Papal States*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>In existence for over a thousand years, the Papal States, also referred to as the
                    Pontifical States, were ruled by the Pope (a temporal ruler) at the time that
                    the United States declared independence from Great Britain in 1776. The first
                    official contact between the two entities occurred in 1784, the first U.S.
                    consul was sent to Rome in 1797, and diplomatic relations were established when
                    the first U.S. diplomatic representative was accredited to the Papal States in
                    1848. The U.S. maintained a legation in Rome until the Papal States were
                    incorporated into the Kingdom of Italy in 1870.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Papal States Recognize the United States, <date when="1784">1784</date>. </head>
                    <p> The first act of official recognition by the Papal States of the United
                        States occurred on December 15, 1784, when American representatives in Paris
                        were approached by the papal nuncio and told that the Papal States “opened
                        the ports of Civita Vecchia on the Mediterranean and Ancona on the Adriatic,
                        to the ships of the young republic of America.” </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The first U.S. consul at Rome, John Baptiste Sartori, was appointed on
                            <date when="1797-06-26">June 26, 1797</date>. </head>
                    <p> Although U.S. representation in <placeName xml:id="rome">Rome</placeName>
                        was not elevated to diplomatic status for nearly a half century, U.S.
                        consuls enjoyed unusual privileges in the Papal States. According to Howard
                        R. Murrow, historian of U.S.-Italian diplomatic relations, U.S. consuls in
                        Rome “were received at all formal functions on the same footing with full
                        diplomatic representatives of other nations.” </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The first representative of the Papal States in the United States.</head>
                    <p>The first representative of the Papal States in the United States was
                            <persName>Count Ferdinando Lucchesi</persName>, who was also the first
                        representative of the Two Sicilies in the United States, and whose exequatur
                        as Consul General of the Papal States at Washington D.C. was signed by U.S.
                        President <persName>John Quincy Adams</persName> on <date when="1826-05-30">May 30, 1826</date>. Consular officers from the Papal States were
                        stationed in various parts of the United States down to at least 1867. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1848">1848</date>.</head>
                    <p> The United States established diplomatic relations with the Papal States
                        when <persName>Jacob L. Martin</persName> was received in Rome on August 19,
                        1848, as the first U.S. Chargé d’Affaires Near the Papal States.
                        Unfortunately, he died shortly thereafter, and <persName>Lewis
                            Cass</persName> was accredited on November 19, 1849, as the new U.S.
                        Chargé d’Affaires. On November 9, 1854, Cass presented his credentials as
                        U.S. Minister Resident to the Pontifical States.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Legation in Rome, <date when="1848">1848</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Legation in Rome was established in 1848 when the first U.S. Chargé
                        d’Affaires Jacob L. Martin presented his credentials on August 19, 1848.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Relations and Closure of the American Legation in Rome, <date when="1867">1867</date>.</head>
                    <p> The American mission to the Papal States closed in 1867 after Congress
                        refused to fund the mission any longer. There were several reasons for this,
                        ranging from religious feeling to domestic politics in the United States to
                        American sympathies for the Italian unification movement. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Proclamation of the Kingdom of Italy, <date when="1861">1861</date>.</head>
                    <p> The aftermath of the Franco-Austrian War brought about a series of
                        plebiscites in the northern Italian states. By going to the ballot box, the
                        states voted to join Piedmont-Sardinia, with the ultimate goal of unifying
                        the entire peninsula. It should be noted that Piedmont-Sardinia was one of
                        the more powerful states in the peninsula, as well as having one of the most
                        liberal political systems. Garibaldi’s march to “liberate” the Kingdom of
                        the Two Sicilies in 1860 brought the southern peninsula into the fold, and
                        the new Kingdom of Italy was proclaimed on March 17, 1861, with the royal
                        family of Piedmont-Sardinia as the new ruling monarchs of Italy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Italian Independence, <date when="1861">1861</date>. </head>
                    <p> The United States officially recognized the Kingdom of Italy when it
                        accepted the credentials of <persName>Chevalier Joseph Bertinatti</persName>
                        as Minister Plenipotentiary of the Kingdom of Italy on April 11, 1861.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Incorporation of Rome into the Kingdom of Italy, <date when="1870">1870</date>.</head>
                    <p> French troops were the main barrier to Italian occupation of the Papal
                        States after 1867; however, when Prussia declared war upon France in the
                        summer of 1870, the Italians took advantage of the situation. With French
                        resources allocated to the struggle of the Franco-Prussian War (1870-71),
                        Napoleon III ordered his troops out of the Italian peninsula. The Italians
                        entered the Papal States in September 1870 and, through the backing of a
                        plebiscite held in early October, annexed the Papal States and Rome to the
                        Kingdom of Italy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Legation to the Kingdom of Italy moves to <placeName xml:id="florence">Florence</placeName> and then Rome, <date when="1871">1865-71</date>.</head>
                    <p> When the Kingdom of Italy moved its seat of government from Turin to
                        Florence in 1865, the U.S. Legation followed. During the summer of 1871, the
                        Italian capital moved from Florence to Rome, reflecting the completion of
                        unification. George P. Marsh, as U.S. Minister Plenipotentiary, oversaw the
                        move of the U.S. Legation from Turin to Florence in 1865 and from Florence
                        to Rome in 1871.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Religion.</head>
                    <p> It is important to note that when the first U.S. diplomatic representatives
                        arrived in Rome, the United States was one of the few countries represented
                        that did not have ties to the Pope as spiritual head of the nation. (i.e.
                        the U.S. was one of the few secular powers with diplomats in Rome.)
                        Then-U.S. Secretary of State <persName>James Buchanan</persName> wrote to
                        the U.S. Chargé d’Affaires in 1848 that <quote>“Your efforts, therefore,
                            will be devoted exclusively to the cultivation of the most friendly
                            civil relations with the papal government, and to the extension of the
                            commerce between the two countries. You will carefully avoid even the
                            appearance of interfering in ecclesiastical questions, whether these
                            relate to the United States or any other portion of the world. It might
                            be proper, should you deem it advisable, to make these views known, on
                            some suitable occasion, to the papal government, so that there may be no
                            mistake or misunderstanding on the subject.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Trade and Commerce.</head>
                    <p> During the early years of the republic, the United States sought to promote
                        trade abroad and to ensure that American vessels, both public and private,
                        would be welcomed in ports around the world. Therefore, the Papal States’
                        recognition of the United States early-on was beneficial to U.S. trade and
                        commerce.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Pietro Orsi. <hi rend="italic">Cavour and the Making of Modern Italy,
                            1810-1861.</hi> (New York: G.P. Putnam’s Sons, 1914).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Denis Mack Smith. <hi rend="italic">Modern Italy: A Political
                            History.</hi> (Ann Arbor, MI: The University of Michigan Press,
                        1997).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Howard R. Marraro. <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic Relations Between the
                            United States and the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies. Volume I:
                            1816-1850.</hi> (New York: S.F. Vanni (Ragusa), 1951.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chiefs of Mission: <ref target="http://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/chiefsofmission/va">Papal States</ref>. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>