<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: The Duchy of
                    Parma</title>
                <title type="short">The Duchy of Parma*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The Duchy of Parma was an independent and sovereign state in 1776 when the United
                    States declared its independence from Great Britain. Although Parma fell under
                    French rule during the Napoleonic Wars, it was reconstituted by the Congress of
                    Vienna in 1815. Mutual recognition between the Duchy of Parma and the United
                    States occurred in 1850 and diplomatic relations were established in 1853. Parma
                    was incorporated into the Kingdom of Italy in 1861.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1850">1850</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first known act of mutual recognition between the United States and the
                        Duchy of Parma occurred in June 1850 when the Duke of Parma appointed a
                        representative to the United States. At the time, this representative,
                        Chevalier Rocco Martuscelli, was the Chargé d’Affaires at Washington for the
                        Kingdom of the Two Sicilies. With consent of the Government of the Two
                        Sicilies, Martuscelli presented his credentials as representative of the
                        Duke of Parma in the United States in June 1850.</p>
                    <!-- <p>Martuscelli died in early 1853. On January 24, 1853, Don Giovacchino Marco di
                        Sastrustegui, the Spanish Minister Resident , was accredited as Consul of
                        Parma for the State of California, resident in San Francisco. From 1853
                        through the 1859 incorporation of Parma into the Kingdom of
                        Piedmont-Sardinia, Spanish diplomats represented the interests of the Duchy
                        of Parma in the United States.</p> -->
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>No Consular Presence.</head>
                    <p>There is no known record of U.S. consular agents sent to Parma prior to its
                        incorporation into the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia (1860) and then the
                        Kingdom of Italy (1861).</p>
                    <p>On January 24, 1853, Don Giovacchino Marco di Sastrustegui, the Spanish
                        Minister Resident, was accredited as Consul of Parma for the State of
                        California, resident in San Francisco.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1853"
                        >1853</date>.</head>
                    <p>On June 20, 1853, U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/marcy-william-learned">William L.
                            Marcy</ref> addressed a note to Don Angel Calderón de la Barca, Minister
                        Resident from Spain, stating that the President would receive him on the
                        following day for the ceremony of presentation of his credentials as Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of the Duke of Parma.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1860">1860</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Ministers of Spain appear to have represented Parma in the United States
                        up to the incorporation of that Duchy into Piedmont-Sardinia in 1860.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Proclamation of the Kingdom of Italy, <date when="1861"
                        >1861</date>.</head>
                    <p>The aftermath of the Franco-Austrian War brought about a series of
                        plebiscites in the northern Italian states. By going to the ballot box, the
                        states voted to join Piedmont-Sardinia, with the ultimate goal of unifying
                        the entire peninsula. It should be noted that Piedmont-Sardinia was one of
                        the more powerful states in the peninsula, as well as having one of the most
                        liberal political systems. Garibaldi’s march to “liberate” the Kingdom of
                        the Two Sicilies in 1860 brought the southern peninsula into the fold, and
                        the new Kingdom of Italy was proclaimed on March 17, 1861, with the royal
                        family of Piedmont-Sardinia as the new ruling monarchs of Italy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Italian Independence, <date when="1861"
                        >1861</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States officially recognized the Kingdom of Italy when it accepted
                        the credentials of Chevalier Joseph Bertinatti as Minister Plenipotentiary
                        of the Kingdom of Italy on April 11, 1861.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Howard R. Marraro. <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic Relations Between the
                            United States and the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies. Volume I:
                            1816-1850.</hi> (New York: S.F. Vanni (Ragusa), 1951), 35-37.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
