<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Peru</title>
                <title type="short">Peru</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Tiffany Hamelin, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>
                    <placeName key="pe">Peru</placeName> and the United States first established
                    diplomatic relations in 1826, five years following the proclamation of Peruvian
                    independence in July 1821 under <persName>General San Martin</persName>. The
                    area that became the Republic of Peru previously had been under Spanish
                    sovereignty. Diplomatic relations have been interrupted due to intermittent
                    territorial disputes with its neighbors, periods of military rule, and coups
                    that have overthrown civilian constitutional government. However, diplomatic
                    ties have never been severed between the two countries. Peru has been a member
                    of the United Nations since 1949.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="peru-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Peru</head>
                </figure>
                <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                    <head>Recognition</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>United States Recognition of Peru, <date when="1826"
                            >1826</date>.</head>
                        <p>The independence of Peru was recognized by the United States by the
                            appointment of <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/cooley-james"
                                >James Cooley</ref> as Charge d’Affaires on May 2, 1826.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>United States Recognition of the Peru-Bolivian Confederation, <date
                                when="1838">1838</date>.</head>
                        <p>Following its independence from Spain, in 1836 Peru joined the
                            Peru-Bolivian Confederation. The United States recognized the
                            Peru-Bolivian Confederation on March 16, 1837 by the appointment of <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/thornton-james-b">James B.
                                Thornton</ref> as Chargé d’Affaires. Thornton was commissioned to
                            Peru but received by the Peru-Bolivian Confederation. Succeeding
                            Thornton, who died in Peru in January, 1838, <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/pickett-james-chamberlayne">J.C.
                                Pickett</ref> was appointed Charge d’Affaires on June 8, 1838. He
                            did not present his credentials until January, 1840. This lapse in
                            diplomatic representation may be attributed to the dissolution of the
                            Peru-Bolivian Confederation in 1839, and the return to separate
                            U.S.-Peru diplomatic relations.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in
                                <placeName key="lima">Lima</placeName>, <date when="1827"
                                >1827</date>.</head>
                        <p>Diplomatic relations and the American Legation in Lima were established
                            on May 21, 1827, when <persName>James Cooley</persName> presented his
                            credentials as Chargé d’Affaires.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of the Peruvian Legation in the United States, <date
                                when="1846">1846</date>.</head>
                        <p>In December 1846, the Government of Peru named <persName>Joaquin José de Osma</persName>, as its first Plenipotentiary Minister to the United
                            States.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1920"
                                >1920</date>.</head>
                        <p>The Legation at Lima was raised to an Embassy on April 24, 1920, when
                            Ambassador <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/gonzales-william-elliott">William
                                E. Gonzales</ref> presented his credentials to the Peruvian
                            Government.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-peru/">Peru</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/peru/">Peru</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Country Study: <ref
                            target="http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/petoc.html">Peru</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
