<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776:
                    Piedmont-Sardinia</title>
                <title type="short">Piedmont-Sardinia*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, January 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States declared independence from Great Britain in 1776, the
                        <placeName xml:id="qp">Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia</placeName> was an
                    independent and sovereign state. The entity referred to commonly in U.S. foreign
                    policy correspondence as the Kingdom of Sardinia is more commonly known as the
                    Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia, as Piedmont and Sardinia were politically joined
                    after 1720. </p>
                <p> Ruled by the House of Savoy out of the capital of Turin, Piedmont-Sardinia sided
                    with Austria when war broke out between Austria and Revolutionary France in
                    1792. The French triumphed and descended into the Italian peninsula, bringing
                    with them revolutionary ideas about government and society, and overthrowing the
                    old established ruling orders. In 1799 the Austrian and Russian armies pushed
                    the French out of the Italian peninsula, which spelled the demise of the
                    fledgling republics. After Napoleon’s rise to power, the Italian peninsula was
                    once again conquered by the French. The House of Savoy fled to Sardinia while
                    Piedmont was annexed directly to the French Empire during the early years of the
                    nineteenth century. Following the Congress of Vienna of 1815, the Kingdom of
                    Piedmont-Sardinia was reconstituted and enlarged to include Genoa. </p>
                <p> The first act of mutual recognition between the United States and the Kingdom of
                    Piedmont-Sardinia occurred in 1802 and diplomatic relations were established in
                    1839. As Piedmont-Sardinia industrialized during the 1840s and 1850s, trade
                    between the two states developed. When the Kingdom of Italy was founded in 1861,
                    the King of Piedmont-Sardinia, <persName>Victor Emmanuel II</persName>, became
                    King of Italy. At this time, the United States appointed its first Envoy
                    Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Italy. The capital of the new
                    kingdom was located in Turin (the old seat of government for the Kingdom of
                    Piedmont-Sardinia). During the next ten years, the seat of government for the
                    new Kingdom of Italy moved twice, first to <placeName key="florence">Florence</placeName> (in 1865) and finally to <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName> (in 1871), and with it, the American Legation. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1802">1802</date>.</head>
                    <p>In an act of mutual recognition, the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia accepted
                        the U.S. Consular Agent at Cagliari, <persName>François de
                        Navoni</persName>, in 1802.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The earliest U.S. consulates in the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia were at
                        Cagliari and Genoa.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. consulate in Piedmont-Sardinia opened at <placeName xml:id="cagliari">Cagliari</placeName> in 1802 with François de Navoni
                        as U.S. Consul. However, the oldest U.S. consulate in the Kingdom of
                        Piedmont-Sardinia was <placeName xml:id="xo">Genoa</placeName>, which was
                        incorporated into Piedmont-Sardinia as a result of the Congress of Vienna in
                        1815. A third U.S. Consulate opened at <placeName xml:id="nice">Nice</placeName> in 1818 with Victor Adolphus Sasserno as U.S. Consul. </p>
                    <p> Piedmont-Sardinia’s first consul in the United States <persName>Gaspare
                            Deabbate</persName> was accredited on May 18, 1820, as Consul General at
                        Philadelphia. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Expansion of Relations, <date when="1839">1839</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established full diplomatic relations with
                        Piedmont-Sardinia on February 7, 1839, when United States accepted the
                        credentials of <persName>Count August Avogadro de Collobiano</persName> as
                        the first Chargé d’Affaires at Washington from the Kingdom of
                        Piedmont-Sardinia. </p>
                    <p> The United States established a legation to the Kingdom of Sardinia at Turin
                        in 1840. The first U.S. Chargé d’Affaires to the Kingdom of
                        Piedmont-Sardinia was <persName>Hezekiah Gold Rogers</persName>, who
                        presented his credentials on September 15, 1840. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Legation in Turin, <date when="1840">1840</date>.</head>
                    <p> The American Legation at Turin was established when U.S. Chargé d’Affaires
                            <persName>Hezekiah Gold Rogers</persName> was accredited on September
                        15, 1840.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Relations, <date when="1861">1861</date>. </head>
                    <p> When the King of Piedmont-Sardinia, <persName>Victor Emmanuel II</persName>,
                        was proclaimed King of Italy on March 17, 1861, <persName>George Perkins
                            Marsh</persName> was appointed U.S. Minister to the King of Italy at
                        Turin on April 26, 1861. That year, the Chargé d’Affaires from
                        Piedmont-Sardinia, <persName>Joseph Bertinatti</persName>, was promoted to
                        Italian minister-resident. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Commerce and Navigation, <date when="1838">1838</date>.</head>
                    <p> On November 26, 1838, the United States signed a Treaty of Commerce and
                        Navigation with the King of Sardinia in Genoa. The agreement was signed by
                        U.S. Special Agent to the Kingdom of Sardinia <persName>Nathaniel
                            Niles</persName> and <persName>Count Clement Solar de la
                            Marguerite</persName>, First Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs of
                        the King of Sardinia. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Franco-Austrian War, <date when="1859">1859</date>. </head>
                    <p> After striking an alliance with <persName>Napoleon III</persName>’s France,
                        Piedmont-Sardinia provoked Austria to declare war in 1859, thus launching
                        the conflict that served to unify the northern Italian states together
                        against their common enemy: the Austrian Army. The Austrians suffered
                        military defeats at Magenta and Solferino, and a ceasefire was agreed to at
                        Villafranca. In the peace negotiations, Austria ceded Lombardy to France,
                        which then ceded it to Piedmont-Sardinia.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Proclamation of the Kingdom of Italy, <date when="1861">1861</date>.</head>
                    <p> The aftermath of the Franco-Austrian War brought about a series of
                        plebiscites in the northern Italian states. By going to the ballot box, the
                        states voted to join Piedmont-Sardinia, with the ultimate goal of unifying
                        the entire peninsula. It should be noted that Piedmont-Sardinia was one of
                        the more powerful states in the peninsula, as well as having one of the most
                        liberal political systems. Garibaldi’s march to “liberate” the Kingdom of
                        the Two Sicilies in 1860 brought the southern peninsula into the fold, and
                        the new Kingdom of Italy was proclaimed on March 17, 1861, with the royal
                        family of Piedmont-Sardinia as the new ruling monarchs of Italy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Italian Independence, <date when="1861">1861.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p> The United States officially recognized the Kingdom of Italy when it
                        accepted the credentials of Chevalier <persName>Joseph Bertinatti</persName>
                        as Minister Plenipotentiary of the Kingdom of Italy on April 11, 1861.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Trade and Commerce.</head>
                    <p> Talks to open full diplomatic relations between the United States and the
                        Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia began in 1837. The original motivation was to
                        stimulate trade and commercial ties between the two states. The United
                        States wanted to modify duties imposed upon its tobacco exports to the
                        kingdom. Moreover, it was hoped that by establishing diplomatic relations
                        and developing trade, both countries would benefit. In addition to tobacco,
                        the United States wanted an export market for raw cotton, fish, timber, and
                        other manufactured items, while it sought to import the silk and cotton
                        fabrics manufactured by Piedmont-Sardinia. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Naval Port.</head>
                    <p> Another issue at stake in diplomatic relations between the United States and
                        the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia was the U.S. desire for a Mediterranean
                        port at which the U.S. Navy could refuel and restock. In June 1848 the
                        Government of Piedmont-Sardinia granted permission for the United States to
                        establish a naval depot at the port town of <placeName xml:id="spezia">Spezia</placeName>. The United States used Spezia until 1868, when
                        Piedmont-Sardinia re-took Spezia for use for its own naval depot. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Pietro Orsi, <hi rend="italic">Cavour and the Making of Modern Italy,
                            1810-1861,</hi> (New York: G.P. Putnam’s Sons, 1914).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Denis Mack Smith. <hi rend="italic">Modern Italy: A Political
                            History.</hi> (Ann Arbor, MI: The University of Michigan Press,
                        1997).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Howard R. Marraro, <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic Relations Between the
                            United States and the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies. Volume I:
                            1816-1850,</hi> (New York: S.F. Vanni (Ragusa), 1951.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Howard R. Marraro, “Spezia” An American Naval Base, 1848-68,” <hi rend="italic">Military Affairs,</hi> Vol. 7, No. 4 (Winter, 1943),
                        202-208.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sister Mary Philip Trauth, “Italo-American Diplomatic Relations 1861-1882:
                        The Mission of George Perkins Marsh, First American Minister to the Kingdom
                        of Italy,” Washington, D.C.: The Catholic University of America Press,
                        1958.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>