<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Poland</title>
                <title type="short">Poland</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Evan Duncan, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>At the height of its power, the <placeName key="pl">Commonwealth of
                        Poland</placeName> included Lithuania, Belarus, and much of Ukraine. It
                    developed a unique form of government in which the nobility elected the king and
                    a single dissenting vote (the liberum veto) stopped any legislation. This system
                    invited foreign intervention and civil war, and made the country vulnerable to
                    more powerful neighbors. In 1772, Austria, Russia, and Prussia conducted the
                    First Partition of Poland. Attempts at reform leading to the Constitution of
                    1791 led Russia and Prussia to conduct a Second Partition in 1793. After
                    suppressing a Polish revolt in 1794, the three powers conducted the Third
                    Partition in 1795. Poland vanished from the map of Europe until 1918; Napoleon
                    created a Grand Duchy of Warsaw from Prussian Poland in 1807, but it did not
                    survive his defeat.</p>
                <p>A Polish Republic was proclaimed on November 3, 1918. On November 14, General
                        <persName>Joseph Pilsudski</persName> became head of state. On January 17,
                    1919, a cabinet was formed with pianist Ignace Jan Paderewski as its Prime
                    Minister.</p>
                <p>The Versailles Treaty of 1919 defined Poland’s western border and granted access
                    to the Baltic Sea by creating a Polish Corridor along the Vistula River. Danzig
                    (now Gdansk), which had a German majority, became a free city supervised by the
                    League of Nations. The League of Nations proposed an eastern ethnic frontier
                    known as “the Curzon Line.” Poland, however, attempted to secure its 1772
                    boundaries with Russia, leading to war with the Soviet Union in 1920. The Treaty
                    of Riga ended the war in 1921, and established an eastern border well to the
                    east of the Curzon Line.</p>
                <p>During the Cold War, U.S.-Polish relations oscillated. Between 1956 and the
                    mid-1960s when Gomulka was in power, U.S.-Polish relations improved; this
                    friendship stagnated during the 1960s, but started to improve again once Gomulka
                    was out of power after 1970. Since 1989, the United States and Poland have
                    enjoyed warm bilateral relations.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="poland-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Poland</head>
                </figure>
                <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                    <head>Recognition</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>U.S. Recognition of Polish Independence, <date when="1919"
                            >1919</date>.</head>
                        <p>The thirteenth of President Woodrow Wilson’s <ref
                                target="/milestones/1914-1920/fourteen-points">Fourteen Points</ref>
                            called for an independent Poland with access to the sea. On January 22,
                            1919, Secretary of State <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Robert
                                Lansing</ref> notified Poland’s Prime Minister and Secretary for
                            Foreign Affairs, <persName>Ignace Jan Paderewski</persName>, that the
                            United States recognized the Provisional Polish Government.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                    <head>Consular Presence</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>First U.S. Consulate, <placeName key="warsaw">Warsaw</placeName>
                            (under Russian administration) <date from="1871" to="1917"
                                >1871-1917</date>.</head>
                        <p>The first U.S. consular post in Poland was a Consulate in Warsaw, which
                            was then under Russian administration. It opened in 1871 and closed in
                            1917.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Consular Posts at Poznan and Krakow, <date when="1946">1946</date>
                            &amp; <date when="1947">1947</date>.</head>
                        <p>Since World War II, the United States has maintained consular posts at
                                <placeName key="poznan">Poznan</placeName> and <placeName
                                key="krakow">Krakow</placeName>. The post at Poznan opened as a
                            Consulate January 16, 1946, became a Vice Consulate May 1, 1947, a
                            Consulate again June 6, 1949, and was closed August 31, 1951. It
                            reopened August 29, 1959, became a Consulate General in 1992 and closed
                            in 1996. The Consulate in Krakow opened July 1, 1946 but closed April
                            17, 1947. It reopened as a Consulate General July 5, 1974 and is still
                            in service.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in Warsaw,
                            <date when="1919">1919</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations and the American Legation in Warsaw were established on
                        May 2, 1919, when <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/gibson-hugh-simons"
                            >Hugh S. Gibson</ref>, the first U.S. Minister to Poland, presented his
                        credentials.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of a Polish Legation in the United States, <date when="1919"
                            >1919</date>.</head>
                    <p>On August 18, 1919, Chief of State Pilsudski announced the appointment of
                            <persName>Prince Casimir Lubomirski</persName> as Poland’s Minister to
                        the United States. Prince Lubomirski was officially recognized on November
                        1, 1919, when he presented his credentials to Acting Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/phillips-william">William
                            Phillips</ref>. He was received by President Woodrow Wilson on May 15,
                        1920.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1930"
                            >1930</date>.</head>
                    <p>Alexander P. Moore was appointed as the first U.S. Ambassador to Poland on
                        January 31, 1930, but died before he could be sworn in. <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/willys-john-north">John N.
                            Willys</ref> was appointed March 8, 1930, presented his credentials on
                        May 24, and served until May 30, 1932.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of Polish Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1930"
                            >1930</date>.</head>
                    <p>Poland’s Minister to the United States, <persName>Tytus
                        Filipowicz</persName>, was promoted to Ambassador and presented his new
                        credentials on March 4, 1930.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Move of American Embassy from Warsaw to Paris, <date when="1939"
                            >1939</date>.</head>
                    <p>World War II began on September 1, 1939, when Nazi Germany invaded Poland.
                        Ambassador <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/biddle-anthony-joseph-drexel-jr"
                            >Anthony J. Drexel Biddle Jr.</ref> left Warsaw on September 5, and
                        followed the Government of Poland to France (September 1939-June 1940).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Move of American Embassy from Paris to London, <date when="1940"
                            >1940</date>.</head>
                    <p>When France fell to the Axis powers in June 1940, the Government of
                        Poland-in-exile moved from Paris to London, and with it, the American
                        Ambassador to Poland <persName>Anthony J. Drexel Biddle Jr.</persName>
                        Biddle was also accredited to the governments-in-exile of Belgium,
                        Czechoslovakia, Greece, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, Norway, and Yugoslavia,
                        all of which were resident in London. Biddle left London on December 1,
                        1943.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Termination of U.S. Mission to the Government of Poland in London, <date
                            when="1945">1945</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. mission to the Government of Poland in London was terminated July 5,
                        1945.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Re-establishment of U.S. Embassy in Warsaw, <date when="1945"
                        >1945</date>.</head>
                    <p>With the end of World War II, the United States re-established its Embassy in
                        Warsaw on July 31, 1945. Ambassador <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/lane-arthur-bliss">Arthur Bliss
                            Lane</ref>, who had been appointed September 21, 1944, presented his
                        credentials August 4, 1945. He served until February 24, 1947.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2875.htm">Poland</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/pl/index.htm">Poland</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
