<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Romania</title>
                <title type="short">Romania</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Evan Duncan, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>In 1862, the Sultan of the <placeName>Ottoman Empire</placeName> allowed the
                    Principalities of Moldavia and Wallachia to unite under the name of <placeName
                        key="ro">Romania</placeName>. In 1866, <persName>Charles of
                        Hohenzollern-Sigmaringen</persName> became Prince. Romania sided with Russia
                    in the Russo-Turkish War of 1877-78. In 1878, the Treaties of San Stefano and
                    Berlin recognized Romania’s independence from the Ottoman Empire. Prince Charles
                    became King in 1881.</p>
                <p>During the twentieth century, U.S. relations with Romania have vacillated between
                    warm (Romania fought on the side of the Allies in the Great War), and cold
                    (Romania declared war upon the United States in 1941 and early Cold War era
                    relations were frosty, at best). The nature of U.S.-Romanian relations began to
                    improve during the 1960s when Romania began to distance its foreign policy from
                    that of the <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName>, especially after the 1968
                    Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia. The 1970s were also a period of warming
                    U.S.-Romania relations fostered by greater cultural, scientific, and educational
                    exchanges; however, during the 1980s criticisms of Romania’s human rights record
                    served to once again strain relations.</p>
                <p>Since Romania’s December 1989 revolution, which unseated the Communist regime,
                    the United States has enjoyed a strengthened relationship with Romania. <figure>
                        <graphic url="romania-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Romania</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Romanian Independence, <date when="1881"
                        >1881</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Kingdom of Romania on April 7, 1881, when
                        U.S. Chargé d’Affaires <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/schuyler-eugene">Eugene Schuyler</ref>
                        had an audience with King Charles and announced that the United States
                        recognized the new kingdom. On April 3, U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/blaine-james-gillespie">James G.
                            Blaine</ref> had authorized Schuyler to recognize Romania after the
                        Great Powers of Europe had done so.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Early U.S. Consulates in Romania, <date from="1866" to="1876"
                            >1866-1876</date>.</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. Consul was appointed to Romania while it was still an
                        autonomous part of the Ottoman Empire. <persName>Louis J.
                        Czapkay</persName>, a native of Hungary but a resident of California, was
                        appointed to <placeName key="bucharest">Bucharest</placeName> on June 20,
                        1866. He served from May 1, 1867 to February 1869.</p>
                    <p>His successor, <persName>Benjamin Franklin Peixotto</persName>, was appointed
                        June 29, 1870, as an expression of U.S. concern with the status of Romania’s
                        Jewish community, which was denied citizenship and subject to persecution.
                        Peixotto, a San Francisco lawyer and a former president of B’nai B’rith, was
                        financially supported by a consortium of American, British, and French Jews
                        since there was little American commerce with Romania. His activities
                        involved not only remonstrating on behalf of Romania’s Jewish community, but
                        establishing schools and cultural societies. He served from February 20,
                        1871 to June 18, 1876. The consulate was abolished that September.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1880">1880.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/schuyler-eugene">Eugene
                            Schuyler</ref> was the first U.S. diplomatic representative to Romania.
                        He was appointed Diplomatic Agent and Consul General on June 11, 1880. The
                        Romanian Foreign Ministry indicated on August 13 that it was willing to
                        enter into provisional relations with the U.S. Legation. Schuyler delivered
                        his credentials on December 14, 1880. He was promoted to Chargé d’Affaires
                        and Consul General on December 21, 1880, and presented his new credentials
                        on January 25, 1881. Schuyler was reaccredited when Romania became a
                        kingdom, presenting his new credentials on May 16, 1881.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of American Legation in <placeName key="bucharest"
                            >Bucharest</placeName>, <date when="1882">1882.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Schuyler was promoted to Minister Resident and Consul General on July 7,
                        1882, and presented his new credentials on September 8, 1882. However, he
                        was also accredited to <placeName>Greece</placeName> and
                            <placeName>Serbia</placeName> and moved his residence to Athens.
                        Schuyler presented his recall on September 7, 1884.</p>
                    <p>Until 1921, no U.S. Minister was commissioned solely to Romania. From 1885 to
                        1905, their commissions were to <placeName>Greece</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Romania</placeName>, and <placeName>Serbia</placeName>, being
                        resident at Athens. <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/jackson-john-brinkerhoff">John B.
                            Jackson</ref> (1902-05) was also commissioned as Diplomatic Agent in
                        Bulgaria in 1903. From 1905 to 1911, U.S. Ministers to Romania were also
                        commissioned to Serbia but were resident in Bucharest. From 1907 to 1910
                        they were also commissioned as Diplomatic Agents in Bulgaria. <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/carter-john-ridgely">John R.
                            Carter</ref> (1909-1911) was appointed Minister to
                            <placeName>Bulgaria</placeName> in 1910. From 1911 to 1918, the U.S.
                        Minister to Romania was also accredited to Serbia and Bulgaria.</p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/jay-peter-augustus">Peter Augustus
                            Jay</ref> was the first U.S. Minister to be commissioned exclusively to
                        Romania. He was appointed April 18, 1921, presented his credentials on June
                        30, and served until May 9, 1925.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Romanian Legation in Washington, <date when="1918"
                            >1918.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Romania established its first diplomatic mission in the United States when
                        Minister <persName>Constantin Angelescu</persName> presented his credentials
                        in Washington on January 15, 1918.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Severance of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1941">1941.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were severed when Romania declared war on the United
                        States on December 12, 1941. The U.S. Minister, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/gunther-franklin-mott">Franklin Mott
                            Gunther</ref>, died in Bucharest on December 22 before he could leave
                        the country; however, the U.S. did not declare war upon Romania until June
                        5, 1942.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Re-establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1946">1946.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were reestablished on October 1, 1946, when
                            <persName>Miha Ralea</persName> presented his credentials as Romania’s
                        first postwar Minister to the United States.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Re-establishment of American Legation in Bucharest, <date when="1947"
                            >1947.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/schoenfeld-rudolf-emil">Rudolph E.
                            Schoenfeld</ref> presented his credentials as the first postwar U.S.
                        Minister to Romania on September 25, 1947.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of American Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1964"
                            >1964.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The U.S. Legation in Bucharest was raised to Embassy status on June 1, 1964.
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/shaw-john-putnam">John P.
                            Shaw</ref> was Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> at
                        the time. On December 4, 1964, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/crawford-william-avery">William A.
                            Crawford</ref>, Minister to Romania since 1962, was promoted to
                        Ambassador. He presented his new credentials on December 24, 1964, and
                        served until October 10, 1965.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of Romanian Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1964"
                            >1964.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Romanian Minister <persName>Petre Balaceanu</persName> presented his new
                        credentials as Romania’s Ambassador on August 14, 1964.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="treaties_agreements">
                    <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>First Diplomatic Agreement Signed, <date when="1881">1881.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>The first diplomatic agreement between the United States and Romania was
                            a convention concerning the rights, privileges, and immunities of
                            consular officers, which was signed in Bucharest on June 17, 1881. It
                            entered into force on June 13, 1883.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="appendix">
                    <head>Resources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/35722.htm ">Romania</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                target="http://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/ro/ ">Romania</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Kennedy, Charles Stuart. <hi rend="italic">The American Consul: A
                                History of the United States Consular Service, 1776-1914</hi>. New
                            York: Greenwood Press, 1990.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Langer, William L. <hi rend="italic">An Encyclopedia of World
                                History</hi>. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1968.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
