<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Russia</title>
                <title type="short">Russia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, March 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Francis Dana</persName>, a prominent member of the Continental
                    Congress and secretary to the American legation at <placeName>Paris</placeName>,
                    was appointed Minister to <placeName key="ru">Russia</placeName> in <date
                        when="1780">1780</date>; however, the Russian Government refused to accept
                    his credentials when he arrived in <placeName key="st-petersburg">St.
                        Petersburg</placeName> in August 1781. Dana nevertheless remained in Russia
                    as a private citizen for two years to promote the American revolutionary cause.
                    In 1795, the Russian Government again declined to receive officially an
                    appointed representative of the United States, when it refused to accept the
                    credentials of John Miller Russell as American Consul at St. Petersburg.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="russia-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Russia</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Russian Recognition of the United States, <date when="1803"
                        >1803</date>.</head>
                    <p>Russia recognized the United States on October 28, 1803, when <persName>Czar
                            Alexander I</persName> issued a ukase declaring his decision to
                        recognize <persName>Levett Harris</persName> as American Consul at St.
                        Petersburg.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1809"
                        >1809</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established formally on July 14, 1809, when
                            <persName>Andrei Dashkov</persName> presented his credentials as Russian
                        Chargé d’Affaires to President <persName>James Madison</persName>.</p>
                    <p>The process of establishing diplomatic relations between the United States
                        and Russia began in August 1807, when the American Minister at London,
                            <persName>James Monroe</persName>, discussed with the Russian Special
                        Envoy at London, <persName>Maksim Alopeus</persName>, the possibility of
                        establishing diplomatic ties between the two states. In December 1807,
                        Alopeus informed the new American Minister-Designate at London,
                            <persName>William Pinkney</persName>, that Emperor <persName>Alexander
                            I</persName> was prepared to send a Minister to the United States as
                        soon as the American government determined the rank of Minister it would in
                        turn send to Russia. On August 30, 1808, Emperor Alexander issued
                        credentials for Andrei Dashkov as Chargé d’Affaires and Consul General at
                        Philadelphia. Meanwhile, the U.S. Senate rejected President <persName>Thomas
                            Jefferson</persName>’s nominee as U.S. Minister to Russia, and also
                        rebuffed newly inaugurated President James Madison, when he nominated
                            <persName>John Quincy Adams</persName> as Minister to Russia in March
                        1809. Madison later resubmitted Adams’ nomination and it won Senate
                        confirmation on June 27, 1809. Soon after, the first accredited diplomatic
                        representative between the United States and Russia took up his post when
                        Chargé Dashkov presented his credentials to President Madison on July 14,
                        1809.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of the American Legation in Russia, <date when="1809"
                            >1809</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation in <placeName key="st-petersburg">St.
                            Petersburg</placeName> was established on November 5, 1809, when U.S.
                        Minister to Russia <persName>John Quincy Adams</persName> presented his
                        credentials to Emperor Alexander I.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Legation Raised to Embassy, <date when="1898">1898</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation in St. Petersburg was raised to an Embassy on February
                        11, 1898, when <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hitchcock-ethan-allen"
                            >Ethan A. Hitchcock</ref> was appointed Ambassador to Russia.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Normal Diplomatic Relations Interrupted, <date when="1917"
                        >1917</date>.</head>
                    <p>Normal diplomatic relations were interrupted following the November 7, 1917,
                        Bolshevik Revolution in Russia. After the abdication of Tsar
                            <persName>Nicholas II</persName> during the February Revolution earlier
                        that year, Ambassador to Russia, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/francis-david-rowland">David R.
                            Francis</ref>, had informed the new Provisional Government that the
                        United States recognized the new government and would maintain diplomatic
                        relations with Russia. On December 6, 1917, following the Bolshevik October
                        Revolution that overthrew the Provisional Government, President
                            <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> instructed all American diplomatic
                        representatives in Russia to refrain from any direct communication with
                        representatives of the Bolshevik Government. Although diplomatic relations
                        with Russia never were formally severed, the United States refused to
                        recognize or have any formal relations with the Bolshevik/Soviet governments
                        until 1933. (The Russian Ambassador accredited to the United States by the
                        defunct Provisional Government, Boris A. Bakhmeteff, remained in the United
                        States until June 30, 1922, at which time he resigned his position on the
                        rationale that the government that had accredited him no longer existed and
                        he had, to the extent possible, liquidated pre-Bolshevik Russian government
                        debts.) </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy Moved Twice, <date when="1918">1918</date>.</head>
                    <p>On February 27, 1918, the American Embassy and the missions of several other
                        states moved from St. Petersburg to <placeName key="vologda"
                            >Vologda</placeName>, due to the close proximity of German troops to St.
                        Petersburg. On August 9, 1918, the American Embassy moved to <placeName
                            key="archangel">Archangel</placeName>, after several embassies in
                        Vologda were harassed by Bolshevik authorities pressuring them to move to
                            <placeName key="moscow">Moscow</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy Closed, <date when="1919">1919</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Embassy at <placeName key="archangel">Archangel</placeName> was
                        closed on September 14, 1919.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Normal Diplomatic Relations Resumed, <date when="1933">1933</date>.</head>
                    <p>Normal diplomatic relations were resumed on November 16, 1933, when President
                            <persName>Franklin Roosevelt</persName> informed Soviet Foreign Minister
                            <persName>Maxim Litvinov</persName> that the United States recognized
                        the Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics and wished to
                        establish normal diplomatic relations. Litvinov on the same day replied that
                        his government was glad to establish normal diplomatic relations and
                        exchange ambassadors.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>American Embassy Established in <placeName key="moscow"
                        >Moscow</placeName>, <date when="1933">1933</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 13, 1933, <persName>William Bullitt</persName> presented his
                        credentials to President <persName>Kalinin</persName> in Moscow as the U.S.
                        Ambassador to the Soviet Union.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Dissolution of the Soviet Union and Recognition of the Russian Federation,
                            <date when="1991">1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Russian Federation as the successor to the
                        Soviet Union on December 25, 1991, when President <persName>George H.W.
                            Bush</persName> announced the decision in an address to the nation. Bush
                        also stated that the Embassy in Moscow would remain in place as the American
                        Embassy to Russia. On December 8, 1991, the leaders of Russia, Belarus, and
                        Ukraine had declared that the Soviet Union ceased to exist and proclaimed a
                        “Commonwealth of Independent States” (CIS) that eleven former Soviet
                        Republics joined on December 21. The formal dissolution of the Soviet Union
                        was completed when <persName>Mikhail Gorbachev</persName> resigned as
                        President on December 25, 1991.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations with Russia, <date when="1991"
                            >1991</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States and the Russian Federation established diplomatic relations
                        on December 31, 1991, when Russian President <persName>Boris
                            Yeltsin</persName> responded positively to President Bush’s proposal to
                        do so.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <!--<bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-russia/">Russia</ref></bibl>-->
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/russia/">Russia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Kennedy, Charles Stuart. <hi rend="italic">The American Consul: A History
                            of the United States Consular Service, 1776-1914</hi>. New York:
                        Greenwood Press, 1990.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Langer, William L. <hi rend="italic">An Encyclopedia of World
                        History</hi>. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1968.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
