<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Saint Vincent and
                    the Grenadines</title>
                <title type="short">Saint Vincent and the Grenadines</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Emily Horne, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Present-day <placeName key="vc">Saint Vincent</placeName> was ceded to Great
                    Britain in 1763 and was briefly under French rule from 1779 until 1796.
                    Following a return to British rule, Saint Vincent passed through a variety of
                    stages as a colony and Commonwealth state. After a 1979 referendum it eventually
                    became the last of the Windward Islands to achieve independence.</p>
                <p>Today the United States and Saint Vincent have solid bilateral relations. Both
                    countries have signed a series of treaties combating the cultivation and
                    shipment of narcotics.<figure>
                        <graphic url="saint-vincent-grenadines-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of St. Vincent and the Grenadines</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of St. Vincent’s Independence, <date when="1981"
                            >1981</date>.</head>
                    <p>St. Vincent and the Grenadines achieved full independence on October 27,
                        1979. The United States had previously informally recognized St. Vincent as
                        a federated state in the British Commonwealth but did not formally recognize
                        its independence until the appointment of <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/bish-milan-d">Milan D. Bish</ref> as
                        American Ambassador to Saint Vincent on November 23, 1981.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <p>The United States maintains no official presence in St. Lucia. The Ambassador
                        and Embassy officers are resident in <placeName>Barbados</placeName> and
                        frequently travel to St. Vincent.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Special Representative to Saint Vincent Appointed, <date when="1977"
                            >1977</date>.</head>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/ortiz-francis-vincent">Frank V.
                            Oritz, Jr.</ref> was appointed United States Special Representative to
                        the States of <placeName>Antigua</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Dominica</placeName>, <placeName>St.
                            Christopher-Nevis-Anguilla</placeName>, <placeName>St.
                        Lucia</placeName>, and <placeName>St. Vincent</placeName> on September 1,
                        1977. The appointment was concurrent to his positions as Ambassador to
                            <placeName>Barbados</placeName> and to
                        <placeName>Grenada</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Established, <date when="1981">1981</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on December 8, 1981, when St. Vincent
                        and the Grenadines Ambassador <persName>Hudson Kemul Tannis</persName>
                        presented his credentials. American Ambassador <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/bish-milan-d">Milan D. Bish</ref>
                        presented his credentials in Bridgetown that same day. He was concurrently
                        Ambassador to Antigua and Barbuda, Barbados, Dominica, and St. Lucia and
                        Special Representative to Saint Christopher and Nevis. All U.S. ambassadors
                        to St. Vincent and the Grenadines have been resident at
                            <placeName>Bridgeport</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="appendix">
                    <head>Resources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-saint-vincent-and-the-grenadines/"
                                >Saint Vincent and the Grenadines</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/saint-vincent-and-the-grenadines/"
                                >Saint Vincent and the Grenadines</ref>
                        </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
