<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: San Marino</title>
                <title type="short">San Marino</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by David Nickles, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p> The United States signed a Treaty of Extradition with <placeName key="sm">San
                    Marino</placeName> in 1906, and established consular relations in 1925, but
                    did not appoint its first diplomatic ambassador to that country until November
                    22, 2006. Nonetheless, it could be argued that the United States recognized San
                    Marino as early as 1861, when President <persName>Abraham Lincoln</persName>
                    warmly accepted its offer of honorary citizenship.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="san-marino-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of San Marino</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of San Marino’s Independence, <date when="1861">1861</date>. </head>
                    <p> The United States recognized San Marino when President Abraham Lincoln, in a
                        letter dated May 7, 1861, accepted San Marino’s offer of honorary
                        citizenship. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Consular Relations, <date when="1925">1925</date>. </head>
                    <p> The United States established a consulate in San Marino on April 9, 1925.
                        The Consul (or Consul General) in Florence has generally been the
                        representative of the U.S. Government to San Marino. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1861">1861</date>. </head>
                    <p> The Government of San Marino, in a March 29, 1861 letter from the Regent
                        Captains, offered U.S. President Lincoln honorary citizenship. On May 7,
                        1861, Lincoln responded, <quote>“Although your dominion is small, your State
                            is nevertheless one of the most honored, in all history.”</quote>
                        Although the United States had consular relations with San Marino dating to
                        1925, it did not accredit an Ambassador to the republic until 2006.
                        Ambassador <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/spogli-ronald">Ronald
                            Spogli</ref>, who was also the U.S. Ambassador to Italy, presented his
                        credentials to San Marino on March 8, 2007, and was resident in Rome. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties &amp; Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Extradition, <date when="1906">1906</date>.</head>
                    <p> On January 10, 1906, the United States and San Marino signed a Treaty of
                        Extradition at Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Extradition, <date when="1934">1934</date>. </head>
                    <p> On October 10, 1934, the United States and San Marino signed a Supplementary
                        Convention to the 1906 Treaty of Extradition at Washington, D.C. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <p>May 1861 was one of the darkest moments in the history of the United States, as
                    the nation faced a civil war that, in the minds of many around the world, raised
                    doubts about the viability of democratic republics. On May 7, 1861, President
                    Lincoln addressed a letter to the Regent Captains of the Republic of San
                    Marino:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Great and Good Friends</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic"> I have received and read with great sensibility the letter
                        which as Regent Captains of the Republic of San Marino you addressed to me
                        on the 29th of March last. I thank the Council of San Marino for the honor
                        of citizenship they have conferred upon me.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic"> Although your dominion is small, your State is nevertheless
                        one of the most honored, in all history. It has by its experience
                        demonstrated the truth, so full of encouragement to the friends of Humanity,
                        that Government founded on Republican principles is capable of being so
                        administered as to be secure and enduring.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">You have kindly adverted to the trial through which this
                        Republic is now passing. It is one of deep import. It involves the question
                        whether a Representative republic, extended and aggrandized so much as to be
                        safe against foreign enemies can save itself from the dangers of domestic
                        faction. I have faith in a good result.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Wishing that your interesting State may endure and flourish
                        forever, and that you may live long and enjoy the confidence and secure the
                        gratitude of your fellow citizens, I pray God to have you in his holy
                        keeping. Your Good Friend. </hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Abraham Lincoln. </hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5387.htm">San Marino</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref target="http://www.state.gov/p/eur/ci/sm">San Marino</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>