<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776:
                    Schaumburg-Lippe</title>
                <title type="short">Schaumburg-Lippe*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, February 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States announced its independence from Great Britain in 1776,
                    Schaumburg-Lippe was a small independent country within the Holy Roman Empire.
                    In 1807 the rulers of Schaumburg-Lippe joined the Confederation of the Rhine. In
                    return, Schaumburg-Lippe was elevated to the status of principality. Retaining
                    its independence and sovereignty after the Napoleonic Wars, the Principality of
                    Schaumburg-Lippe joined the German Confederation in 1815. The first official act
                    of mutual recognition between Schaumburg-Lippe and the United States came in
                    1854. </p>
                <p> Schaumburg-Lippe originally sided with Austria during the 1866 Austro-Prussian
                    War but changed allegiances and joined Prussia. Schaumburg-Lippe subsequently
                    joined the North German Confederation in 1867, and in 1871 Schaumburg-Lippe
                    became part of the German Empire. From this point forward, foreign policy of the
                    German Empire was made in Berlin, with the German Kaiser (who was also the King
                    of Prussia) accrediting ambassadors of foreign nations. Relations with Imperial
                    Germany were severed when the U.S. declared war in 1917. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1854">1854</date>.</head>
                    <p> On June 7, 1854, Schaumburg-Lippe signed the Declaration of Accession to the
                        Convention for the Extradition of Criminals, Fugitive from Justice, of June
                        16, 1852 between the United States and Prussia and Other States of the
                        Germanic Confederation in Buckeburg. This agreement provided for the
                        reciprocal extradition of fugitive criminals in special cases between
                        Schaumburg-Lippe and the United States. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations.</head>
                    <p> The United States and the Principality of Schaumburg-Lippe never established
                        diplomatic relations.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Declaration of Accession to the Convention for the Extradition of
                        Criminals, Fugitive from Justice, of June 16, 1852, between the United
                        States and Prussia and other States of the German Confederation, <date when="1854">1854</date>.</head>
                    <p> On June 7, 1854, the Government of the Prince of Schaumburg-Lippe declared
                        its accession to the convention providing for reciprocal extradition of
                        fugitive criminals in special cases between the United States, Prussia, and
                        other states of the German Confederation. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Schaumburg-Lippe Joins the North German Confederation, <date when="1867">1867</date>.</head>
                    <p>Schaumburg-Lippe Joins the North German Confederation, 1867. Following the
                        Austro-Prussian War of 1866, the Principality of Schaumburg-Lippe joined the
                        North German Confederation in 1867 when it was created as a federal
                        state.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Schaumburg-Lippe Joins the German Empire, <date when="1871">1871</date>.</head>
                    <p> The Principality of Schaumburg-Lippe joined the German Empire, which was
                        proclaimed on January 18, 1871.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>German Unification. </head>
                    <p> The Principality of Schaumburg-Lippe was one of the states involved in the
                        process of German unification during the mid-nineteenth century. See “<ref target="/countries/issues/german-unification">Unification of German
                            States</ref>” for greater detail.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>William M. Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements Between The United States of American
                            and Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi> (Washington DC: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law</hi>
                        (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">Four Phases of American
                            Development</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, 1912).</bibl>
                    <bibl>James J. Sheehan, <hi rend="italic">German History 1770-1866</hi>,
                        (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1989).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>