<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Serbia</title>
                <title type="short">Serbia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Aaron Marrs, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Note: This entry is for the modern state, the Republic of
                        Serbia. Please click <ref target="/countries/kingdom-of-yugoslavia"
                            >here</ref> for information on the Kingdom of Serbia and the Socialist
                        Federal Republic of Yugoslavia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The U.S. shared normalized relations with Yugoslavia until 1992 when Slovenia,
                    Croatia, Bosnia and Herzegovina, and Macedonia all seceded. The republics of
                    Serbia and Montenegro declared a new Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (FRY) in
                    April 1992. On May 21, 1992, the U.S. announced that it would not recognize the
                    Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (FRY) as the successor state of the Socialist
                    Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (SFRY), as Serbia and Montenegro claimed. The
                    U.S. Ambassador was recalled from Belgrade, but the mission continued with a
                    staff under the authority of a Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                        interim</hi>.</p>
                <p>In response to the conflict in Kosovo, and one day prior to the NATO bombing of
                    Yugoslavia, on March 23, 1999, the U.S. severed relations with the Federal
                    Republic of Yugoslavia, and closed Embassy Belgrade. Diplomatic recognition and
                    full diplomatic relations between the two countries were established in November
                    2000, and ambassadorial relations between the two nations resumed with the
                    appointment of <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/montgomery-william-dale"
                        >William Dale Montgomery </ref>as U.S. Ambassador Extraordinary and
                    Plenipotentiary on November 26, 2001.</p>
                <p>In 2003, the FRY became <placeName>Serbia</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Montenegro</placeName>, a loose federation of the two republics
                    with a federal level parliament. The office of President of the Federal Republic
                    of Yugoslavia, held by <persName>Vojislav Kostunica</persName>, ceased to exist
                    once <persName>Svetozar Marovic</persName> was elected President of Serbia and
                    Montenegro in March of 2003. In May 2006, <placeName>Montenegro</placeName>
                    invoked its right to secede from the federation and, following a referendum,
                    declared itself an independent nation on June 3, 2006. Two days later, Serbia
                    declared that it was the successor state to the union of Serbia and
                    Montenegro.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="serbia-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Serbia</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia, <date when="2000"
                            >2000</date>.</head>
                    <p>In an exchange of letters dated November 12, 2000, U.S. President
                            <persName>William J. Clinton</persName> and Federal Republic of
                        Yugoslavia President<persName>Vojislav Kostunica</persName> established full
                        diplomatic relations between the two states. This constituted recognition of
                        the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Normal Relations with Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia
                        Interrupted, <date when="1992">1992</date>.</head>
                    <p>The republics of <placeName>Serbia</placeName> and
                            <placeName>Montenegro</placeName> declared a new Federal Republic of
                        Yugoslavia (FRY) in April 1992. On May 21, 1992, the U.S. announced that it
                        would not recognize the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia as a successor state
                        of the <ref target="/countries/kingdom-of-yugoslavia">Socialist Federal
                            Republic of Yugoslavia</ref>. U.S. Ambassador <ref
                            target="/people/zimmermann-warren">Warren Zimmerman</ref> was recalled
                        from <placeName>Belgrade</placeName>, but the mission continued with a staff
                        under the authority of a Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed, <date when="1999">1999</date>.</head>
                    <p>In response to the continued conflict between
                            <placeName>Yugoslavia</placeName> and <placeName>Kosovo</placeName>, and
                        one day prior to the NATO bombing of Yugoslavia, on March 23, 1999, the U.S.
                        severed relations with the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia, and closed
                        Embassy Belgrade.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Full Diplomatic Relations, <date when="2000"
                        >2000</date>.</head>
                    <p>In an exchange of letters dated November 12, 2000, U.S. President
                            <persName>William J. Clinton</persName> and Federal Republic of
                        Yugoslavia President <persName>Kostunica</persName> established full
                        diplomatic relations between the two states.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Embassy in Serbia Reopened, <date when="2001">2001</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Embassy reopened in May 2001, and <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/montgomery-william-dale">William Dale
                            Montgomery</ref> was appointed Ambassador Extraordinary and
                        Plenipotentiary to Serbia on November 26, 2001. The Republic of Serbia is
                        considered the successor state to the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="appendix">
                    <head>Resources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-serbia/"
                                >Serbia</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/serbia/">Serbia</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="/countries/kingdom-of-yugoslavia">Recognitions and
                                Relations, Yugoslavia</ref>
                        </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
