<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: South Africa</title>
                <title type="short">South Africa</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>On May 31, 1910, four colonies were joined together to create the Union of
                        <placeName key="za">South Africa</placeName>, a self-governing Dominion in
                    the British Empire. While the new nation was sovereign when it came to its
                    domestic affairs, the United Kingdom maintained control over its relations with
                    the wider world. Over the next two decades, South Africa gradually gained
                    control over its external policy. The Balfour Declaration of 1926, issued at the
                    end of the Imperial Conference held in London that year, recognized that the
                    United Kingdom and the Dominions were <quote>“autonomous Communities within the
                        British Empire, equal in status, in no way subordinate one to another in any
                        aspect of their domestic or external affairs.”</quote> In December 1931, the
                    United Kingdom approved the Statute of Westminster, codifying this relationship.<figure>
                        <graphic url="south-africa-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of South Africa</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of South African Independence, <date when="1929"
                            >1929</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Union of South Africa on November 5, 1929,
                        when President <persName>Herbert Hoover</persName> accepted the credentials
                        of <persName>Eric Hendrik Louw</persName> as Envoy Extraordinary and
                        Minister Plenipotentiary of the Union of South Africa.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the South African Legation in
                        the United States, <date when="1929">1929</date>.</head>
                    <p>On November 5, 1929, the Union of South Africa established its legation in
                        Washington with the presentation of the credentials of Eric Hendrik Louw as
                        Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of the Union of South
                        Africa to the Government of the United States.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of U.S. Legation in South Africa, <date when="1929"
                            >1929</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 19, 1929, the United States established a legation in <placeName
                            key="cape-town">Cape Town</placeName> by appointing <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/totten-ralph-james">Ralph J.
                            Totten</ref>, who was serving as Consul General, as Minister Resident;
                        Totten presented his credentials as Minister Resident to the Government of
                        the Union of South Africa on February 18, 1930. On June 20, 1930, the
                        legation was relocated to <placeName key="pretoria">Pretoria</placeName> and
                        Totten was appointed Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to the
                        Government of the Union of South Africa. Totten presented his credentials to
                        the Government of the Union of South Africa on September 8, 1930.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of Legations to Embassy Status, <date when="1949"
                        >1949</date>.</head>
                    <p>On December 21, 1948, the Department of State announced the elevation of the
                        South African and U.S. legations to embassy stratus, effective as of the
                        date of the presentation of ambassadorial credentials. On March 3, 1949,
                            <persName>H. T. Andrews</persName> presented his credentials as
                        Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary of the Union of South Africa to
                        President <persName>Harry S. Truman</persName>. On March 23, 1949, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/winship-north">North Winship</ref>
                        presented his credentials as Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary of
                        the United States to the Government of the Union of South Africa.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The Republic of South Africa, <date when="1961">1961</date>.</head>
                    <p>On May 31, 1961, the Government of the Union of South Africa declared that
                        henceforth the country would be a republic. On that same day, U.S.
                        Ambassador <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/satterthwaite-joseph-charles">Joseph
                            C. Satterthwaite</ref> was reaccredited to the newly-formed Republic of
                        South Africa through the transmission of new credentials to the South
                        African Foreign Office.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <!--<bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-south-africa/">South Africa</ref></bibl>-->
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/south-africa/">South
                            Africa</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
