<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: South Sudan</title>
                <title type="short">South Sudan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2011</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Tiffany Cabrera, November 2011</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Since achieving its independence from British and Egyptian rule in 1956, Sudan
                    experienced recurring civil wars primarily between North and South. The 2005
                    signing of the Comprehensive Peace Agreement (CPA) officially ended the
                    North-South conflict and set the date for a referendum on South Sudan’s
                    self-determination in January 2011. Voters overwhelmingly chose independence and
                    the Republic of South Sudan declared independence on July 9, 2011. The United
                    States recognized the Republic of South Sudan that same day.<figure>
                        <graphic url="south-sudan-flag.png"/>
                        <head>Flag of South Sudan</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Recognition, <date when="1882">2011</date>.</head>
                    <p>President Barack Obama declared that the United States formally recognized
                        the Republic of South Sudan as a sovereign and independent state on July 9,
                        2011. This followed the historic January referendum on self-determination
                        for Southern Sudan, demonstrating full implementation of the 2005
                        Comprehensive Peace Agreement between the North and South.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_relations">
                <head>Consular Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Consular Relations, <date when="2005">2005</date>.</head>
                    <p>After the signing of the Comprehensive Peace Agreement in 2005, the U.S.
                        government established a consulate in Juba on November 11, 2005, to
                        reinforce its partnership with the South Sudanese people.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="2011-07-09"
                        >2011</date>.</head>
                    <p>Following its declaration of independence, the United States established full
                        diplomatic relations with the Republic of South Sudan, upgrading the U.S.
                        Consulate General in Juba to a U.S. Embassy on July 9, 2011. The United
                        States appointed Ambassador Barrie Walkley, the U.S. Consul General in Juba,
                        to serve as Chargé d’Affaires pending the appointment of a U.S. Ambassador
                        to Juba. Susan D. Page was confirmed as the Ambassador Designate to the
                        Republic of South Sudan on October 18, 2011.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Consulate Elevated to Embassy, <date when="2011-07-09">2011</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Consulate at Juba was elevated to Embassy status on July 9, 2011
                        when U.S. Ambassador to the United Nations Susan Rice officially transformed
                        the U.S. Consulate General into the United States Embassy in the new
                        Republic of South Sudan.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-south-sudan/">South
                            Sudan</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/south-sudan/">South
                            Sudan</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
