<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Suriname</title>
                <title type="short">Suriname</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>
                    <placeName key="sr">Suriname</placeName> was a Dutch colony on the northern
                    coast of South America dating from 1667. Beginning in 1951, Suriname was
                    accorded increasing degrees of autonomy, and was finally granted independence in
                    1975 from the <ref target="/countries/netherlands">Netherlands</ref>. In 1980
                    the democratically elected parliamentary government was overthrown; a regime run
                    by the military under <persName>Desi Bouterse</persName> was installed in its
                    place. Since the reestablishment of a democratic, elected government in 1991,
                    the United States has maintained positive and mutually beneficial relations with
                    Suriname.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="suriname-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Suriname</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Suriname Independence, <date when="1975"
                        >1975</date>.</head>
                    <p>On November 25, 1975, a ceremony to proclaim Suriname independence was held
                        in the Suriname capital of <placeName key="paramaribo"
                            >Paramaribo</placeName>. The U.S. Secretary of the Navy represented the
                        United States at the ceremony. That same day, U.S. President
                            <persName>Gerald Ford</persName> wrote a letter to Suriname President
                            <persName>Johan Henri Eliza Ferrier</persName> in which he extended the
                        recognition of Suriname by the United States Government and stated that he
                        hoped for the prompt establishment of diplomatic relations between the two
                        countries.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in
                        Suriname, <date when="1975">1975.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The United States Diplomatic relations and the American Embassy in Paramaribo
                        were established on November 25, 1975, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/flanagin-robert-l">Robert L.
                            Flanagin</ref> as Chargé d'Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                        interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="appendix">
                    <head>Resources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/1893.htm ">Suriname</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                target="http://www.state.gov/p/wha/ci/ns/index.htm ">Suriname</ref>
                        </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
