<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Syria</title>
                <title type="short">Syria</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States became independent, <placeName key="sy">Syri</placeName>a
                    was part of the Ottoman Empire and its foreign relations were conducted through
                    the Sultan’s government at Istanbul (Constantinople). In 1922, after the
                    collapse of the Ottoman Empire, the <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/league"
                        >League of Nations</ref> approved a French Mandate for Syria and Lebanon,
                    which gave France exclusive control over their foreign relations. The United
                    States appointed <persName>George Wadsworth</persName> as “Agent and Consul
                    General” on October 9, 1942, to provide a quasi-diplomatic presence in Damascus
                    until the United States determined that Syria achieved effective independence in 1944.<figure>
                        <graphic url="syria-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Syria</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Syrian Independence, <date when="1944"
                        >1944</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Syria as an independent state on September 8,
                        1944, when the Syrian Minister of Foreign Affairs, <persName>Jamil Mardam
                            Bey</persName>, informed the United States that Syria fully recognized
                        and would protect existing rights of the United States and its nationals.
                        This Syrian assurance was in response to a letter sent on September 7, 1944,
                        by the American Diplomatic Agent and Consul General in Syria that offered
                        “full and unconditional recognition” upon receipt of such written
                        assurances.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Formation and Recognition of the United Arab Republic, <date when="1958"
                            >1958</date>.</head>
                    <p>Egypt and Syria united to form a new state, the United Arab Republic (UAR),
                        on February 22, 1958. The United States recognized the UAR on February 25,
                        1958, when U.S. Ambassador to Egypt <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hare-raymond-arthur">Raymond
                            Hare</ref> delivered a note to that effect to the UAR Ministry of
                        Foreign Affairs in Cairo.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Dissolution of the United Arab Republic and Recognition of Syria, <date
                            when="1961">1961</date>.</head>
                    <p>Syria seceded from the UAR on September 28, 1961, and reestablished the
                        independent Syrian Arab Republic (<placeName>Egypt</placeName> continued to
                        be known officially as the “United Arab Republic” until 1971). The United
                        States recognized Syria on October 10, 1961, in a press release on that
                        date.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Legation in Syria,
                            <date when="1944">1944</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established diplomatic relations with Syria when <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/wadsworth-george">George
                            Wadsworth</ref> presented his credentials as Envoy Extraordinary and
                        Minister Plenipotentiary on November 17, 1944. Wadsworth had been serving as
                        Diplomatic Agent and Consul General to Syria and
                            <placeName>Lebanon</placeName> while the United States considered them
                        to be “semi-independent” states.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations with Syria Relations Ended, Embassy in Damascus
                        Downgraded, and Relations Established with the United Arab Republic, <date
                            when="1958">1958</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations with Syria ended and the American Embassy in <placeName
                            key="damascus">Damascus</placeName> was reclassified as a Consulate
                        General on February 25, 1958, after Syria joined Egypt to form the new
                        state, the United Arab Republic. The UAR’s capital was established at Cairo,
                        where the United States maintained its embassy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Reestablishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in Syria,
                            <date when="1961">1961</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States reestablished diplomatic relations with the Syrian Arab
                        Republic and the American Consulate General at Damascus was raised to
                        Embassy Status on October 10, 1961, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/knight-ridgway-brewster">Ridgway B.
                            Knight</ref> as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.
                        This action followed Syrian withdrawal from the United Arab Republic on
                        September 28, 1961.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed, <date when="1967">1967</date>.</head>
                    <p>Syria severed diplomatic relations with the United States on June 6, 1967 in
                        the wake of the <ref target="/milestones/1961-1968/arab-israeli-war-1967"
                            >June 1967 Arab-Israeli War</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of U.S. Interests Section, <date when="1974"
                        >1974</date>.</head>
                    <p>A U.S. Interests Section in Syria was established on February 8, 1974, in the
                        Italian Embassy with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/scotes-thomas-james">Thomas J.
                            Scotes</ref> as Principal Officer.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Reestablishment of Diplomatic Relations and American Embassy, <date
                            when="1974">1974</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations and the American Embassy in Damascus were reestablished
                        on June 16, 1974, with Scotes as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                            interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <!--<bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-syria/">Syria</ref></bibl>-->
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/syria/">Syria</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back> </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
