<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Texas</title>
                <title type="short">Texas*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Chris Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Colonized in the eighteenth century by the Spanish, the Republic of Texas
                    declared its independence from Mexico on March 2, 1836. The Republic of Texas
                    was not recognized by the United States until a year later in 1837.</p>
                <p>The question of incorporating Texas into the United States was an issue that
                    strained U.S. relations with Mexico during the 1840s. Although Texas was annexed
                    by the United States in late December 1845, the formal transfer ceremony
                    occurred on February 19, 1846, thus officially ending diplomatic relations
                    between the Republic of Texas and the United States.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Texan Independence, <date when="1837"
                        >1837</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Texan independence on March 3, 1837, when U.S.
                        President <persName>Andrew Jackson</persName> nominated <persName>Alcée La
                            Branche</persName> as Minister to Texas.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Consulate at Galveston</head>
                    <p>Prior to Texan independence, a consulate was established at Galveston, and
                        Joseph Washington Eliot Wallace was confirmed as consul on March 29, 1830.
                        Additional consulates existed at the following locations: </p>
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Goliad: Earliest Date: January 9, 1835. No extant latest date. </item>
                        <item>Matagorda: Earliest Date: June 26, 1838. No extant latest date. </item>
                        <item>Sabine: Earliest Date: March 21, 1843. Latest date: December 29, 1845 </item>
                        <item>Velasco (Freeport) Earliest Date: October 12, 1837. No extant latest
                            date. </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the U.S. Legation in Houston,
                            <date when="1837">1837</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations began when the U.S. Secretary of State accepted the
                        credentials of William Harris Wharton, Texan Minister to the United States,
                        on March 6, 1837. Alcée La Branche, the appointed Chargé d’Affaires of the
                        U.S. Legation in Houston, then functioning as the seat of government,
                        presented his credentials sometime between October 23 and 27, 1837.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Relations, <date when="1846">1846</date>.</head>
                    <p>Although Texas entered the United States as a state on December 29, 1845,
                        relations formally ended during the transfer of Texan sovereignty to the
                        United States on February 19, 1846. Despite this, <persName>Andrew J.
                            Donelson</persName>, the last U.S. Chargé D’Affaires, left his post on
                        or shortly after August 9, 1845.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Claims Convention, <date when="1838">1838</date>.</head>
                    <p>On April 11, 1838, the U.S. concluded a Claims Convention with the Republic
                        of Texas. This agreement was signed by Alcée La Branche, the U.S. Chargé
                        d’Affaires near the Republic of Texas and R.A. Irion, the Secretary of State
                        of the Republic of Texas, and served to set Texan indemnity to the United
                        States for injuries suffered by U.S. Citizens by Texan authorities as well
                        as indemnity to compensate U.S. merchants for the capture, seizure, and
                        confiscation of two U.S. vessels.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention for Marking Boundary, <date when="1838">1838</date>.</head>
                    <p>On April 25, 1838, the U.S. and the Republic of Texas signed a convention to
                        mark the boundary between the two states.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Summary.</head>
                    <p>One of the issues at play in the interactions between the United States and
                        the Republic of Texas was the eventual annexation of Texas by the U.S. There
                        were two main difficulties with the issue of Texas joining the United States
                        at the time: first, incorporating Texas into the Union might provoke Mexico;
                        and second, Texas wished to join as a slave state.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Disrupting Relations With Mexico.</head>
                    <p>On August 23, 1843, Mexican Foreign Minister Bocanegra informed U.S. Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Mexico, Waddy Thompson, that
                        U.S. annexation of Texas would be grounds for war. On March 1, 1845, U.S.
                        President John Tyler signed a congressional joint resolution favoring the
                        annexation of Texas. On March 4, 1845, U.S. President James Knox Polk noted
                        his approval of the “reunion” of the Republic of Texas with the United
                        States in his inaugural address. In response, the Mexican Minister of
                        Foreign Affairs informed U.S. Minister to Mexico, Wilson Shannon, on March
                        28, 1845, that Mexico was severing diplomatic relations with the United
                        States. In December 1845 Texas was admitted to the union as the
                        twenty-eighth state. In April 1846, Mexican troops attacked what they
                        perceived to be invading U.S. forces that had occupied territory claimed by
                        both Mexico and the United States, and on May 13, the U.S. Congress declared
                        war against Mexico.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Slavery and Cotton.</head>
                    <p>Another issue raised by the debate over Texan annexation was that of slavery.
                        Since the early nineteenth century, Texas was a producer of cotton. It was
                        also dependent upon slave labor to produce its cotton. The question of
                        whether or not the United States should annex Texas came at a time of
                        increased tensions between the Northern and Southern states of the Union
                        over the legality and morality of slavery; thus the possibility of admitting
                        Texas as another slave state proved to be contentious.</p>
                    <p>Additionally, there was another issue raised by the Texas-cotton nexus: that
                        of the market for raw cotton. One of the largest export markets for North
                        American raw cotton in the mid-nineteenth century was to Great Britain. As
                        long as Texas remained an independent state, it could give Southern U.S.
                        cotton plantation owners competition in terms of setting prices – to force
                        them to be more competitive.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Samuel Flagg Bemis, <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of State
                            and Their Diplomacy</hi>, (New York: Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.,
                        1963), Volume V.</bibl>
                    <bibl>George Pierce Garrison, ed. <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic Correspondence of
                            the Republic of Texas.</hi> Austin, 1908,</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ethel Zivley Ratiler. “Recognition of the Republic of Texas by the United
                        States,” <hi rend="italic">Southwestern Historical Quarterly</hi>, 13:3,
                        155-256.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Richard Bruce Winders. <hi rend="italic">Crisis in the Southwest: The
                            United States, Mexico, and the Struggle over Texas.</hi> Wilmington:
                        Scholarly Resources, 2002. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
