<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Tonga</title>
                <title type="short">Tonga</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Aaron Marrs, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The Tongan islands were united in 1845 under King <persName>George Tupou
                        I</persName> and became a constitutional monarchy in 1875. Although Tonga
                    was recognized by the United States in 1886, it entered into a protectorship
                    agreement with the British Empire in 1900. This agreement maintained Tongan
                    autonomy, but placed sole control of its foreign affairs with the British
                    Foreign Office. <placeName xml:id="to">Tonga</placeName> hosted U.S. military
                    forces during <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945">World War II</ref> in
                        <placeName xml:id="tongatapu">Tongatapu</placeName>, which became a major
                    transit hub for the Allies’ shipping lanes during the war. After Tonga withdrew
                    from its British protectorate agreement in 1970, the United States accredited
                    the U.S. Ambassador to <placeName>New Zealand</placeName>,
                        <placeName>Fiji</placeName>, and <placeName>Western Samoa</placeName> to
                    Tonga. Since then, the United States and Tonga have enjoyed close cooperation on
                    a range of international issues. The United States does not have an embassy in
                    the Tongan capital of Nuku’alofa; instead, since 1979 the U.S. Ambassador to
                    Fiji is also accredited to Tonga and resident in Suva. <figure>
                        <graphic url="tonga-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Tonga</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Tonga, <date when="1886">1886</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States and the King of Tonga signed a Treaty of Amity, Commerce
                        and Navigation in Nuku’alofa on October 2, 1886. The treaty entered into
                        force in 1888 but was terminated on July 28, 1920, by the British Foreign
                        Office on behalf of the King of Tonga.</p>
                    <p>In 1900 when Tonga became a protectorate of Great Britain, the British
                        Foreign Office undertook control over all Tongan external affairs, and the
                        U.S. ceased to appoint consul-generals to Nuku’alofa.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Tongan Independence, <date when="1972"
                        >1972</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States appointed <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/franzheim-kenneth">Kenneth Franzheim
                            II</ref> as Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary to Tonga on
                        October 4, 1972, thus recognizing Tongan independence and sovereignty.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <p>The first U.S. Consul-General to Nuku’alofa, <persName>Church
                        Howe</persName>, was appointed on June 30, 1897 and replaced by
                            <persName>Luther W. Osborn</persName> on July 26, 1897. The post was
                        resident in Apia, Samoa, and closed in 1901.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1972">1972.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Tonga became an independent and sovereign nation within the British
                        Commonwealth on June 4, 1970. On October 4, 1972, the United States
                        accredited its Ambassador to New Zealand, Fiji, and Western Samoa, Kenneth
                        Franzheim II, to Tonga; however, Franzheim resigned from his post in
                        Wellington before he presented his credentials to Tonga on November 6, 1972.
                        He resigned as U.S. Ambassador to Tonga shortly thereafter in January
                        1973.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Change from Wellington to Suva, <date when="1979">1979.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Beginning in 1979, the U.S. Ambassador to Fiji has also been accredited to
                        Tonga, resident in Suva. On April 11, 1979, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/condon-john-peter">John P.
                            Condon</ref> presented his credentials to the Tongan government.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties_agreements">
                <head>Treaties &amp; Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of 1886 Terminated, <date when="1920">1920</date>.</head>
                    <p>The treaty signed in 1886 was terminated on July 28, 1920, with the exception
                        of the article which allowed ships of war from each country to enter the
                        other’s ports.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key_diplomatic_events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Friendship and Protectorship, <date when="1900"
                        >1900</date>.</head>
                    <p>In 1900 the King of Tonga signed a Treaty of Friendship and Protectorship
                        with Great Britain. The treaty delegated sole authority of Tongan foreign
                        relations to the British Foreign Office, although it maintained Tongan
                        autonomy. Subsequent amendments to this agreement gave further powers over
                        internal Tongan affairs to the British, thus eroding the true autonomy of
                        Tonga.</p>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Entry of Tonga into the British Commonwealth, <date when="1970"
                                >1970</date>.</head>
                        <p>On June 4, 1970, Tonga officially withdrew from its protectorship
                            agreement with Great Britain and instead became a part of the British
                            Commonwealth.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/16092.htm">Tonga</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/p/eap/ci/tn/index.htm">Tonga</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back> </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
