<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Trinidad and
                    Tobago</title>
                <title type="short">Trinidad and Tobago</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and Written by Lindsay Krasnoff, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Under first Spanish and then British colonial rule, the two islands that
                    constitute the state of <placeName xml:id="tt">Trinidad and Tobago</placeName>
                    achieved independence in 1962. At that time, it joined the British Commonwealth.
                    Since the 1960s, Trinidad and Tobago has emerged as one of the most
                    industrialized countries in the English-speaking Caribbean, and is an active
                    member of the international community. Today, the United States and Trinidad and
                    Tobago enjoy cordial relations.<figure>
                        <graphic url="trinidad-tobago-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Trinidad and Tobago</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of the Independence of Trinidad and Tobago, <date
                            when="1962">1962</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized Trinidad and Tobago the same day that it became
                        independent on August 31, 1962, by establishing the U.S. Embassy in
                            <placeName xml:id="port-of-spain">Port-of-Spain</placeName>. William
                        Henry Hastie, a judge on the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit,
                        led the U.S. delegation at the independence ceremonies.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1962"
                        >1962</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established diplomatic relations with Trinidad and Tobago
                        on August 31, 1962, when it recognized the island nation’s independence.
                        That same day, the United States established the American Embassy in
                        Port-of-Spain, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/christensen-william-harold">William H.
                            Christensen</ref> as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                        interim</hi>. The first U.S. Ambassador to Trinidad and Tobago was <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/miner-robert-graham">Robert G.
                            Miner</ref> who presented his credentials on December 1, 1962.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/35638.htm">Trinidad and
                            Tobago</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/p/wha/ci/td/">Trinidad and Tobago</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
