<?xml-stylesheet?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Tunisia</title>
                <title type="short">Tunisia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>At the time of U.S. independence, Tunis was a state with nominal dependence to
                    the Ottoman Empire, but which was able to conduct its own foreign policy and
                    conclude treaties. The United States has maintained official representation in
                    Tunis almost continuously since 1795, and a Treaty of Peace and Friendship with
                        <placeName xml:id="tn">Tunisia</placeName> was signed in 1797.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="tunisia-flag.jpg"/>
                    <head>Modern Flag of Tunisia</head>
                </figure>
                <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                    <head>Recognition</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Tunisian Recognition of the United States, <date when="1795"
                                >1795</date>.</head>
                        <p>Tunisian recognition of the United State occurred at some time in
                            mid-1795, when Tunisian authorities accepted the appointment of an
                            American consular representative for Tunis. At the time,
                                <persName>Joseph Donaldson</persName> held U.S. consular authority
                            over all the Barbary States, and was named Consul for Tunis on March 28,
                            1795, but remained at post in Algiers. <persName>Joseph Étienne
                                Famin</persName>, a French merchant at Tunis, was deputized to act
                            as U.S. consular official. Famin also established a truce between the
                            United States and the Tunisian government which took effect on June 15,
                            1796. He subsequently was empowered to negotiate a formal Treaty of
                            Peace and Friendship on behalf of the United States with the Bey of
                            Tunis, which was signed on or around August 28, 1797.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Tunisia under French Control, 1881-1956.</head>
                        <p>After a period of increasing political and economic influence in Tunisia,
                            the French government established control over Tunisia by the Treaty of
                            Bardo on May 12, 1881. The La Marsa Convention, signed June 8, 1883,
                            explicitly stated that Tunisia was a French protectorate, and ended
                            Tunisian power to conduct international diplomacy.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>U.S. Recognition of Tunisian Independence, 1956.</head>
                        <p>The United States recognized Tunisia’s independence from France on March
                            22, 1956, when U.S. Consul General in Tunisa, <ref
                                target="/departmenthistory/people/hughes-morris-nelson">Morris N.
                                Hughes</ref>, sent an official congratulatory message to Sidi
                            Mohammed Lamine Pasha, Bey of Tunis and the Tunisian Government.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                    <head>Consular Presence</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Consulate at Tunis, <date from="1795" to="1956">1795 to 1956</date>
                            (with interruptions).</head>
                        <p>Consular relations began with the deputization of Joseph Flamin in 1795
                            or 1796. At this time, Joseph Donaldson held U.S. consular authority
                            over all the Barbary States, but remained at post in Algiers. Flamin
                            remained in Tunis after the signing of the August 1, 1797 treaty, until
                            the arrival of William Eaton, who presented his credentials to Hamouda
                            Pasha, Bey of Tunis, on March 15, 1798. The U.S. maintained a consular
                            presence into the Protectorate period, except for several closings. The
                            first closing was from 1882 to 1890, although there is no extant record
                            of an agent until 1894. The Consulate was also temporarily closed from
                            June 30, 1904 until after the confirmation of vice consul Auguste Proux
                            on Ocotber 8, 1904. The consulate closed again after Proux’s retirement,
                            on April 19, 1912. The Consulate was revived again in 1915, but owing to
                            wartime conditions, it was not staffed until the summer of 1916. The
                            Consulate was also closed from late 1942 until spring of 1943. The
                            office was raised to the status of a Consulate General effective May 22,
                            1946. The Consulate General was elevated to the status of U.S. Embassy
                            on June 5, 1956. This status was recognized the next day.</p>
                        <p>Other consulates, with extant dates:</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <placeName xml:id="bizerte">Bizerte</placeName> (Bizerta) (
                                1871-1923 )</item>
                            <item>
                                <placeName xml:id="jerba">Jerba</placeName> (Djerba, Gerba) ( 1871-?
                                )</item>
                            <item>
                                <placeName xml:id="la-goulette">La Goulette</placeName> (Goletta,
                                Halq al-Wadi) ( 1871-? )</item>
                            <item>
                                <placeName xml:id="mahdia">Mahdia</placeName> (Madia, al-Mahdiya,
                                Mahedia, Mehdia) ( 1871-? )</item>
                            <item>
                                <placeName xml:id="monatico">Monatico</placeName>(?)( 1871-?
                                )</item>
                            <item>
                                <placeName xml:id="sfax">Sfax</placeName> (Safaqis) ( 1871-?
                                )</item>
                            <item>
                                <placeName xml:id="sousse">Sousse</placeName> (Susa) ( 1871-?
                                )</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>No Permanent Diplomatic Relations, <date from="1796" to="1881"
                                >1796-1881</date>.</head>
                        <p>Although the United States maintained a consular presence in Tunis from
                            1795, with interruptions, and a Tunisian envoy visited the United States
                            from 1805-1806, no permanent diplomatic relations existed during the
                            period prior to the French Protectorate.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="timeline">
                        <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in
                            Tunisia, <date when="1956">1956</date>.</head>
                        <p>Diplomatic relations were established on June 6, 1956, when U.S. Charge
                            d’Affaires <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hughes-morris-nelson"
                                >Morris N. Hughes</ref> presented his credentials. The U.S.
                            Government designated the opening of the Embassy on June 5.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5439.htm ">Tunisia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/p/nea/ci/c2421.htm">Tunisia</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Irwin, Ray W. <hi rend="italic">The Diplomatic Relations of the United
                            States with the Barbary Powers, 1776-1816.</hi> Chapel Hill: University
                        of North Carolina Press, 1931.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lambert, Frank. <hi rend="italic">The Barbary Wars: American Independence
                            in the Atlantic World.</hi> New York: Hill and Wang, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ling, Dwight L. <hi rend="italic">Tunisia, from Protectorate to
                            Republic.</hi> Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1967.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nelson, Harold D. and Howard C. Reese. <hi rend="italic">Tunisia, a
                            Country Study.</hi> Washington: U.S. Government Printing Office,
                        1979.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
