<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Two Sicilies</title>
                <title type="short">Two Sicilies*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, February 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States declared independence from Great Britain in 1776, the
                    Kingdoms of Naples and Sicily were independent and sovereign states. After 1734
                    they shared the same ruler and were governed by the Bourbon royal family. After
                    Napoleon’s rise to power, the Italian peninsula was invaded by the French in
                    1799. The Bourbons fled to the island of Sicily. Under <persName>Napoleon</persName>, the Kingdom of
                    Naples was ruled first by Napoleon’s brother Joseph and then Napoleon’s
                    brother-in-law <persName>Joachim Murat</persName>. </p>
                <p> Despite the fall of Napoleon in 1814, Murat struck a deal with the Austrians and
                    thus retained his position. Yet, as the Congress of Vienna began that year,
                    Murat doubted that the Austrians would stand by their pledge to allow him to
                    remain on the throne. Ever the opportunist, Murat reconciled with Napoleon and
                    thus benefitted from Napoleon’s return to power. On March 15, 1815, in the
                    attempt to maintain power, Murat called the Italians together in a war of
                    national independence. The surge of patriotism that he expected failed to
                    materialize, and though Murat invaded the peninsula as far north as the Po
                    region, he was eventually defeated by early May 1815. On May 22, 1815, he
                    renounced the throne of the Kingdom of Naples and rule by the Bourbons was
                    restored in the kingdom. When Ferdinand of Bourbon regained his throne in
                    Naples, he decided to consolidate his holdings and out of the two kingdoms of
                    Naples and Sicily he created the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies on December 18,
                    1815. </p>
                <p>The King of Naples recognized the United States in 1796 and diplomatic relations
                    between the two countries were established in 1832. During the process of the
                    Risorgimento (1860-61), the monarchy in Naples and Sicily was toppled and
                    incorporated into the Kingdom of Italy under King Victor Emmanuel II. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Kingdom of Naples (after 1816, Kingdom of the Two Sicilies) Recognition of
                        the United States, <date when="1796">1796</date>.</head>
                    <p> The Kingdom of Naples recognized the United States when it accepted the
                        credentials of U.S. consular agent <persName>John S. M. Matthiew</persName>, who was appointed to
                        the position of U.S. Consul in Naples on May 20, 1796. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Consular Agents</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. consular agent appointed to what became the Kingdom of the Two
                        Sicilies was John S. M. Matthiew on May 20, 1796, who was assigned to
                        Naples. <persName>Frederick Degan</persName> was assigned as consul on March 20, 1805, during
                        Congressional recess. He was confirmed by Congress on January 17, 1806. He
                        was succeeded by Alexander Hammett, appointed on April 7, 1809 and confirmed
                        on June 21, 1809. Hammett was appointed specifically to the King of the Two
                        Sicilies on April 20, 1816. </p>
                    <p> The first Consul of the United States for the island of Sicily was <persName>Joseph
                        Barnes</persName>, who was appointed on February 10, 1802. On January 17, 1806, <persName>Abraham
                        Gibbs</persName> and <persName>John Broadbent</persName> were commissioned as Consuls at the Sicilian cities
                        of Palermo and Messina, respectively. </p>
                    <p>The first representative from the Two Sicilies in the United States was <persName>Count
                        Ferdinando Lucchesi</persName>. On May 30, 1826, his exequatur as Consul General of the
                        Two Sicilies at Washington, D.C. was signed by U.S. President <persName>John Quincy
                        Adams</persName>. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1832">1832</date>.</head>
                    <p> Although the first diplomatic interaction between the United States and the
                        Kingdom of the Two Sicilies occurred with the reception of U.S. Special
                        Minister Plenipotentiary to Naples <persName>William Pinkney</persName> in 1816, this did not
                        result in the establishment of full diplomatic relations at the time.
                        Pinkney was commissioned on April 23, 1816, with the mission to negotiate a
                        treaty to pay reparations to U.S. merchants for items lost during the reign
                        of Murat. Pinkney’s mission was unsuccessful, and in October 1816 he
                        departed for his post at St. Petersburg, Russia. </p>
                    <p> Full diplomatic relations were established when the first U.S. Chargé
                        d’Affaires to the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies <persName>John Nelson</persName> presented his
                        credentials to the King of the Two Sicilies on January 25, 1832. The first
                        U.S. Minister Resident at Naples was <persName>Robert Dale Owen</persName>, who presented his
                        credentials on September 20, 1854. </p>
                    <p>On December 7, 1846, the Chevalier Rocco Martuscelli presented his
                        credentials as the Chargé d’Affairs at Washington of the Kingdom of the Two
                        Sicilies. From then until 1861 the Government of the Two Sicilies was almost
                        continuously represented in the United States by a Chargé d’Affaires. The
                        last of these representatives was <persName>Giuseppe Anfora dei Duchi di Liccignano</persName>,
                        Consul General, who acted as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> from September 24,
                        1860, to December 15, 1861. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Relations, <date when="1861">1861</date>.</head>
                    <p> During the course of the Risorgimento, the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies
                        ceased to exist, thanks to the work of <persName>Giuseppe Garibaldi</persName> who, in 1860,
                        overthrew the Bourbon monarchs and proclaimed a dictatorship on behalf of
                       <persName> Victor Emmanuel II</persName> (the King of Piedmont-Sardinia). </p>
                    <p> The U.S. closed its mission in Naples in November 1860. When the Kingdom of
                        Italy was proclaimed in early 1861, Sicily and Naples were part of the newly
                        constituted nation, and U.S. diplomatic representatives were located in
                        Turin. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Claims Convention, 1832. </head>
                    <p> This convention, also known as the Convention to Terminate the Reclamations
                        of the Government of the Untied States for the Depredations Inflicted upon
                        American Commerce by Murat During the Years 1809, 1810, 1811, and 1812,
                        1832, was signed on October 14, 1832 in Naples by U.S. Chargé d’Affaires
                        near the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies John Nelson Esq. and the Minister
                        Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs for the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies
                        Prince D. Antonio Maria Statella. The objective of this treaty was to allow
                        U.S. merchants to be <quote>“indemnified for losses inflicted upon them by Murat,
                        by the depredations, seizures, confiscations and destruction of their
                        Vessels [sic] and cargoes, during the years 1809, 1810, 1811, and 1812.”</quote>
                        This treaty was deemed obsolete when the Two Sicilies was consolidated into
                        the Kingdom of Italy in 1861. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Arrangement Providing for the Reception in One Payment of the Balance of
                        the Indemnity Remaining Under the Convention of <date when="1832-10-14">October 14, 1832</date>.</head>
                    <p> This agreement, concluded in Washington, D.C., by U.S. Secretary of State
                        John Forsyth and the Sicilian Majesty’s Consul-General at the United States
                        the Chevalier Dominico Mobelli on December 26, 1835, arranged for the
                        payment of the remainder of monies owed to the United States by the 1832
                        agreement. This sum, 1,500,000 Neapolitan ducats, was to be paid to the
                        United States Government on February 8, 1836. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Treaty of Commerce and Navigation, <date when="1845">1845</date>.</head>
                    <p> Negotiated by U.S. Chargé d’Affaires to the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies
                        <persName>William H. Polk</persName> and <persName>Giustino Fortunato</persName>, Minister Secretary of State of the
                        Kingdom of the Two Sicilies, <persName>Michael Gravina</persName> and Requesenez, Minister
                        Secretary of State of the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies, and Antonio Spinelli,
                        Member of the General Consulat and Surintendant-General of the Archives of
                        the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies, the Treaty of Commerce and Navigation was
                        concluded on December 1, 1845, in Naples. The treaty was superseded by the
                        convention of October 1, 1855.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention Relative to Rights of Neutrals at Sea, <date when="1855">1855</date>.</head>
                    <p> Concluded on January 13, 1855, in Naples between the United States and the
                        Kingdom of the Two Sicilies, this convention inscribed principles of the
                        right of neutrals at sea, which was viewed as being <quote>“indispensable
                        conditions of all freedom of navigation and maritime trade.”</quote> The convention
                        was signed by U.S. Minister Resident at Naples <persName>Robert Dale Owen</persName> and <persName>Louis
                        Carafa della Spina</persName>, who was charged with the Foreign Affairs portfolio for
                        the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies. This treaty was superseded by the 1871
                        treaty with Italy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention of Amity, Commerce, Navigation, and Extradition, <date when="1855">1855</date>.</head>
                    <p> The Convention of Amity, Commerce, Navigation, and Extradition signed
                        between the United States and the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies on October 1,
                        1855, was signed in Naples by U.S. Minister Resident to the Kingdom of the
                        Two Sicilies <persName>Robert Dale Owen</persName>, <persName>Louis Carafa della Spina</persName>, charged
                        provisionally with the Portfolio of Foreign Affairs of the Kingdom of the
                        Two Sicilies, <persName>Michael Gravina e Requesnez</persName>, late his Minister Secretary of
                        State, and <persName>Joseph Marius Arpino</persName>, Advocate-General of the Grand Court of
                        Accounts. There was a separate declaration attached to this convention which
                        stipulated that all red and white wines exported from the Kingdom of the Two
                        Sicilies to the United States would not pay other or higher duties that that
                        paid on wines by most favored nations. In reciprocation, U.S. cotton
                        imported into the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies would not be taxed other or
                        higher duties than those of Egypt, Bengal, or other most favored nations.
                        This treaty became obsolete when the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies was
                        absorbed into the Kingdom of Italy in 1861.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Proclamation of the Kingdom of Italy, <date when="1861">1861</date>.</head>
                    <p> The aftermath of the Franco-Austrian War brought about a series of
                        plebiscites in the northern Italian states. By going to the ballot box, the
                        states voted to join Piedmont-Sardinia, with the ultimate goal of unifying
                        the entire peninsula. It should be noted that Piedmont-Sardinia was one of
                        the more powerful states in the peninsula, as well as having one of the most
                        liberal political systems. Garibaldi’s march to “liberate” the Kingdom of
                        the Two Sicilies in 1860 brought the southern peninsula into the fold, and
                        the new Kingdom of Italy was proclaimed on March 17, 1861, with the royal
                        family of Piedmont-Sardinia as the new ruling monarchs of Italy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Italian Independence, <date when="1861">1861</date>.</head>
                    <p> The United States officially recognized the Kingdom of Italy when it
                        accepted the credentials of Chevalier Joseph Bertinatti as Minister
                        Plenipotentiary of the Kingdom of Italy on April 11, 1861.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Compensation.</head>
                    <p> One of the main issues of contention in the early nineteenth century between
                        the United States and the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies was the question of
                        Neapolitan compensation to U.S. merchants for ships and goods seized or
                        confiscated in Neapolitan waters during the period 1809-1812. Such policies
                        were implemented by Murat at the behest of Napoleon. The quest for
                        compensation was, in fact, the original motivation behind the United States
                        Government accrediting William Pinkney as a Special Minister Plenipotentiary
                        to Naples in 1816. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Denis Mack Smith, <hi rend="italic">Modern Italy: A Political
                            History,</hi> (Ann Arbor, Mich.: University of Michigan Press,
                        1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl>William Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements between the United States of America and
                            Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi>, Washington, D.C.: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Howard R. Marraro, <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic Relations Between the
                            United States and the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies. Volume I:
                            1816-1850,</hi> (New York: S.F. Vanni (Ragusa), 1951.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pietro Orsi, <hi rend="italic">Cavour and the Making of Modern Italy,
                            1810-1861,</hi> (New York: G.P. Putnam’s Sons, 1914).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>