<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Uganda</title>
                <title type="short">Uganda</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2008</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Christopher Morrison, March 2008</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The United States recognized Ugandan independence in 1962 by President
                        <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName>. U.S.-Ugandan relations have, except
                    for a period in the 1970s, remained strong. The United States currently works
                    with <placeName xml:id="ug">Uganda</placeName> to promote economic development
                    of its abundant natural resources, and combat public-health risks such as HIV/
                    AIDS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Ugandan Independence, <date when="1962"
                        >1962</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized <placeName>Uganda</placeName> on October 9,
                        1962, in a congratulatory message from President <persName>John F.
                            Kennedy</persName> to Prime Minister A. Milton Obote. Uganda previously
                        had been under British sovereignty.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="uganda-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Uganda</head>
                    </figure>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations and the American Embassy in Uganda,
                            <date when="1962">1962</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on October 9, 1962, when the American
                        consulate general at <placeName xml:id="kampala">Kampala</placeName> was
                        raised to Embassy status with Olcott H. Deming as Chargé d’Affaires <hi
                            rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Closure of American Embassy, <date when="1973">1973</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Embassy at Kampala was closed on November 10, 1973, when all
                        U.S. diplomatic personnel were withdrawn from Uganda. The Department of
                        State later cited as factors that prompted the closure persistent internal
                        security problems, operating difficulties for American programs and
                        personnel, repeated public threats against Embassy officials and other
                        Americans by high Ugandan officials, and finally the abrupt expulsion of the
                        U.S. Marine Security Guard that protected the Embassy. Diplomatic relations
                        were not interrupted and Uganda maintained an embassy in Washington.
                        American interests in Uganda were represented by the Federal Republic of
                        Germany.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Re-establishment of American Embassy, <date when="1979"
                        >1979</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Embassy at Kampala was re-established on June 18, 1979, with
                        David Halstead as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2963.htm">Uganda</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                            target="http://www.state.gov/p/af/ci/ug/index.htm">Uganda</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back> </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
