<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Vietnam</title>
                <title type="short">Vietnam</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Evan Dawley, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>Relations between citizens of the United States and residents of what is today
                    the Socialist Republic of <placeName xml:id="vn">Vietnam</placeName> began
                    during the 19th century, when that region was a colony of the French Empire. For
                    decades interactions were primarily of a commercial nature, with a few other
                    areas of non-official contact. Formal relations began only after Vietnam gained
                    its independence from <ref target="/countries/france">France</ref> following
                    World War II.<figure>
                        <graphic url="vietnam-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Vietnam</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Vietnamese Independence, <date when="1950"
                        >1950</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the State of Viet Nam on February 7, 1950, when
                        the U.S. Department of State made an announcement to that effect. Vietnam
                        previously had been part of Indochina as a Protectorate of France and had
                        become an independent state as part of the French Union in 1949. The State
                        of Viet Nam incorporated all of the territory of contemporary Vietnam.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular_presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Consular Relations, <date when="1907">1907</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established its first full consular post in the French
                        colony of Indochina in the city of Saigon on December 9, 1907. There had
                        been a commercial agent in this city since 1889.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Additional Consular Posts, <date from="1947" to="1957"
                            >1947-57</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established additional consulates as follows: <placeName
                            xml:id="hanoi">Hanoi</placeName> (1947); <placeName xml:id="hue"
                            >Hue</placeName> (1957).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1950">1950.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on February 17, 1950, when the
                        Consulate General at Saigon was raised to Legation status with <ref
                            target="/people/gullion-edmund-asbury">Edmund A. Gullion</ref> as Chargé
                        d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of U.S. Legation to Embassy Status, <date when="1952"
                            >1952.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The United States Legation in Saigon was raised to Embassy status on June 24,
                        1952, when Ambassador <ref target="/people/heath-donald-read">Donald R.
                            Heath</ref> received confirmation of his appointment from the United
                        States Senate. This followed a joint announcement by the Governments of the
                        United States and Vietnam to this effect on June 6, 1952.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations and the North-South Division of Vietnam, <date
                            when="1955">1955.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>As a result of the First Indochina War and the Geneva Conference of 1954 that
                        marked its conclusion, the territory of the State of Vietnam became divided
                        along the 17th parallel, with separate regimes in the North and South. The
                        United States was not a signatory to the Geneva Accords and so did not
                        recognize the Government of <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName>. The United
                        States maintained its Embassy in Saigon and conducted diplomatic relations
                        solely with the Government of <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>, which in
                        1955 <ref target="/1953-1960/DienBienPhu">reorganized itself as the Republic
                            of Vietnam</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Relations Interrupted, <date when="1975">1975.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The United States <ref target="/1969-1976/VietnamWar">closed the Embassy in
                            Saigon and evacuated all Embassy personnel</ref> on April 29, 1975, just
                        prior to the surrender of South Vietnam to North Vietnamese forces.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Liaison Office Opened, <date when="1995">1995.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The United States opened a Liaison Office in Hanoi on January 28, 1995.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Relations Resumed, <date when="1995">1995.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The United States and Vietnam reestablished diplomatic relations on August 5,
                        1995 during Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/people/christopher-warren-minor">Warren Christopher</ref>'s
                        visit to Vietnam, when he and Vietnam's Foreign Minister signed documents
                        agreeing to do so and to open embassies in Hanoi and Washington. Christopher
                        announced that <ref target="/people/anderson-l-desaix">L. Desaix
                            Anderson</ref> would serve as the Chargé d'Affaires a.i. pending the
                        nomination and confirmation of the Ambassador. The opening of Embassy Hanoi
                        took place on August 6.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="appendix">
                    <head>Resources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/4130.htm">Vietnam</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Information <ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/p/eap/ci/vm/index.htm">Vietnam</ref>
                        </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
