<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States' History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Württemberg</title>
                <title type="short">Württemberg*</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Lindsay Krasnoff, February 2010</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>When the United States announced its independence from Great Britain in 1776,
                    Württemberg was a sovereign, independent state. It was raised to the status of
                    kingdom by <persName>Napoleon</persName> (1806) during the <ref target="/1801-1829/NapoleonicWars">Napoleonic Wars</ref> of the early
                    nineteenth century. The 1819 constitution created a bicameral legislature. The
                    first act of mutual recognition between the United States and the Kingdom of
                    Württemberg occurred in 1825, and relations between the two countries expanded
                    through 1871 when the Kingdom of Württemberg joined the German Empire at the
                    close of the Franco-Prussian War. From this point forward, foreign policy of the
                    German Empire was made in Berlin, with the German Kaiser (who was also the King
                    of Prussia) accrediting ambassadors of foreign nations. Relations were severed
                    when the U.S. declared war upon Imperial Germany in 1917.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Mutual Recognition, <date when="1842">1842</date>.</head>
                    <p> The first known act of mutual recognition between the United States and the
                        Kingdom of Württemberg occurred on November 21, 1825, when U.S. Secretary of
                        State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/clay-henry">Henry Clay</ref>
                        granted an exequatur to <persName>Christian Mayer Esq.</persName> to serve
                        as Consul General for the Kingdom of Württemberg at Baltimore. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="consular-presence">
                <head>Consular Presence</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>The first U.S. consulate opened in Württemberg on <date when="1842-10-13">October 13, 1842.</date>
                    </head>
                    <p>The first U.S. consulate opened in Württemberg on October 13, 1842, and
                        closed on March 3, 1843. The U.S. later opened a consulate in Stuttgart on
                        March 3, 1847, which closed in September 1985.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Expansion of Relations, <date when="1868">1868</date>.</head>
                    <p> The relations between the United States and the Kingdom of Württemberg
                        continued to expand through the 1860s. On July 27, 1868, specially
                        accredited U.S. Minister to the Kingdom of Württemberg George Bancroft
                        signed a naturalization treaty with the Kingdom of Württemberg. At the time,
                        Bancroft was also accredited to Prussia and the <ref target="/countries/north-german-union">North German Confederation</ref>
                        and, after 1871, to the German Empire. Yet, although Bancroft was recalled
                        from his position in Berlin in 1874 (at his own request), he was never
                        officially recalled from the court of Württemberg. Years after his 1891
                        death, Bancroft remained listed as the official diplomatic representative of
                        the U.S. in Württemberg. See entry on <ref target="/countries/issues/german-unification">German Unification.</ref>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Cessation of Relations, <date when="1917">1917</date>.</head>
                    <p> On February 3, 1917, U.S. President Woodrow Wilson instructed the Secretary
                        of State to notify the German Ambassador to the United States that all
                        diplomatic relations between the U.S. and the German Empire were severed. As
                        the foreign affairs of Imperial Germany were run out of Berlin and decided
                        upon by the Kaiser, this constituted the severance of relations with
                        Württemberg, as part of the German Empire. On April 6, 1917, Wilson declared
                        war upon Imperial Germany. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaties-agreements">
                <head>Treaties and Agreements</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention Abolishing <hi rend="italic">Droit d’Aubaine</hi> and Taxes on
                        Emigration, <date when="1844">1844</date>.</head>
                    <p> On April 10, 1844, the Convention Abolishing Droit D’Aubaine and Taxes on
                        Emigration was signed by U.S. Minister to Prussia Henry Wheaton and
                        Württemberg’s Chargé d’Affaires to Prussia <persName>Baron de
                            Maucler</persName>. Droit d’aubaine was when a state would confiscate
                        all territory and possessions, moveable or immoveable, of the deceased
                        rather than the deceased heirs receiving the property. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Declaration of Accession to the Convention for the Extradition of
                        Criminals, Fugitive from Justice, of June 16, 1852, Between the United
                        States and Prussia and Other States of the Germanic Confederation, <date when="1853">1853</date>.</head>
                    <p> This declaration, dated October 13 and proclaimed December 27, 1853, was the
                        accession of the Kingdom of Württemberg into the agreement made between the
                        United States and Prussia for the provision of the extradition of criminals
                        in 1852. At the time that the convention was negotiated, it was deemed that
                        any state of the German Confederation who wished to enter into the
                        convention might do so. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Convention as to Naturalization and Extradition, <date when="1868">1868</date>.</head>
                    <p> On July 27, 1868, U.S. Minister to Württemberg <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/bancroft-george">George Bancroft</ref>
                        and Württemberg’s Minister of Foreign Affairs <persName>Charles Baron
                            Varnbüler</persName> signed a convention to regulate citizenship between
                        those who emigrated from the United States to Württemberg and vice versa.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="key-events">
                <head>Key Diplomatic Events</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Württemberg Joins the German Empire, <date when="1871">1871</date>.</head>
                    <p> The Kingdom of Württemberg was one of the founding states of the German
                        Empire, which was proclaimed on January 18, 1871.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>German Unification. </head>
                    <p> Württemberg was one of the states involved in the process of German
                        unification during the mid-nineteenth century. See “<ref target="/countries/issues/german-unification">Unification of German
                            States</ref>” for greater detail.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="issues">
                <head>Issues Relevant to U.S. Foreign Diplomacy</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Trade.</head>
                    <p>In the 1850s there was little serious trade between the United States and
                        Württemberg. As with all of the German states that the United States had
                        treaties with, after Württemberg joined the Second Reich in 1871 there were
                        questions as to whether U.S. officials abided by treaties concluded with
                        Württemberg or with Prussia in dealing with issues of trade, citizenship, or
                        extradition. It was decided that a variety of different circumstances would
                        guide U.S. foreign policy towards German states. First, <quote>“where a
                            State has lost its separate existence, as in the case of Hanover and
                            Nassau, no questions can arise.” </quote>Second, <quote>“where no treaty
                            has been negotiated with the Empire, the treaties with the various
                            States which have preserved a separate existence have been resorted
                            to.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p> Despite the Constitution of the German Empire of 1871, which stipulated that
                        the Empire was responsible for treaties, alliances, and representing the
                        Empire amongst nations, the smaller states still retained the right of
                        legation. This included the right to legislate, to grant exequators to
                        foreign consuls in their territories (though not to send German consuls
                        abroad), and to enter into conventions with foreign nations as long as they
                        did not concern matters already within the jurisdiction of the Empire or the
                        Emperor. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Resources</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>William Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, International
                            Acts, Protocols, and Agreements between the United States of America and
                            Other Powers, 1776-1909</hi>, Washington, D.C.: Government Printing
                        Office, 1910.</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">A Digest of International Law</hi>
                        (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1906).</bibl>
                    <bibl>John Bassett Moore, <hi rend="italic">Four Phases of American
                            Development</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press, 1912).</bibl>
                    <bibl>James J. Sheehan, <hi rend="italic">German History 1770-1866</hi>,
                        (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1989).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>