<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Guide to the United States’ History of Recognition,
                    Diplomatic, and Consular Relations, by Country, since 1776: Yemen</title>
                <title type="short">Yemen</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 2009</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Researched and written by Evan Dawley, February 2009</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="summary">
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>The area that comprises Yemen today has traditionally, since the nineteenth
                    century, been divided in two along a north-south divide. What was once North
                    Yemen was part of the former Ottoman Empire during the nineteenth and early
                    twentieth centuries, while what used to be South Yemen fell under British
                    influence starting in 1839 when the British captured the port of Aden. After the
                    collapse of the Ottoman Empire in 1918, North Yemen became an independent
                    republic while South Yemen continued under the British until Britain withdrew in
                    1967. British authorities left southern Yemen in November 1967 in the wake of an
                    intense terrorist campaign. The two countries were formally unified as the
                    Republic of Yemen in 1990.<figure>
                        <graphic url="yemen-flag.jpg"/>
                        <head>Modern Flag of Yemen</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="recognition">
                <head>Recognition</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Yemen (Northern Yemen), <date when="1946"
                        >1946</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States recognized the Kingdom of the Yemen as a sovereign state on
                        March 4, 1946, in a letter from President Harry Truman to the Imam Yahya,
                        the King of the Yemen.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of Yemen Arab Republic (North Yemen), <date when="1962"
                            >1962</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States was one of the first countries to recognize the Yemen Arab
                        Republic, doing so on December 19, 1962.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>U.S. Recognition of People’s Republic of Southern Yemen, <date when="1967"
                            >1967</date>.</head>
                    <p>Although the People’s Republic of Southern Yemen gained independence on
                        November 30, 1967, the United States did not recognize it until December 7,
                        when the U.S. consul general in Aden, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/eagleton-william-lester-jr">William L.
                            Eagleton, Jr.</ref> informed the new government authorities of the
                        United States’ decision. In 1970, the name of the country was changed to the
                        People’s Democratic Republic of Yemen.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic_relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations with the Kingdom of Yemen (North
                        Yemen), <date when="1946">1946</date>.</head>
                    <p>Diplomatic relations were established on March 4, 1946, when the United
                        States and Yemen agreed to the appointment of an American Special Diplomatic
                        Mission to the Kingdom of the Yemen. <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/eddy-william-alfred">William A.
                            Eddy</ref> was named Chief of this mission and concluded a provisional
                        agreement on relations between the two states on May 4, 1946.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>First U.S. Minister to Kingdom of Yemen (North Yemen), <date when="1946"
                            >1946</date>.</head>
                    <p>On September 30, 1946, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/childs-james-rives">J. Rives
                            Childs</ref> presented his credentials as Envoy Extraordinary and
                        Minister Plenipotentiary to the Kingdom of Yemen (North Yemen). Childs was
                        also accredited to Saudi Arabia and was resident at Jidda.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of American Legation at Taiz (North Yemen), <date
                            when="1959">1959</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation at Taiz was opened to the public as of March 16, 1959,
                        with <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/ferguson-charles-beverly">
                            Charles B. Ferguson</ref> as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                            interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Elevation of American Legation in Taiz (North Yemen) to Embassy Status,
                            <date when="1963">1963</date>.</head>
                    <p>The American Legation at Taiz was raised to Embassy status on January 28,
                        1963. However, from 1962 until 1967 there was no U.S. Minister or Ambassador
                        accredited to the Kingdom of Yemen, which during this time changed its name
                        to the Yemen Arab Republic. The American Embassy was run by the chargé
                        d’affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Movement of American Embassy from Taiz to San’a (North Yemen), <date
                            when="1966">1966</date>.</head>
                    <p>In 1966 the U.S. moved its embassy from Taiz, the old capital, to San’a, the
                        new capital of the Yemen Arab Republic.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Severed, <date when="1967">1967</date>.</head>
                    <p>The Yemen Arab Republic (North Yemen) severed relations with the United
                        States on June 7, 1967 in the wake of the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1961-1968/arab-israeli-war-1967"> Arab-Israeli
                            conflict</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of Diplomatic Relations with People’s Republic of Southern
                        Yemen (South Yemen), <date when="1967">1967</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States established diplomatic relations with the People’s Republic
                        of Southern Yemen the same day that it recognized the Republic’s
                        independence, on December 7, 1967, when it established the U.S. Embassy in
                        Aden. <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/eagleton-william-lester-jr"
                            >William L. Eagleton, Jr.</ref>, served as Chargé d’Affaires <hi
                            rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Establishment of American Embassy in Aden (South Yemen), <date when="1967"
                            >1967</date>.</head>
                    <p>The U.S. Embassy in Aden was established on December 7, 1967, with <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/eagleton-william-lester-jr">William L.
                            Eagleton, Jr.</ref>, as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                            interim</hi>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Severance of Diplomatic Relations, <date when="1969">1969</date>.</head>
                    <p>Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/eagleton-william-lester-jr">William
                            L. Eagleton, Jr.</ref> was in charge of the American Embassy in Aden
                        when the People’s Republic of Southern Yemen severed diplomatic relations
                        with the United States on October 24, 1969.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Closure of Embassy Aden (South Yemen), <date when="1969"
                        >1969</date>.</head>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/keller-edward-eugene-jr">Edward E.
                            Keller, Jr.</ref>, was Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                            interim</hi> when the Embassy was closed on Oct 26, 1969.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Diplomatic Relations Resumed and Reopening of American Embassy San’a,
                            <date when="1972">1972</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States reestablished diplomatic relations with the Yemen Arab
                        Republic after a visit to San’a by U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/rogers-william-pierce">William P.
                            Rogers</ref> in July 1972. At this time, the Embassy in San’a reopened.
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/stein-robert-andrew">Robert A.
                            Stein</ref> served as Chargé d’Affaires <hi rend="italic">ad
                            interim</hi>. U.S. Ambassador William R. Crawford, Jr. presented his
                        credentials on December 19, 1972, and was the first U.S. Ambassador resident
                        in Yemen.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Resumption of Diplomatic Relations with the People’s Democratic Republic
                        of Yemen (South Yemen), <date when="1990">1990</date>.</head>
                    <p>The United States resumed diplomatic relations with the People’s Democratic
                        Republic of Yemen on Apr 30, 1990.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="timeline">
                    <head>Unification of the Yemen Arab Republic and the People’s Democratic
                        Republic of Yemen, <date when="1990">1990</date>.</head>
                    <p>On May 22, 1990, the Yemen Arab Republic and the People’s Democratic Republic
                        of Yemen announced that they would form a united “Republic of Yemen.” The
                        U.S. Embassy in Aden never reopened.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="appendix">
                    <head>Resources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <!--<bibl>Department of State Country Fact Sheet: <ref target="https://www.state.gov/u-s-relations-with-yemen/">Yemen</ref></bibl>-->
                        <bibl>Department of State Country Information: <ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/countries-areas/yemen/">Yemen</ref>
                        </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
